<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

  <sect2 arch="sparc" id="boot-tftp"><title>Booting with TFTP</title>

&boot-installer-intro-net.xml;

<para>

On machines with OpenBoot, simply enter the boot monitor on the
machine which is being installed (see 
<xref linkend="invoking-openboot"/>).
Use the command <userinput>boot net</userinput> to boot from a TFTP
and RARP server, or try <userinput>boot net:bootp</userinput> or
<userinput>boot net:dhcp</userinput> to boot from a TFTP and BOOTP
or DHCP server. Some older OpenBoot revisions require using
the device name, such as <userinput>boot le()</userinput>; these
probably don't support BOOTP nor DHCP.

</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="sparc"><title>Booting from a CD-ROM</title>

&boot-installer-intro-cd.xml;

<para>

Most OpenBoot versions support the <userinput>boot cdrom</userinput>
command which is simply an alias to boot from the SCSI device on ID 6
(or the secondary master for IDE based systems). You may have to use
the actual device name for older OpenBoot versions that don't support
this special command. Note that some problems have been reported on Sun4m
(e.g., Sparc 10s and Sparc 20s) systems booting from CD-ROM.

</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="sparc">
  <title>Booting from Floppies</title>
<para>

To boot from floppy on a Sparc, use 
<informalexample><screen>

Stop-A -> OpenBoot: "boot floppy"

</screen></informalexample>
</para><para>

Be warned that the newer Sun4u (ultra) architecture does not support
floppy booting. A typical error message is <computeroutput>Bad magic
number in disk label - Can't open disk label package</computeroutput>.
Furthermore, a number of Sun4c models (such as the IPX) do not support
the compressed images found on the disks, so also are not supported.

</para><para>

Several Sparcs (e.g. Ultra 10) have an OBP bug that prevents them from
booting (instead of not supporting booting at all). The appropriate
OBP update can be downloaded as product ID 106121 from
<ulink url="http://sunsolve.sun.com"></ulink>.

</para><para>

If you are booting from the floppy, and you see messages such as 
<informalexample><screen>

Fatal error: Cannot read partition
Illegal or malformed device name

</screen></informalexample>
then it is possible that floppy booting is simply not supported on
your machine.

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 arch="sparc"><title>IDPROM Messages</title>
<para>

If you cannot boot because you get messages about a problem with
``IDPROM'', then it's possible that your NVRAM battery, which holds
configuration information for you firmware, has run out.  See the
<ulink url="&url-sun-nvram-faq;">Sun NVRAM FAQ</ulink> for more
information.

</para>
  </sect2>
