<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id: powerpc.xml 11648 2004-03-22 00:37:46Z joeyh $ -->

  <sect2 arch="powerpc"><title>&arch-title; Boot Loaders</title>

  <sect3><title><quote>OldWorld</quote> PowerMacs</title>
<para>

The boot loader for OldWorld Power Macintosh machines is
<command>quik</command>.  You can also use it on CHRP. The installer
will attempt to set up <command>quik</command> automatically at the
Make Hard Disk Bootable step. The setup has been
known to work on 7200, 7300, and 7600 Powermacs, and on some Power
Computing clones.

</para><para>

For beige G3s, a patched <command>quik</command>
<filename>first.b</filename> module is available at <ulink
url="http://www.cpu.lu/~mlan/ftp/quik-first.b-g3"></ulink>.  To apply
the patched module, follow these steps. After booting back into the
installer, switch to console 2. Copy that file to your
<filename>/target/boot</filename> folder, and rename it
<userinput>first.b</userinput> to supercede the
<filename>first.b</filename> that's there. Then run:
<informalexample><screen>

chroot /target /bin/bash
mount -t proc proc /proc
quik -v 
exit

</screen></informalexample>

</para><para>
      
If you want to use <command>BootX</command> to boot into the installed
system, just select your desired kernel in the <filename>Linux
Kernels</filename> folder, un-choose the ramdisk option, and add
a root device corresponding to your installation;
e.g. <userinput>/dev/hda8</userinput>.

</para><para>

A final option for machines where MacOS/<command>BootX</command> is
not desired and <command>quik</command> is not functional, is to patch
the floppy disk image in order to make it into a boot disk. Use
<command>ResEdit</command> in MacOS to edit the System's cmdl
resource, or use a binary editor such as <command>beav</command> to
edit the image directly, to remove the ramdisk arguments and
substitute an appropriate
<userinput>root=/dev/<replaceable>xxx</replaceable></userinput>
argument.  A <ulink url="&url-powerpc-patch-floppy;">perl
script</ulink> is also available for this purpose.

</para><para>

If the machine fails to boot after completing the installation, and
stops with a <prompt>boot:</prompt> prompt, try typing
<userinput>Linux</userinput> followed by &enterkey;. (The default boot
configuration in <filename>quik.conf</filename> is labeled Linux). The
labels defined in <filename>quik.conf</filename> will be displayed if
you press the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key at the <prompt>boot:</prompt>
prompt. You can also try booting back into the installer, and editing
the <filename>/target/etc/quik.conf</filename> placed there by the
Make Hard Disk Bootable step. Clues for dealing with
<command>quik</command> are available at <ulink
url="&url-powerpc-quik-faq;"></ulink>.

</para><para>

To boot back into MacOS without resetting the nvram, type
<userinput>bye</userinput> at the
Open Firmware prompt (assuming MacOS has not been removed from the
machine). To obtain an OpenFirmware prompt, hold down the <keycombo>
<keycap>command</keycap> <keycap>option</keycap> <keycap>o</keycap>
<keycap>f</keycap> </keycombo> keys while cold booting the machine. If
you need to reset the OpenFirmware nvram changes to the MacOS default
in order to boot back to MacOS, hold down the <keycombo>
<keycap>command</keycap> <keycap>option</keycap> <keycap>p</keycap>
<keycap>r</keycap> </keycombo> keys while cold booting the machine.

</para>
   </sect3>

   <sect3><title><quote>NewWorld</quote> PowerMacs</title>
<para>

Newer (mid 1998 and on) PowerMacs use <command>yaboot</command> as
their boot loader. The installer will set up <command>yaboot</command>
automatically, so all you should need to do is run the Make Hard Disk
Bootable step, if that completes successfully then your disk should
now be bootable and OpenFirmware will be set to boot &debian;.

</para><para>

On G4 machines and iBooks, you can hold down the
<keycap>option</keycap> key and get a
graphical screen with a button for each bootable OS, &debian; will be
a button with a small penguin icon.

</para><para>

If you kept MacOS and at some point it changes the OpenFirmware
<envar>boot-device</envar> variable you should reset OpenFirmware to
its default configuration.  To do this hold down the <keycombo>
<keycap>command</keycap> <keycap>option</keycap> <keycap>p</keycap>
<keycap>r</keycap> </keycombo> keys while cold booting the machine.

</para><para>

The labels defined in <filename>yaboot.conf</filename> will be
displayed if you press the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key at the 
<prompt>boot:</prompt> prompt.

</para><para>

Resetting OpenFirmware on G3 or G4 hardware will cause it to boot
&debian; by default (if you correctly partitioned and placed the
Apple_Bootstrap partition first).  If you have &debian; on a SCSI disk
and MacOS on an IDE disk this may not work and you will have to enter
OpenFirmware and set the <envar>boot-device</envar> variable,
<command>ybin</command> normally does this automatically.

</para><para>

After you boot &debian; for the first time you can add any additional
options you desire (such as dual boot options) to
<filename>/etc/yaboot.conf</filename> and run <command>ybin</command>
to update your boot partition with the changed configuration.  Please
read the <ulink url="&url-powerpc-yaboot-faq;">yaboot HOWTO</ulink>
for more information.

</para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
