<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id: i386.xml 11648 2004-03-22 00:37:46Z joeyh $ -->


<!--  This is not set off for i386 only, because many people will have -->
<!--  access to a PC in order to make a floppy for other arches. --> 

  <sect2><title>Writing Disk Images From DOS, Windows, or OS/2</title>

<para condition="workaround-bug-99926">

If you have access to an i386 machine, you can use one of the 
following programs to copy images to floppies.
<!-- links from 99926 info -->

</para><para condition="workaround-bug-99926">

The FDVOL, WrtDsk or RaWrite3 programs can be used under MS-DOS.

</para><para condition="workaround-bug-99926">

<ulink url="http://www.minix-vmd.org/pub/Minix-vmd/dosutil/">
</ulink>

</para><para condition="workaround-bug-99926">

To use these programs, first make sure that you are booted into
DOS. Trying to use these programs from within a DOS box in Windows, or
double-clicking on these programs from the Windows Explorer is
<emphasis>not</emphasis> expected to work.  If you don't know how to
boot into DOS, just hit <keycap>F8</keycap> while booting.

</para><para>

<command>NTRawrite</command> is a freeware contemporary version of
<command>Rawrite/Rawrite3</command> that is compatible with WinNT and
Win2K. It is a self-explanatory GUI application; you select the disk
drive to write to, browse to the disk image you want to place there
and hit the Write button.

</para><para>

<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ntrawrite/"></ulink>

</para>
  </sect2>

<!-- FIXME: Questionable whether or how this will be supported in d-i -->
  <sect2 id="set-lang">
   <title>
     Modifying the Rescue Floppy to Support National Language
   </title>

<para>

The messages shown by the rescue floppy (before loading the Linux
kernel) can be shown in your mother tongue. To achieve this if you are
not an English speaker, after writing the image file, you must copy
the provided message files and a font to the floppy. For MS-DOS and
Windows users there is a batch file <filename>setlang.bat</filename> in the
<filename>dosutils</filename> directory, which copies the correct
files. Simply enter this directory (e.g.
<userinput>cd c:\debian\dosutils</userinput>) within a command prompt
window, and run
<userinput>setlang <replaceable>lang</replaceable></userinput>, 
where <replaceable>lang</replaceable> is a
two-letter code of your language in lower case, for example
<userinput>setlang pl</userinput> to set the language to Polish. 
Currently these language codes are available: 
<informalexample><screen>
&setlang-language-code-list;
</screen></informalexample> 

</para><para>

<!-- TRANSLATORS: Please replace "non localized (English)" -->
<!-- in the following paragraph with "localized (your-language)" -->

Note that the descriptions in this manual assume that you use
non localized (English) installation; otherwise the names of
menus and buttons will differ from what you will see on your screen.
</para>

  </sect2>
