<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id: m68k.xml 11648 2004-03-22 00:37:46Z joeyh $ -->


  <sect2 arch="m68k"><title>Booting from Hard Disk</title>

&boot-installer-intro-hd.xml;

  </sect2>

  <sect2 arch="m68k"><title>Booting from AmigaOS</title>
<para>

In the <command>Workbench</command>, start the Linux installation
process by double-clicking on the <guiicon>StartInstall</guiicon> icon
in the <filename>debian</filename> directory.

</para><para>

You may have to press the &enterkey; key twice after the Amiga
installer program has output some debugging information into a window.
After this, the screen will go grey, there will be a few seconds'
delay. Next, a black screen with white text should come up, displaying
all kinds of kernel debugging information.  These messages may scroll
by too fast for you to read, but that's OK.  After a couple of
seconds, the installation program should start automatically, so you
can continue down at <xref linkend="init-config"/>.

</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="m68k"><title>Booting from Atari TOS</title>
<para>

At the GEM desktop, start the Linux installation process by
double-clicking on the <guiicon>bootstra.prg</guiicon> icon in the
<filename>debian</filename> directory and clicking
<guibutton>Ok</guibutton> at the program options dialog box.

</para><para>

You may have to press the &enterkey; key after the Atari
bootstrap program has output some debugging information into a
window. After this, the screen will go grey, there will be a few
seconds' delay.  Next, a black screen with white text should come up,
displaying all kinds of kernel debugging information. These messages
may scroll by too fast for you to read, but that's OK. After a couple
of seconds, the installation program should start automatically, so
you can continue below at <xref linkend="init-config"/>.

</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="m68k"><title>Booting from 68k MacOS</title>
<para>

At the MacOS desktop, start the Linux installation process by
double-clicking on the <guiicon>Penguin Prefs</guiicon> icon in
the <filename>debian</filename> directory. The
<command>Penguin</command> booter will start up. Go to the
<guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem> item in the
<guimenu>File</guimenu> menu, click the
<guilabel>Kernel</guilabel> tab.  Select the kernel
(<filename>linux.bin</filename>) and ramdisk
(<filename>root.bin</filename>) images in the
<filename>debian</filename> directory by clicking on the corresponding
buttons in the upper right corner, and navigating the file select
dialogs to locate the files. Close the <guilabel>Settings</guilabel>
dialog, save the settings and start the bootstrap using the
<guimenuitem>Boot Now</guimenuitem> item in the
<guimenu>File</guimenu> menu.

</para><para>

The <command>Penguin</command> booter will output some debugging
information into a window. After this, the screen will go grey, there
will be a few seconds' delay. Next, a black screen with white text
should come up, displaying all kinds of kernel debugging
information. These messages may scroll by too fast for you to read,
but that's OK. After a couple of seconds, the installation program
should start automatically, so you can continue below at 
<xref linkend="init-config"/>.

</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="m68k"><title>Booting from a CD-ROM</title>

&boot-installer-intro-cd.xml;

<para>

Currently, the only &arch-title; subarchitecture that
supports CD-ROM booting is the BVME6000. The easiest route In that
case will be to use a 
<ulink url="&url-debian-cd-vendors;">set of Debian CDs</ulink>. 
Simply insert your CD, reboot, and proceed to the next chapter.  

</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="m68k" id="boot-tftp"><title>Booting with TFTP</title>

&boot-installer-intro-net.xml;

<para>

After booting the VMEbus systems you will be presented with the LILO
<prompt>Boot:</prompt> prompt.  At that prompt enter one of the
following to boot Linux and begin installation proper of the Debian
software using vt102 terminal emulation:

<!-- Because the &enterkey; definition uses <keycap>,    -->
<!-- we use <screen> instead of <userinput> in this list -->

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>

type <screen>i6000 &enterkey;</screen> to install a BVME4000/6000

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

type <screen>i162 &enterkey;</screen> to install an MVME162

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

type <screen>i167 &enterkey;</screen> to install an MVME166/167

</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

</para><para>

You may additionally append the string
<screen>TERM=vt100</screen> to use vt100 terminal emulation,
e.g., <screen>i6000 TERM=vt100 &enterkey;</screen>.

</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="m68k" id="boot-from-floppies">
  <title>Booting from Floppies</title>
<para>

For most m68k architectures, booting from a local filesystem is the
recommended method.

</para><para>

Booting from the boot floppy is supported only for Atari and VME
(with a SCSI floppy drive on VME) at this time. 

</para>
 </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="m68k"><title>Macintosh Limitations</title>
<para>

In the case of Macintosh, you must retain the original Mac system and
boot from it. It is <emphasis>essential</emphasis> that, when booting
MacOS in preparation for booting the Penguin linux loader, you must
hold the <keycap>shift</keycap> key down to prevent extensions from
loading. If you
don't use MacOS except for loading linux, you can accomplish the same
thing by removing all extensions and control panels from the Mac's
System Folder. Otherwise extensions may be left running and cause
random problems with the running linux kernel.

</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="m68k"><title>Penguin Boot Parameters</title>
<para>

In the Penguin boot program, choose <guimenu>File</guimenu> -&gt;
<guimenuitem>Settings...</guimenuitem>, then switch to the
<guilabel>Options</guilabel> tab.  Boot parameters may be typed in to
the text entry area.  If you will always want to use these settings,
select <guimenu>File</guimenu> -&gt; <guimenuitem>Save Settings as
Default</guimenuitem>.

</para>
  </sect2>
