<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 16467 untranslated -->

 <sect1 id="installation-media">
 <title>Installation Media</title>

  <sect2 condition="supports-floppy-boot"><title>Floppies</title>

<para>

In many cases, you'll have to do your first boot from floppy disks.
Generally, all you will need is a
high-density (1440 kilobytes) 3.5 inch floppy drive.

</para><para arch="m68k">

Double-density installation floppy images (720 k) are also
provided for Ataris. 

</para><para arch="powerpc">

For CHRP, floppy support is currently broken.

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>CD-ROM/DVD-ROM</title>

<note><para>

Whenever you see <quote>CD-ROM</quote> in this manual, read it like
<quote>CD-ROM or DVD-ROM</quote>, because both technologies are really
the same from the operating system's point of view. (Except some very
old nonstandard neither SCSI nor IDE/ATAPI CD-ROM drives.)

</para></note><para>

CD-ROM based installation is supported for some architectures.
On machines which support bootable CD-ROMs, you should be able to do a
completely
<phrase arch="not-s390">floppy-less</phrase>
<phrase arch="s390">tape-less</phrase>
installation.  Even if your system doesn't
support booting from a CD-ROM, you can use the CD-ROM in conjunction
with the other techniques to install your system, once you've booted
up by other means; see <xref linkend="boot-installer"/>.

</para><para arch="mips">

Mips does currently not support booting off a cdrom. 

</para><para arch="i386"> 

Both SCSI and IDE/ATAPI CD-ROMs are supported.  In addition, all
non-standard CD interfaces supported by Linux are supported by the
boot disks (such as Mitsumi and Matsushita drives).  However, these
models might require special boot parameters or other massaging to get
them to work, and booting off these non-standard interfaces is
unlikely.  The <ulink url="&url-cd-howto;">Linux CD-ROM HOWTO</ulink>
contains in-depth information on using CD-ROMs with Linux.

</para><para arch="i386"> 

Supported are also external USB CD-ROM drives. FireWire devices that
are supported by the ohci1394 and sbp2 drivers may also be useable.

</para><para arch="arm"> 

IDE/ATAPI CD-ROMs are supported on all ARM machines.
On RiscPCs, SCSI CD-ROMs are also supported. 

</para><para arch="mipsel"> 

On DECstations, booting from CD-ROM requires a SCSI CD-ROM drive
capable of working with a logical blocksize of 512 bytes. Many of the
SCSI CD-DROM drives sold for the PC market do not have this
capability. If your CD-ROM drive has a jumper labeled "Unix/PC" or
"512/2048", place it in the "Unix" or "512" position.

</para><para arch="mipsel">

CD 1 contains the installer for the r3k-kn02 subarchitecture
(the R3000-based DECstations 5000/1xx and 5000/240 as well as
the R3000-based Personal DECstation models), CD 2 the
installer for the r4k-kn04 subarchitecture (the R4x00-based
DECstations 5000/150 and 5000/260 as well as the Personal DECstation
5000/50).

</para><para arch="mipsel">

To boot from CD, issue the command <userinput>boot
<replaceable>#</replaceable>/rz<replaceable>id</replaceable></userinput>
on the firmware prompt, where <replaceable>#</replaceable> is the
number of the TurboChannel device from which to boot (3 on most
DECstations) and <replaceable>id</replaceable> is the SCSI ID of the
CD-ROM drive.  If you need to pass additional parameters, they can
optionally be appended with the following syntax:

</para><para arch="mipsel">

<userinput>boot
<replaceable>#</replaceable>/rz<replaceable>id</replaceable>
param1=value1 param2=value2 ...</userinput>

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Hard Disk</title>

<para>

Installation system booting from a hard disk is another option for
many architectures.

</para><para arch="m68k">

In fact, installation from your local disk is the preferred
installation technique for most &architecture; machines.

</para><para arch="sparc">

Although the &arch-title; does not allow booting from SunOS 
(Solaris), you can install from a SunOS partiton (UFS slices).

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 condition="bootable-usb"><title>USB Memory Stick</title>

<para>

Many Debian boxes need their floppy and/or CD-ROM drives only for
setting up the system and for rescue purposes. If you operate some
servers, you will probably already have thought about omitting those
drives and using an USB memory stick for installing and (when
necessary) for recovering the system. This is also useful for small
systems which have no room for unnecessary drives.

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Network</title>

<para condition="supports-tftp">

You can also <emphasis>boot</emphasis> your system over the network.
<phrase arch="mips">This is the preferred installation technique for
Mips.</phrase>

</para><para condition="supports-nfsroot">

Diskless installation, using network booting from a local area network
and NFS-mounting of all local filesystems, is another option &mdash;
you'll probably need at least &minimum-memory-with-nfsroot; of RAM for
a diskless installation.

</para><para>

After the operating system kernel is installed, you can install the
rest of your system via any sort of network connection (including
PPP after installation of the base system), via FTP, HTTP, or NFS.

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Un*x or GNU system</title>

<para>

If you are running other Unix-like system, you could use it to install
&debian; without using the &d-i; described in the rest of the
manual. This kind of install may be useful for users with otherwise
unsupported hardware or on hosts which can't afford downtimes.  If you
are interested in this technique, skip to the <xref
linkend="linux-upgrade"/>.

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Supported Storage Systems</title>

<para>

The Debian boot disks contain a kernel which is built to maximize the
number of systems it runs on.  Unfortunately, this makes for a larger
kernel, which includes many drivers that won't be used for your
machine (see <xref linkend="kernel-baking"/> to learn how to
build your own kernel).  Support for the widest possible range of
devices is desirable in general, to ensure that Debian can be
installed on the widest array of hardware.

</para><para arch="i386">

Generally, the Debian installation system includes support for
floppies, IDE drives, IDE floppies, parallel port IDE devices, SCSI
controllers and drives.  The file systems supported include MINIX,
FAT, Win-32 FAT extensions (VFAT), among others (note that NTFS is not
supported by the installation system; you can add it later, as
described in <xref linkend="kernel-baking"/>).

</para><para arch="i386">

The disk interfaces that emulate the ``AT'' hard disk interface which
are often called MFM, RLL, IDE, or ATA are supported.  Very old 8 bit
hard disk controllers used in the IBM XT computer are supported only
as a module. SCSI disk controllers from many different manufacturers
are supported. See the 
<ulink url="&url-hardware-howto;">Linux Hardware Compatibility HOWTO</ulink> 
for more details.

</para><para arch="i386">

Not supported are IDE SCSI drives and some SCSI controllers, including
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>

EATA-DMA protocol compliant SCSI Host Adapters like the SmartCache
III/IV, SmartRAID controller families and the DPT PM2011B and PM2012B
controllers.

</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>

The 53c7 NCR family of SCSI controllers (but 53c8 and 5380 controllers
are supported)

</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para><para arch="m68k">

Pretty much all storage systems supported by the Linux kernel are
supported by the Debian installation system.  Note that the current
Linux kernel does not support floppies on the Macintosh at all, and
the Debian installation system doesn't support floppies for Amigas.
Also supported on the Atari is the Macintosh HFS system, and AFFS as a
module.  Macs support the Atari (FAT) file system.  Amigas support the
FAT file system, and HFS as a module.

</para><para arch="sparc"> 

Any storage system supported by the Linux kernel is also supported by
the boot system. The following SCSI drivers are supported in the default
kernel:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>

Sparc ESP

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

PTI Qlogic,ISP

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Adaptec AIC7xxx

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

NCR and Symbios 53C8XX

</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

IDE systems (such as the UltraSPARC 5) are also supported. See 
<ulink url="&url-sparc-linux-faq;">Linux for SPARC Processors FAQ</ulink> 
for more information on SPARC hardware supported by the Linux kernel.

</para><para arch="alpha">

Any storage system supported by the Linux kernel is also supported by
the boot system.  The following SCSI drivers are supported in the default
kernel:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>

Qlogic ISP

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

NCR and Symbios 53c8xx

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Adaptec AIC7xxx

</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

IDE disks are also supported.  Note, however, that on many systems,
the SRM console is unable to boot from IDE drives, and the Jensen is
unable to boot from floppies.  (see 
<ulink url="&url-jensen-howto;"></ulink> 
for more information on booting the Jensen)

</para><para arch="powerpc"> 

Any storage system supported by the Linux kernel is also supported by
the boot system.  Note that the current Linux kernel does not support
floppies on CHRP systems at all. 

</para><para arch="hppa">

Any storage system supported by the Linux kernel is also supported by
the boot system.  Note that the current Linux kernel does not support
the floppy drive.

</para><para arch="mips">

Any storage system supported by the Linux kernel is also supported by
the boot system.

</para><para arch="s390">

Any storage system supported by the Linux kernel is also supported by
the boot system.  This means that FBA and ECKD DASDs are supported with
the old Linux disk layout (ldl) and the new common S/390 disk layout (cdl).

</para>

  </sect2>

 </sect1>
