<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 11648 untranslated -->

 <sect1 condition="bootable-disk" id="boot-drive-files">
 <title>Preparing Files for Hard Disk Booting</title>
<para>

The installer may be booted using boot files placed on an
existing hard drive partition, either launched from another operating
system or by invoking a boot loader directly from the BIOS.

</para><para>

A full, "pure network" installation can be achieved using this
technique. This avoids all hassles of removable media, like finding
and burning CD images or struggling with too numerous and 
<xref linkend="unreliable-floppies"/> unreliable floppy disks.

</para><para arch="i386">

The installer cannot boot from files on an NTFS file system.

</para><para arch="powerpc"> 

The installer cannot boot from files on an HFS+ file system.  MacOS
System 8.1 and above may use HFS+ file systems; NewWorld PowerMacs all
use HFS+. To determine whether your existing file system is HFS+,
select <userinput>Get Info</userinput> for the volume in question. HFS
file systems appear as <userinput>Mac OS Standard</userinput>, while
HFS+ file systems say <userinput>Mac OS Extended</userinput>. You must
have an HFS partition in order to exchange files between MacOS and
Linux, in particular the installation files you download.

</para><para arch="powerpc"> 

Different programs are used for hard disk installation system booting,
depending on whether the system is a ``NewWorld'' or an ``OldWorld''
model.

</para>

  <sect2 arch="i386" id="files-lilo">
  <title>Hard disk installer booting using <command>LILO</command> or
  <command>GRUB</command></title>
<para>

This section explains how to add to or even replace an existing linux
installation using either <command>LILO</command> or
<command>GRUB</command>.

</para><para>

At boot time, both bootloaders support loading in memory not
only the kernel, but also a disk image. This RAM disk can be used as
the root file-system by the kernel. Choose the flavor in 
<xref linkend="kernel-choice"/> that best fits your taste, and you 
will be (almost) done.

</para><para>

Copy the following two or three files from the Debian archives in a
convenient location on your hard drive, for instance in
<filename>/boot/newinstall/</filename>.

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>

<filename>vmlinuz</filename> (kernel binary)

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>initrd.gz</filename> (ramdisk image)

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>drivers.tgz</filename> (optional kernel modules) 

</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

Extract recursively everything <emphasis>now</emphasis> (easier than
later). Remember on which physical partition
(e.g. <filename>/dev/hda4</filename>) are the <filename>.o</filename>
drivers you just extracted from <filename>drivers.tgz</filename>.

</para><para>

You can also replace <filename>vmlinuz</filename> and
<filename>drivers.tgz</filename> by your custom kernel and the
carefully chosen drivers that you will need for the installation, for
instance a module for your exotic and unsupported network interface.
Do not forget that your custom kernel must have (at least) the
<filename>RAMDISK</filename> and <filename>initrd</filename> features
<emphasis>built-in</emphasis>.  See the very beginning of 
<xref linkend="rescue-replace-kernel"/> for the list of the other
mandatory built-in kernel features required to boot and launch the
installer. The floppy-related stuff after the list of features is
irrelevant to you.

</para><para>

Finally, to configure the bootloader proceed to 
<xref linkend="boot-initrd"/>.

</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="powerpc" id="files-oldworld">
  <title>Hard Disk Installer Booting for OldWorld Macs</title>
<para>

The <filename>boot-floppy-hfs</filename> floppy uses
<application>miBoot</application> to launch Linux installation, but
<application>miBoot</application> cannot easily be used for hard disk
booting. <application>BootX</application>, launched from MacOS,
supports booting from files placed on the hard
disk. <application>BootX</application> can also be used to dual-boot
MacOS and Linux after your Debian installation is complete. For the
Performa 6360, it appears that <command>quik</command> cannot make the
hard disk bootable.  So <application>BootX</application> is required
on that model.

</para><para>

Download and unstuff the <application>BootX</application>
distribution, available from <ulink url="&url-powerpc-bootx;"></ulink>, 
or in the
<filename>dists/woody/main/disks-powerpc/current/powermac</filename>
directory on Debian http/ftp mirrors and official Debian CDs. Use
<application>Stuffit Expander</application> to extract it from its
archive. Within the package, there is an empty folder called
<filename>Linux Kernels</filename>. Download
<filename>linux.bin</filename> and
<filename>ramdisk.image.gz</filename> from the
<filename>disks-powerpc/current/powermac</filename> folder, and place
them in the <filename>Linux Kernels</filename> folder. Then place the
<filename>Linux Kernels</filename> folder in the active System Folder.

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 arch="powerpc" id="files-newworld">
  <title>Hard Disk Installer Booting for NewWorld Macs</title>
<para>

NewWorld PowerMacs support booting from a network or an ISO9660
CD-ROM, as well as loading ELF binaries directly from the hard
disk. These machines will boot Linux directly via
<command>yaboot</command>, which supports loading a kernel and RAMdisk
directly from an ext2 partition, as well as dual-booting with
MacOS. Hard disk booting of the installer is particularly appropriate
for newer machines without floppy drives. <command>BootX</command> is
not supported and must not be used on NewWorld PowerMacs.

</para><para>

<emphasis>Copy</emphasis> (not move) the following four files which
you downloaded earlier from the Debian archives, onto the root level
of your hard drive (this can be accomplished by
<keycap>option</keycap>-dragging each file to the hard drive icon).

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>

<filename>linux.bin</filename>

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>root.bin</filename> (from inside the images-1.44 folder)

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>yaboot</filename>

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>yaboot.conf</filename>

</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para><para>

Make a note of the partition number of the MacOS partition where you
place these files. If you have the MacOS <command>pdisk</command>
program, you can use the L command to check for the partition
number. You will need this partition number for the command you type
at the Open Firmware prompt when you boot the installer.

</para><para>

To boot the installer, proceed to <xref linkend="boot-newworld"/>.

</para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
