<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 14171 untranslated -->

 <sect1 id="downloading-files">
 <title>Downloading Files from Debian Mirrors</title>

<para>

To find the nearest (and thus probably the fastest) mirror, see the
<ulink url="&url-debian-mirrors;">list of Debian mirrors</ulink>.

</para><para>

When downloading files from a Debian mirror, be sure to download the
files in <emphasis>binary</emphasis> mode, not text or automatic
mode. It's important to replicate the directory structure you find on
the mirror to create a local `sub-mirror'.

<phrase arch="not-s390">

It isn't really necessary to do this
if you place all the installation files on floppies; but it still
makes it easier to find the files when you need them.

</phrase>

You should start your local directory structure at the level under
<filename>installer-&architecture;</filename>, for example:

<informalexample><screen arch="i386">
current/images/floppy/boot.img
</screen><screen arch="not-i386">
current/images/<replaceable>subarchitecture</replaceable>/netboot/initrd.gz
</screen></informalexample>

You don't need to download every file under that level, just those
that apply to you (you'll find out which ones apply as you read on).
Just name the directories the same as the mirror's, and keep the files
in their proper directories.

</para><para>

If your machine is set up to automatically decompress/decode files you
download, you must turn that feature off when downloading the
installation system files. They will be decompressed just-in-time by
the installer. Decompressing in your current system will waste space
and time, and if the original compressed archives are deleted by the
decompression program, they won't be there later when the installer
needs them.

</para><para arch="powerpc;m68k">

This is particularly true on the Macintosh, where <filename>.bin</filename>
files are interpreted to be MacBinary, and the decoder's attempts to
convert them will fail noisily. 

</para><para arch="powerpc"> 

Also, many of the binary files such as <filename>yaboot</filename>
will be automatically interpreted as text since they have no file
extensions unless you specifically select binary transfer mode. These
files will be <emphasis>unusable</emphasis> if they are transferred in
text mode.

</para>

  <sect2 arch="m68k">
  <title>Installation Options</title>
<para> 

For m68k (except VME), the installation system files
(<filename>rescue.bin, linux.bin, root.bin, and
drivers.tgz</filename>) have been compiled into one tarball. You may
also need the base system installation file
<filename>basedebs.tar</filename>.

</para><para> 

If you have a working Ethernet connection on the computer, and your
Ethernet card is of one of the types compiled into the installation
kernel, you may only need the install system tarball.

</para><para> 

If you are installing on a system without a working network
connection, or if your network connection is via PPP (using a modem)
rather than Ethernet, you will also need to download
<filename>basedebs.tar</filename> before starting the installation.  

</para>
</sect2>

  <sect2 arch="not-m68k">
  <title>Installation Options</title>
<para>

Files you may need fall into three categories: 

</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>

Files needed to boot into the installation system (for example,
<phrase arch="not-s390"> 
<filename>boot.img</filename> and <filename>root.img</filename>, or
<filename>vmlinuz</filename> and <filename>initrd.gz</filename>)
</phrase>

<phrase arch="s390">
<filename>kernel.debian</filename>, 
<filename>parmfile.debian</filename>, and 
<filename>initrd.debian</filename>)
</phrase>

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Files the installation system will need access to
after it has been booted in order to install the operating system
kernel and peripheral drivers (for example, 
<filename>net-drivers.img</filename> and 
<filename>cd-drivers.img</filename>)

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

Base system installation files

</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>

If you have a working Ethernet connection on the computer, and your
Ethernet card is of one of the types compiled into the installation
kernel, you may only need the install system boot files. The installer
is capable of installing drivers and the rest of the system over the
network for many common Ethernet cards.

</para><para>

If you have an Ethernet connection for which the installer doesn't
have built-in support, you may need both the install system boot files
and the peripheral driver installation files. 

</para><para>

If you are installing on a system without a working network
connection, or if your network connection is via PPP (using a modem)
rather than Ethernet, you will need to obtain all three types of files
before starting the installation. The base system installation files
are available on the first Debian CD (or on its smaller variant called
<firstterm>netinst</firstterm>, which is under 120MB). You can use
this ISO image even if you don't have a CD-ROM drive.

</para><para>

If you're not sure which files you need, just start with the install
system boot files. If your first attempt to configure the network
within the installer fails, you can just quit, get the extra files you
need, and re-start the installation.

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 arch="i386" id="kernel-choice">
  <title>Choosing the Right Installation Set</title>
<para>

Installation files include kernel images, which are available in
various <firstterm>flavors</firstterm>.  Each flavor supports a
different set of hardware. The flavors available for &arch-title; are:

<variablelist>
 <varlistentry>
  <term>vanilla</term>
<listitem><para>

The standard kernel package available in Debian. This includes almost
all drivers supported by Linux built as modules, which includes
drivers for network devices, SCSI devices, sound cards, Video4Linux
devices, etc. The <quote>vanilla</quote> flavor includes one boot
floppy, one root and two driver floppies.

</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>speakup</term>
<listitem><para>

Almost like <quote>vanilla</quote>, but it contains support for
braille display. A complete list of supported models may be found in
brltty documentation. This flavor includes one boot floppy, one root
floppy and one driver floppy.

</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>linux26</term>
<listitem><para>

This is an experimental flavor which uses kernel from the 2.6
series. It might not be as stable as the other flavors, but it
supports some newer hardware components. If you can't complete the
installation due to a missing driver for your hardware, try this
one.

</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</para><para>

Although we have described above how many 1.44MB diskettes the
different sets occupy, you may still choose different methods of
installation.

</para><para>

The kernel config files for these flavors can be found in their
respective directories in a file named <filename>kernel-config</filename>. 

</para>
</sect2>

  <sect2 arch="not-i386">
  <title>Choosing the Right Installation Set</title>
<para>

Installation files include kernel images, which are available for
various <firstterm>subarchitectures</firstterm>. Each subarchitecture
supports a different set of hardware.  The kernel config files for
these subarchitectures can be found in their respective directories in
a file named <filename>kernel-config</filename>.  The subarchitectures
available for &arch-title; are:

</para>

<variablelist arch="sparc">
<varlistentry>
 <term>`sun4cmd'</term>
<listitem><para>

This is the kernel required for older SPARC hardware.  For specific
models supported, see <xref linkend="sparc-cpus"/>.

</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
 <term>`sun4u'</term>
<listitem><para>

UltraSPARC machines.

</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para arch="sparc">

The kernel config files for these subarchitectures can be found in their
respective directories in a file named <filename>kernel-config</filename>. 

</para>

    <variablelist arch="mipsel">
    <varlistentry>
<term>`r4k-kn04'</term>
    <listitem><para>

This is the kernel required for the R4000 based DECstation 5000/150 and
similar machines, such as the R4400 based DECstation 5000/260.
    
</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
<term>`r3k-kn02'</term>
    <listitem><para>

This is the kernel required for R3000 based DECstations with KN02 (or
compatible) main board, such as the DECstation 5000/1xx series with
xx=20,25,33 and the DECstation 5000/240.
    
</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

<para arch="mipsel">

The kernel config files for these subarchitectures can be found in their
respective directories in a file named <filename>kernel-config</filename>. 

</para>

    <variablelist arch="mips">
    <varlistentry>
<term>`r4k-ip22'</term>
    <listitem><para>

This is the kernel required for SGI Indy, Indigo 2 and Challenge S machines.
The kernel includes almost all drivers supported by Linux built as modules,
which includes drivers for network devices, SCSI devices, etc.  There are no
other flavors for &arch-title; available currently.
    
</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

<para arch="mips">

The kernel config files for these subarchitectures can be found in their
respective directories in a file named <filename>kernel-config</filename>. 

</para>

    <variablelist arch="hppa">
    <varlistentry>
<term>`32'</term>
    <listitem><para>

This is the kernel to use on all 32 bit processors.  On processors
that support 32 and 64 bit modes, this is probably also the best
kernel to use for installation.
    

</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
<term>`64'</term>
    <listitem><para>

This is the kernel to use on all 64 bit processors.  On processors
that support 32 and 64 bit modes, the 32 bit kernel is probably the
best kernel to use for installation.    

</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

<para arch="hppa">

These kernels include almost all drivers supported by Linux built as
modules, which includes drivers for network devices, SCSI devices,
etc.  Support for standard hardware is compiled in to the kernel,
so it is unlikely that you will need to configure any modules during
installation.

</para><para arch="hppa">

The kernel config files for these subarchitectures can be found in their
respective directories in a file named <filename>kernel-config</filename>. 

</para>


<variablelist arch="s390">
<varlistentry>
<term>`tape'</term>
<listitem><para>

Includes a kernel image which supports booting (IPL) from a tape
(emulated or real) and a DASD (Direct Access Storage Device). You need
these files if you want to install &debian; native or in an
LPAR (logical partition) but they can also be used to install under VM
with a tape (real or emulated).

</para><para arch="s390"><phrase condition="FIXME">

<emphasis>FIXME: what about the nolabel kernel?</emphasis>

</phrase></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>`vmrdr'</term>
<listitem><para>

Includes a kernel image which supports booting (IPL) from the VM
reader and a DASD, These files can only be used if you want to install
&debian; in a VM guest.

</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para arch="s390">

Both of these kernels include almost all drivers supported by Linux
built as modules.  Support for standard hardware is compiled into the
kernel, so it is unlikely that you will need to configure any modules
during installation.

</para><para arch="s390">

Both kernels were also built to directly support IBM's OCO modules.  You
can simply download then from IBM's 
<ulink url="http://oss.software.ibm.com/developerworks/opensource/linux390/index.shtml">
developerWorks web site</ulink> and load them into the running kernel.
Please make sure that you pick the modules for the standard kernel,
i.e. not the ones for a kernel with the ``on-demand'' timer patch.

</para><para arch="s390">

The kernel config files for these subarchitectures can be found in their
respective directories in a file named <filename>kernel-config</filename>. 

</para>


    <variablelist arch="powerpc">
    <varlistentry>
<term>`powermac'</term>
    <listitem><para>

This is the kernel to use for most Power Macintosh computers; it uses
version 2.2 of the Linux kernel.

</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
<term>`new-powermac'</term>
    <listitem><para>

Use this kernel for very new Power Macintosh computers; it is based on
version 2.4 of the Linux kernel. If you want to install the
new-powermac version on an OldWorld machine, you are limited to using
BootX to boot the installer; the kernel doesn't fit on a floppy and
Debian CDs are not bootable on OldWorlds. You could also switch to the
&kernelversion; kernel after you finish the powermac flavor install.

</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
<term>`apus'</term>
    <listitem><para>

Use this kernel for Amiga Power-UP Systems (APUS); it is based on
version 2.2 of the Linux kernel.

</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
<term>`chrp'</term>
    <listitem><para>

Use this kernel for embedded CHRP computers; it is based on
version 2.2 of the Linux kernel.

</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
<term>`prep'</term>
    <listitem><para>

Use this kernel for Motorola and IBM RS/6000 PReP computers; it is based on
version 2.2 of the Linux kernel.

</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

<para arch="powerpc">

The kernel config files for these subarchitectures can be found in their
respective directories in a file named <filename>config.gz</filename>. 

</para><para arch="arm">

There is only one installation kernel available for each supported ARM
machine family.

</para><para arch="m68k;ia64">

There is only one install kernel available for &arch-title;, which
should include sufficient functionality to install on all systems.  It
is unlikely to be optimised for your particular hardware, and you
might consider replacing it once installation is complete.  In
particular, this kernel does not support SMP.  

</para><para arch="m68k;ia64">

The kernel config files for these kernels can be found in their
respective directories in a file named <filename>config.gz</filename>. 

</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="where-files">
  <title>Where to Find Installation Files</title>

<para arch="m68k"> 

For Amiga, Atari, and 68k Mac, the install system files have been
compiled into one tarball. You will download the appropriate tarball
listed in 
<xref linkend="amiga-install-files"/>, 
<xref linkend="atari-install-files"/>, or 
<xref linkend="mac-install-files"/>. Only
VME machines will need the separate boot, root, kernel and drivers
files.  

</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>boot image</term>
<listitem>
<itemizedlist>
&list-rescue-images;
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry condition="rescue-needs-root-disk">
<term>root image(s) or tarball</term>
<listitem>
<itemizedlist>
&list-root-images;
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>kernel binary</term>
<listitem>
<itemizedlist>
&list-kernel-files;
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>driver images or tarball</term>
<listitem>
<itemizedlist>
&list-driver-images;
&list-driver-disk-tarball;
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para arch="not-powerpc">

The boot image contains a compressed Linux boot
kernel. It is used for 
<phrase arch="not-s390">both floppy disk booting (when transferred to a
floppy) and as the source for </phrase>
the Linux kernel when the kernel is
being installed on your machine. The kernel binary 
<filename>vmlinuz</filename>
is an uncompressed binary kernel.  It is used when booting the
installer from 
<phrase arch="not-s390">

the hard disk, usb stick, network or CD-ROM, and is not needed for
floppy installer booting.

</phrase><phrase arch="s390">

tape, emulated tape or the VM reader.

</phrase></para>

<para arch="mipsel">

Besides the file <filename>linux.bin</filename>, which is a kernel image in
ELF format, the file <filename>linux.ecoff</filename> contains the same
kernel in ECOFF format, which is required for net booting DECstations.

</para><para arch="powerpc"> 

Both the <filename>boot-floppy-hfs</filename> floppy image and the
<filename>boot.img</filename> image contain a compressed Linux boot
kernel. The <filename>boot-floppy-hfs</filename> floppy is used to
boot the installation system, while <filename>boot.img</filename>
serves as the source for the Linux kernel when the kernel is being
installed on your machine. A <filename>boot.img</filename> floppy
cannot be booted on &arch-title;. A third uncompressed kernel image,
simply named <filename>linux.bin</filename>, is used when booting the
installer from the hard disk or CD-ROM.  It is not needed for floppy
installer booting.

</para><para arch="powerpc"> 

There are two versions of the hfs boot floppy image. The standard one,
<filename>boot-floppy-hfs.img</filename>, may work best on older
machines such as the 7200 and 8500 with no added video cards. If the
standard image gives a black screen when booting, try the image with
video=ofonly added to the boot arguments:
<filename>boot-video-ofonly.img</filename>.

</para><para condition="supports-floppy-boot">

Refer to <xref linkend="create-floppy"/> 
for important information on properly
creating floppy disks from floppy images.

</para><para condition="rescue-needs-root-disk">

The root floppy image <filename>root.img</filename> contains a
compressed RAMdisk filesystem which gets loaded into memory after you
boot the installer.

</para><para>

The peripheral drivers may be downloaded as a series of floppy images
or as a tarball (<filename>drivers.tgz</filename>). The installer
system will need access to the drivers file during installation. If
you have a hard drive partition or connected computer which will be
accessible to the installer (see below), the tarball will be more
convenient to handle. The floppy image files are needed only if you
must install the drivers from floppies.

</para><para>

When downloading files, you should also pay attention to the type of
file system you are downloading them <emphasis>to</emphasis>, unless
you will use floppies for the kernel and drivers. The installer can
read files from many kinds of file systems, including FAT, HFS,
ext2fs, and Minix.  When downloading files to a *nix file system,
choose the largest possible files from the archive.

</para><para>

During the installation, you will erase the partition(s) on which you
are installing Debian before beginning the installation. All
downloaded files must be placed on partitions
<emphasis>other</emphasis> than those on which you are planning to
install the system.

</para>

&download-alpha.xml;
&download-arm.xml;
&download-powerpc.xml;
&download-m68k.xml;

  </sect2>

 </sect1>
