<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 14975 untranslated -->

 <sect1 id="module-details">
 <title>Using Individual Components</title>
<para>

In this section we will describe each installer component in
detail. The components are logically grouped together to
a user-recognisable parts as they appear during the install.

</para>

  <sect2>
  <title>Setting up Debian Installer and Hardware Configuration</title>
<para>

Let's assume the Debian Installer has booted and you are facing its
first screen.  At this time, &d-i; is still quite incapable. It
doesn't know much about your computer hardware, preferred language, or
even the task it should fulfil. Don't worry. Because &d-i; is quite
clever, it can automatically probe for your hardware, locate the rest
of its components and upgrade itself to a modern, well-built program.

However, you still need to help &d-i; with some tasks it can't guess
easily (like selecting your preferred language, keyboard layout or
desired network mirror).

</para>

&module-languagechooser.xml;
&module-countrychooser.xml;
&module-s390-netdevice.xml;
&module-s390-dasd.xml;
&module-ddetect.xml;
&module-pcmcia.xml;
&module-kbd-chooser.xml;
&module-netcfg.xml;
&module-iso-scan.xml;
&module-choose-mirror.xml;
&module-cdrom-detect.xml;
&module-lowmem.xml;
&module-anna.xml;
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
  <title>Partitioning and Mount Point Selection</title>
<para>

At this time, &d-i; should be in its full strength, customized for
user's needs and ready to do some real work.

As the title of this chapter states, the main task of the next few
components lies in partitioning your disks, creating filesystems,
assigning mountpoints and configuring closely related issues like LVM
or RAID devices.

</para>

&module-partman.xml;
&module-autopartkit.xml;
&module-partitioner.xml;
&module-partconf.xml;
&module-lvmcfg.xml;
&module-mdcfg.xml;
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
  <title>Installing the Base System</title>
<para>

Albeit this part is the least problematic, it consumes most time of
the install, because it downloads, verifies and unpacks the whole base
system. If you have a slow computer or network connection, this could
take some time.

</para>

&module-base-installer.xml;
&module-kernel-chooser.xml;
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
  <title>Making Your System Bootable</title>
<para>

Note that multiple operating systems booting on a single machine is
still something of a black art.  This document does not even attempt
to document the various boot managers, which vary by architecture and
even by subarchitecture.  You should see your boot manager's
documentation for more information.

</para><para condition="supports-nfsroot">

If you are installing a diskless workstation, obviously, booting off
the local disk isn't a meaningful option, and this step will be
skipped. <phrase arch="sparc">You may wish to set the OpenBoot to boot
from the network by default; see <xref
linkend="boot-dev-select-sun"/>.</phrase>

</para>

&module-os-prober.xml;
&module-alpha-aboot-installer.xml;
&module-hppa-palo-installer.xml;
&module-i386-grub-installer.xml;
&module-i386-lilo-installer.xml;
&module-ia64-elilo-installer.xml;
&module-mips-arcboot-installer.xml;
&module-mipsel-colo-installer.xml;
&module-mipsel-delo-installer.xml;
&module-powerpc-yaboot-installer.xml;
&module-powerpc-quik-installer.xml;
&module-s390-zipl-installer.xml;
&module-sparc-silo-installer.xml;
&module-nobootloader.xml;
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
  <title>Finishing the First Stage</title>
<para>

These are the last bits to do before rebooting to your new Debian. It
mostly consists of tidying up after the &d-i;.

</para>

&module-prebaseconfig.xml;
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
  <title>Miscellaneous</title>
<para>

Following components are usually not involved in the installation
process, but they are awaiting in the background to help the user in
case something goes wrong.

</para>

&module-baseconfig.xml;
&module-bugreporter.xml;
&module-cdrom-checker.xml;
&module-shell.xml;
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
