<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id: shadow.xml 11648 2004-03-22 00:37:46Z joeyh $ -->

 <sect2 id="base-config-users">
 <title>Setting Up Users And Passwords</title>

  <sect3 id="base-config-shadow">
  <title>Shadow Passwords</title>

<para>

Depending on a given priority, the system may ask whether you want to
enable shadow passwords.  This is a system in which your GNU/Linux
system is made to be a bit more secure.  In a system without shadow
passwords, passwords are stored (encrypted) in a world-readable file,
<filename>/etc/passwd</filename>.  This file has to be readable to
anyone who can log in because it contains vital user information, for
instance, how to map between numeric user identifiers and login names.
Therefore, someone could conceivably grab your
<filename>/etc/passwd</filename> file and run a brute force attack
(i.e. run an automated test of all possible password combinations)
against it to try to determine passwords.

</para><para>

If you have shadow passwords enabled, passwords are instead stored in
<filename>/etc/shadow</filename>, which is readable and writable only
by root, and readable by group shadow. Therefore, we recommend that
you enable shadow passwords.

</para><para>

Reconfiguration of the shadow password system can be done at any time
with the <command>shadowconfig</command> program.  After installation,
see <filename>/usr/share/doc/passwd/README.debian.gz</filename> for
more information.

</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="base-config-root">
  <title>Set the Root Password</title>

<para>

The <emphasis>root</emphasis> account is also called the
<emphasis>super-user</emphasis>; it is a login that bypasses all
security protection on your system. The root account should only be
used to perform system administration, and only used for as short
a time as possible.

</para><para>

Any password you create should contain at least 6 characters, and
should contain both upper- and lower-case characters, as well as
punctuation characters.  Take extra care when setting your root
password, since it is such a powerful account.  Avoid dictionary
words or use of any personal information which could be guessed.

</para><para>

If anyone ever tells you they need your root password, be extremely
wary. You should normally never give your root account out, unless you
are administering a machine with more than one system administrator.

</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="make-normal-user">
  <title>Create an Ordinary User</title>

<para>

The system will ask you whether you wish to create an ordinary user
account at this point.  This account should be your main personal
log-in.  You should <emphasis>not</emphasis> use the root account for
daily use or as your personal login.

</para><para>

Why not?  Well, one reason to avoid using root's privileges is that it
is very easy to do irreparable damage as root.  Another reason is that
you might be tricked into running a <emphasis>Trojan-horse</emphasis>
program &mdash; that is a program that takes advantage of your
super-user powers to compromise the security of your system behind
your back. Any good book on Unix system administration will cover this
topic in more detail &mdash; consider reading one if it is new to you.

</para><para>

Name the user account anything you like.  If your name is John Smith,
you might use <userinput>smith</userinput>,
<userinput>john</userinput>, <userinput>jsmith</userinput> or
<userinput>js</userinput>.  You will also be prompted for the full
name of the user, and, like before, a password.

</para><para>

If at any point after installation you would like to create another
account, use the <command>adduser</command> command.

</para><para arch="s390">

You need to create a user account on &arch-title; if you want to login
over the network using telnet. The telnet server does not allow root
logins in Debian's default configuration. However, you can use ssh
(Secure SHell) to remotely login as root but this is not
recommended.

</para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>
