<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 24663 untranslated -->

  <sect2 arch="ia64"><title>Booting from a CD-ROM</title>

&boot-installer-intro-cd.xml;

  <note>
  <title>CD Contents</title>

<para>

There are three basic variations of Debian Install CDs.
The <emphasis>Business Card</emphasis> CD has a minimal installation
that will fit on the small form factor CD media.
It requires a network connection in order to install the rest of the
base installation and make a usable system.
The <emphasis>Network Install</emphasis> CD has all of the packages
for a base install but requires a network connection to a Debian
mirror site in order to install the
extra packages one would want for a complete system .
The set of Debian CDs can install a complete system from the wide
range of packages without needing access to the network.
</para>
  </note>

<para>

The IA-64 architecture uses the next generation Extensible Firmware Interface
(EFI) from Intel.
Unlike the traditional x86 BIOS which knows little about the boot
device other than the partition table and Master Boot Record (MBR),
EFI can read and write files from FAT16 or FAT32 formatted disk
partitions.
This simplifies the often arcane process of starting a system.
The system boot loader and the EFI firmware that supports it have
a full filesystem to store the files necessary for booting the
machine.
This means that the system disk on an IA-64 system has an additional
disk partition dedicated to EFI instead of the simple MBR or boot
block on more conventional systems. 

</para><para>

The Debian Installer CD contains a small EFI partition where the
<command>ELILO</command> bootloader, its configuration file, the installer's
kernel, and initial filesystem (initrd) are located.
The running system also contains an EFI partition where the necessary
files for booting the system reside.
These files are readable from the EFI Shell as described below.

</para><para>

Most of the details of how <command>ELILO</command> actually loads and
starts a system are transparent to the system installer.
However, the installer must set up an EFI partition prior to installing
the base system.  Otherwise, the installation of <command>ELILO</command>
will fail, rendering the system un-bootable.
The EFI partition is allocated and formatted in the partitioning step
of the installation prior to loading any packages on the system disk.
The partitioning task also verifies that a suitable EFI partition is
present before allowing the installation to proceed.

</para><para>

The EFI Boot Manager is presented as the last step of the firmware
initialization.
It displays a menu list from which the user can select
an option.
Depending on the model of system and what other software has been
loaded on the system, this menu may be different from one system
to another.
There should be at least two menu items displayed,
<command>Boot Option Maintenance Menu</command> and
<command>EFI Shell (Built-in)</command>.
Using the first option is preferred, however, if that
option is not available or the CD for some reason does not
boot with it, use the second option.

</para>

  <warning>
  <title>IMPORTANT</title>
<para>
The EFI Boot Manager will select a default boot action, typically
the first menu choice, within a pre-set number of seconds.
This is indicated by a countdown at the bottom of the screen.
Once the timer expires and the systems starts the default action,
you may have to reboot the machine in order to continue the installation.
If the default action is the EFI Shell, you can return to the Boot Manager
by running <command>exit</command> at the shell prompt.
</para>
  </warning>

  <sect3 arch="ia64" id="bootable-cd">
  <title>Option 1: Booting from the Boot Option Maintenance Menu</title>
<para>

</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
Insert the CD in the DVD/CD drive and reboot the machine.
The firmware will display the EFI Boot Manager page and menu after
it completes its system initialization.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Select <command>Boot Maintenance Menu</command> from the menu
with the arrow keys and press <command>ENTER</command>.
This will display a new menu.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Select <command>Boot From a File</command> from the menu
with the arrow keys and press <command>ENTER</command>.
This will display a list of devices probed by the firmware.
You should see two menu lines containing either the label
<command>Debian Inst [Acpi ...</command> or
<command>Removable Media Boot</command>.
If you examine the rest of the menu line, you will notice that
the device and controller information should be the same.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
You can choose either of the entries that refer to the CD/DVD
drive.
Select your choice with the arrow keys and press <command>ENTER</command>.
If you choose <command>Removable Media Boot</command> the machine
will immediately start the boot load sequence.
If you choose <command>Debian Inst [Acpi ...</command> instead, it
will display a directory listing of the bootable portion of the
CD, requiring you to proceed to the next (additional) step.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
You will only need this step if you chose
<command>Debian Inst [Acpi ...</command>.
The directory listing will also show
<command>[Treat like Removable Media Boot]</command> on the next to
the last line.
Select this line with the arrow keys and press <command>ENTER</command>.
This will start the boot load sequence.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>

These steps start the Debian boot loader which will display a
menu page for you to select a boot kernel and options.
Proceed to selecting the boot kernel and options.

</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 arch="ia64" id="boot-with-efi">
  <title>Option 2: Booting from the EFI Shell</title>
<para>

If, for some reason, option 1 is not successful, reboot the machine
and when the EFI Boot Manager screen appears there should be
one option called <command>EFI Shell [Built-in]</command>.
Boot the Debian Installer CD with the following steps:

</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
Insert the CD in the DVD/CD drive and reboot the machine.
The firmware will display the EFI Boot Manager page and menu after
it completes system initialization.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Select <command>EFI Shell</command> from the menu with the arrow keys
and press <command>ENTER</command>.
The EFI Shell will scan all of the bootable devices and display
them to the console before displaying its command prompt.
The recognized bootable partitions on devices will show a device name of
<filename>fs<replaceable>n</replaceable>:</filename>.
All other recognized partitions will be named
<filename>blk<replaceable>n</replaceable>:</filename>.
If you inserted the CD just before entering the shell, this may
take a few extra seconds as it initializes the CD drive.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>
Examine the output from the shell looking for the CDROM drive.
It is most likely the <filename>fs0:</filename> device although
other devices with bootable partitions will also show up as
<filename>fs<replaceable>n</replaceable></filename>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Enter <command>fs<replaceable>n</replaceable>:</command> and press
<command>ENTER</command> to select that
device where <replaceable>n</replaceable> is the partition number for the
CDROM.  The shell will now display the partition number as its prompt.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Enter <command>elilo</command> and press <command>ENTER</command>.
This will start the boot load sequence.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para> 

As with option 1, these steps start the Debian boot loader which will
display a menu page for you to select a boot kernel and options.
You can also enter the shorter 
<command>fs<replaceable>n</replaceable>:elilo</command> command at
the shell prompt.
Proceed to selecting the boot kernel and options.

</para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 arch="ia64" id="serial-console">
  <title>Installing using a Serial Console</title>

<para>

You may choose to perform an install using a monitor and keyboard
or using a serial connection.  To use a monitor/keyboard setup,
select an option containing the string [VGA console].  To install
over a serial connection, choose an option containing the string
[<replaceable>BAUD</replaceable> baud serial console], where
<replaceable>BAUD</replaceable> is the speed of your serial console.
Menu items for the most typical baud rate settings on the ttyS0
device are preconfigured.

</para><para>

In most circumstances, you will want the installer to use the same
baud rate as your connection to the EFI console.  If you aren't
sure what this setting is, you can obtain it using the command
<command>baud</command> at the EFI shell.

</para><para>

If there is not an option available that is configured for the serial
device or baud rate you would like to use, you may override the console setting
for one of the existing menu options.  For example, to use a
57600 baud console over the ttyS1 device, enter
<command>console=ttyS1,57600n8</command> into
the <classname>Boot:</classname> text window.

</para>

<note><para>
Most IA-64 boxes ship with a default console setting of 9600 baud.
This setting is rather slow, and the normal installation process
will take a significant time to draw each screen.  You should consider
either increasing the baud rate used for performing the installation,
or performing a Text Mode installation.  See the <classname>Params</classname>
help menu for instructions on starting the installer in Text Mode.
</para></note>

<warning><para>
If you select the wrong console type, you
will be able to select the kernel and enter parameters but both
the display and your input will go dead as soon as the kernel starts,
requiring you to reboot before you can begin the installation.
</para></warning>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 arch="ia64" id="kernel-option-menu">
  <title>Selecting the Boot Kernel and Options</title>

<para>

The boot loader will display a form with a menu list and a text
window with a <classname>Boot:</classname> prompt.
The arrow keys select an item from the menu and any text typed
at the keyboard will appear in the text window.
There are also help screens which can be displayed by pressing
the appropriate function key.
The <classname>General</classname> help screen explains the menu
choices and the <classname>Params</classname> screen explains
the common command line options.

</para><para>

Consult the <classname>General</classname> help screen for the
description of the kernels and install modes most appropriate
for your installation.
You should also consult <xref linkend="boot-parms"/> below for any additional
parameters that you may want to set in the <classname>Boot:</classname>
text window.
The kernel version you choose selects the kernel version that will be
used for both the installation process and the installed system.
If you encounter kernel problems with the installation, you may also
have those same problems with the system you install.
The following two steps will select and start the install:

</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
Select the kernel version and installation mode most
appropriate to your needs with the arrow keys.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Enter any boot parameters by typing at the keyboard.
The text will be displayed directly in the text window.
This is where kernel parameters (such as serial console
settings) are specified.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Press <command>ENTER</command>.  This will load and start the
kernel.
The kernel will display its usual initialization messages followed
by the first screen of the Debian Installer.
</para></listitem> 

</itemizedlist>

<para>

Proceed to the next chapter to continue the installation where you will
set up the language locale, network, and disk partitions.

</para>
  </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 arch="ia64" id="boot-tftp"><title>Booting with TFTP</title>

<para>
Booting an IA64 system from the network is similar to a CD boot.
The only difference is how the installation kernel is loaded.
The EFI Boot Manager can load and start programs from a server on
the network.
Once the installation kernel is loaded and starts, the system install
will proceed thru the same steps as the CD install with the exception
that the packages of the base install will be loaded from the network
rather than the CD drive.

</para>

&boot-installer-intro-net.xml;

<para>

Network booting an ia64 system requires two architecture-specific actions.
On the boot server, DHCP and TFTP must be configured to deliver
<command>elilo</command>.
On the client a new boot option must be defined in the EFI boot manager
to enable loading over a network.

</para>

  <sect3 arch="ia64" id="boot-tftp-server">
  <title>Configuring the Server</title>
<para>

A suitable TFTP entry for network booting an ia64 system looks something
like this:

<informalexample><screen>
host mcmuffin {
        hardware ethernet 00:30:6e:1e:0e:83;
        fixed-address 10.0.0.21;
        filename "debian-installer/ia64/elilo.efi";
}
</screen></informalexample>

Note that the goal is to get <command>elilo.efi</command> running on
the client.

</para><para>

Extract the <filename>netboot.tar.gz</filename> file into the directory used
as the root for your tftp server.  Typical tftp root directories include
<filename>/var/lib/tftp</filename> and <filename>/tftpboot</filename>.
This will create a <filename>debian-installer</filename> directory
tree containing the boot files for an IA-64 system.

</para><para>

<informalexample><screen>
# cd /var/lib/tftp
# tar xvfz /home/user/netboot.tar.gz
./
./debian-installer/
./debian-installer/ia64/
[...]
</screen></informalexample>

The <filename>netboot.tar.gz</filename> contains an
<filename>elilo.conf</filename> file that should work for most configurations.
However, should you need to make changes to this file, you can find it in the
<filename>debian-installer/ia64/</filename> directory.

It is possible to have different config files for different clients by naming
them using the client's IP address in hex with the suffix
<filename>.conf</filename> instead of <filename>elilo.conf</filename>.
See documentation provided in the <classname>elilo</classname> package
for details.

</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 arch="ia64" id="boot-tftp-client">
  <title>Configuring the Client</title>
<para>

To configure the client to support TFTP booting, start by booting to
EFI and entering the <guimenu>Boot Option Maintenance Menu</guimenu>.

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>

Add a boot option.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

You should see one or more lines with the text
<guimenuitem>Load File [Acpi()/.../Mac()]</guimenuitem>.  If more
than one of these entries exist, choose the one containing the
MAC address of the interface from which you'll be booting.
Use the arrow keys to highlight your choice, then press enter.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Name the entry <userinput>Netboot</userinput> or something similar,
save, and exit back to the boot options menu.  

</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

You should see the new boot option you just created, and selecting it
should initiate a DHCP query, leading to a TFTP load of
<filename>elilo.efi</filename> from the server.

</para><para>

The boot loader will display its prompt after it has downloaded and
processed its configuration file.
At this point, the installation proceeds with the same steps as a
CD install.  Select a boot option as in above and when the kernel
has completed installing itself from the network, it will start the
Debian Installer.

</para><para>

Proceed to the next chapter to continue the installation where
you will set up the language locale, network, and the disk partitions.

</para>
  </sect3>
  </sect2>
