<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id$ -->


 <sect1 id="debian-orientation"><title>Orienting Yourself to Debian</title>
<para>

Debian is a little different from other distributions.  Even if you're
familiar with Linux in other distributions, there are things you
should know about Debian to help you to keep your system in a good,
clean state.  This chapter contains material to help you get oriented;
it is not intended to be a tutorial for how to use Debian, but just a
very brief glimpse of the system for the very rushed.

</para>

  <sect2><title>Debian Packaging System</title>
<para>

The most important concept to grasp is the Debian packaging system.
In essence, large parts of your system should be considered under the
control of the packaging system.  These include:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>

<filename>/usr</filename> (excluding <filename>/usr/local</filename>)

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>/var</filename> (you could make
<filename>/var/local</filename> and be safe in there)

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>/bin</filename>

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>/sbin</filename>

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>/lib</filename>

</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

For instance, if you replace <filename>/usr/bin/perl</filename>, that
will work, but then if you upgrade your <classname>perl</classname>
package, the file you put there will be replaced.  Experts can get
around this by putting packages on <quote>hold</quote> in
<command>aptitude</command>.

</para><para>

One of the best installation methods is apt. You can use the command
line version <command>apt-get</command> or full-screen text version
<application>aptitude</application>.  Note apt will also let you merge
main, contrib, and non-free so you can have export-restricted packages
as well as standard versions.

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Application Version Management</title>
<para>


Alternative versions of applications are managed by update-alternatives. If
you are maintaining multiple versions of your applications, read the
update-alternatives man page.

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Cron Job Management</title>
<para>

Any jobs under the purview of the system administrator should be in
<filename>/etc</filename>, since they are configuration files.  If you
have a root cron job for daily, weekly, or monthly runs, put them in
<filename>/etc/cron.{daily,weekly,monthly}</filename>.  These are
invoked from <filename>/etc/crontab</filename>, and will run in
alphabetic order, which serializes them.

</para><para>

On the other hand, if you have a cron job that (a) needs to run as a
special user, or (b) needs to run at a special time or frequency, you
can use either <filename>/etc/crontab</filename>, or, better yet,
<filename>/etc/cron.d/whatever</filename>.  These particular files
also have an extra field that allows you to stipulate the user under
which the cron job runs.

</para><para>

In either case, you just edit the files and cron will notice them
automatically. There is no need to run a special command. For more
information see cron(8), crontab(5), and
<filename>/usr/share/doc/cron/README.Debian</filename>.

</para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
