<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 28997 untranslated -->

 <sect1 id="non-debian-partitioning">
 <title>Pre-Partitioning for Multi-Boot Systems</title>
<para>

Partitioning your disk simply refers to the act of breaking up your
disk into sections. Each section is then independent of the others.
It's roughly equivalent to putting up walls inside a house; if you add
furniture to one room it doesn't affect any other room.

</para><para arch="s390">

Whenever this section talks about <quote>disks</quote> you should translate
this into a DASD or VM minidisk in the &arch-title; world. Also a machine
means an LPAR or VM guest in this case.

</para><para>

If you already have an operating system on your system

<phrase arch="i386">
(Windows 9x, Windows NT/2000/XP, OS/2, MacOS, Solaris, FreeBSD, &hellip;)
</phrase>

<phrase arch="alpha">
(Tru64 (Digital UNIX), OpenVMS, Windows NT, FreeBSD, &hellip;)
</phrase>

<phrase arch="s390">
(VM, z/OS, OS/390, &hellip;)
</phrase>

<phrase arch="m68k">
(Amiga OS, Atari TOS, Mac OS, &hellip;)
</phrase>

and want to stick Linux on the same disk, you will need to repartition
the disk. Debian requires its own hard disk partitions. It cannot be
installed on Windows or MacOS partitions. It may be able to share some
partitions with other Linux systems, but that's not covered here. At
the very least you will need a dedicated partition for the Debian
root.

</para><para>

You can find information about your current partition setup by using
a partitioning tool for your current operating system<phrase
arch="i386">, such as fdisk or PartitionMagic</phrase><phrase
arch="powerpc">, such as Drive Setup, HD Toolkit, or MacTools</phrase><phrase
arch="m68k">, such as HD SC Setup, HDToolBox, or SCSITool</phrase><phrase
arch="s390">, such as the VM diskmap</phrase>. Partitioning tools always
provide a way to show existing partitions without making changes.

</para><para>

In general, changing a partition with a file system already on
it will destroy any information there. Thus you should always make
backups before doing any repartitioning.  Using the analogy of the
house, you would probably want to move all the furniture out of the
way before moving a wall or you risk destroying it.

</para><para arch="hppa" condition="FIXME">

<emphasis>FIXME: write about HP-UX disks?</emphasis>

</para><para>

If your computer has more than one hard disk, you may want to dedicate
one of the hard disks completely to Debian. If so, you don't need to
partition that disk before booting the installation system; the
installer's included partitioning program can handle the job nicely.

</para><para>

If your machine has only one hard disk, and you would like to
completely replace the current operating system with &debian;,
you also can wait to partition as part of the installation process
(<xref linkend="partman"/>), after you have booted the
installation system.  However this only works if you plan to boot the
installer system from tapes, CD-ROM or files on a connected machine.
Consider: if you boot from files placed on the hard disk, and then
partition that same hard disk within the installation system, thus
erasing the boot files, you'd better hope the installation is
successful the first time around.  At the least in this case, you
should have some alternate means of reviving your machine like the
original system's installation tapes or CDs.

</para><para>

If your machine already has multiple partitions, and enough space can
be provided by deleting and replacing one or more of them, then you
too can wait and use the Debian installer's partitioning program. You
should still read through the material below, because there may be
special circumstances like the order of the existing partitions within
the partition map, that force you to partition before installing
anyway.

</para><para arch="i386">

If your machine has a FAT or NTFS filesystem, as used by DOS and Windows,
you can wait and use Debian installer's partitioning program to
resize the filesystem.

</para><para>

If none of the above apply, you'll need to partition your hard disk before
starting the installation to create partition-able space for
Debian. If some of the partitions will be owned by other operating
systems, you should create those partitions using native operating
system partitioning programs. We recommend that you do
<emphasis>not</emphasis> attempt to create partitions for &debian;
using another operating system's tools. Instead, you should just
create the native operating system's partitions you will want to
retain.

</para><para>

If you are going to install more than one operating system on the same
machine, you should install all other system(s) before proceeding with
Linux installation. Windows and other OS installations may destroy
your ability to start Linux, or encourage you to reformat non-native
partitions.

</para><para>

You can recover from these actions or avoid them, but installing
the native system first saves you trouble.

</para><para arch="powerpc">

In order for OpenFirmware to automatically boot &debian; the Linux
partitions should appear before all other partitions on the disk,
especially MacOS boot partitions. This should be kept in mind when
pre-partitioning; you should create a Linux placeholder partition to
come <emphasis>before</emphasis> the other bootable partitions on the
disk. (The small partitions dedicated to Apple disk drivers are not
bootable.) You can delete the placeholder with the Linux partition
tools later during the actual install, and replace it with Linux
partitions.

</para><para>

If you currently have one hard disk with one partition (a common setup
for desktop computers), and you want to multi-boot the native
operating system and Debian, you will need to:

  <orderedlist>
<listitem><para>

Back up everything on the computer.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Boot from the native operating system installer media such as CD-ROM
or tapes.

<phrase arch="powerpc">When booting from a MacOS CD, hold the
<keycap>c</keycap> key while
booting to force the CD to become the active MacOS system.</phrase>

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Use the native partitioning tools to create native system
partition(s). Leave either a place holder partition or free space for
&debian;.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Install the native operating system on its new partition.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Boot back into the native system to verify everything's OK,
    and to download the Debian installer boot files.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Boot the Debian installer to continue installing Debian.

</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

</para>

&nondeb-part-alpha.xml;
&nondeb-part-i386.xml;
&nondeb-part-m68k.xml;
&nondeb-part-sparc.xml;
&nondeb-part-powerpc.xml;

 </sect1>
