<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 23845 untranslated -->

 <sect2 id="configure-apt">
 <title>Configuring APT</title>

<para>

The main means that people use to install packages on their system is
via a program called <command>apt-get</command>, from the
<classname>apt</classname> package.<footnote>

<para>

Note that the actual program that installs packages is called
<command>dpkg</command>.  However, this package is more of a low-level
tool.  <command>apt-get</command> is a higher-level tool as it will
invoke <command>dpkg</command> as appropriate and also because it knows
to install other packages which are required for the package you're
trying to install, as well as how to retrieve the package from your
CD, the network, or wherever.

</para>
</footnote>

Other front-ends for package management, like <command>aptitude</command>,
<command>synaptic</command> and the older <command>dselect</command> also
use and depend on <command>apt-get</command>. These front-ends are recommended
for new users, since they integrate some additional features (package
searching and status checks) in a nice user interface.

</para><para>

APT must be configured so that it knows where to retrieve packages from.
The helper application which assists in this task is called
<command>apt-setup</command>.

</para><para>

The next step in your configuration process is to tell APT where other
Debian packages can be found.  Note that you can re-run this tool at
any point after installation by running <command>apt-setup</command>,
or by manually editing <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename>.

</para><para>

If an official CD-ROM is in the drive at this point, then that CD-ROM
should automatically be configured as an apt source without prompting.
You will notice this because you will see the CD-ROM being scanned.

</para><para>

For users without an official CD-ROM, you will be offered an array of
choices for how Debian packages are accessed: FTP, HTTP, CD-ROM, or
a local file system.

</para><para>

You should know that it's perfectly acceptable to have a number of
different APT sources, even for the same Debian archive.
<command>apt-get</command> will automatically pick the package with
the highest version number given all the available versions.  Or, for
instance, if you have both an HTTP and a CD-ROM APT source,
<command>apt-get</command> should automatically use the local CD-ROM
when possible, and only resort to HTTP if a newer version is available
there.  However, it is not a good idea to add unnecessary APT sources,
since this will tend to slow down the process of checking the network
archives for new versions.

</para>

  <sect3 id="configure-apt-net">
  <title>Configuring Network Package Sources</title>

<para>

If you plan on installing the rest of your system via the network, the
most common option is to select the <userinput>http</userinput>
source.  The <userinput>ftp</userinput> source is also acceptable, but
tends to be somewhat slower making connections.

</para><para>

The next step during the configuration of network package sources is
to tell <command>apt-setup</command> which country you live in.  This
configures which of the official Debian Internet mirrors you will
connect to.  Depending on which country you select, you will be presented
with a list of possible servers.  It's generally fine to pick the one at
the top of the list, but any of them should work. Note however that the
mirror list provided by the installation was generated when this version
of Debian was released and some mirrors may no longer be available.

</para><para>

After you have selected a mirror, you will be asked if a proxy server
should be used. A proxy server is a server that will forward all your
HTTP and/or FTP requests to the Internet and is most often used to regulate
and optimize access to the Internet on corporate networks. In some networks
only the proxy server is allowed access to the Internet, in which case you
will have to enter the name of the proxy server. You may also have to
include an user name and password. Most home users will not need to specify
a proxy server, although some ISPs may provide proxy servers for their
users.

</para><para>

After you select a mirror, your new network package source will be tested.
If all goes well, you will be prompted whether you want to add another
package source. If you have any problems using the package source you selected,
try using a different mirror (either from your country list or from the
global list), or try using a different network package source.

</para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>
