<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!-- -*- DocBook -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
    "/usr/share/sgml/docbook/dtd/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
 <!ENTITY % xml.features  "INCLUDE">
 <!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC
      "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.2//EN"
      "/usr/share/sgml/docbook/dtd/xml/4.2/dbcentx.mod"> %dbcent;
 <!ENTITY % commondata     SYSTEM "common.ent"        > %commondata;
 <!ENTITY % urlsdata       SYSTEM "urls.ent"          > %urlsdata;
]>


<article>

<articleinfo>
<title>
&debian; Installer internationalisation and localisation documentation
</title>
<authorgroup>
  <author>
  <firstname>Christian</firstname>
  <surname>Perrier</surname>
  </author>

  <author>
  <firstname>Dennis</firstname>
  <surname>Stampfer</surname>
  </author>

  <author>
  <firstname>Petter</firstname>
  <surname>Reinholdtsen</surname>
  </author>

</authorgroup>

<abstract>
<para>
This document describes how Debian Installer (D-I) internationalisation and localisation are handled.
</para>

<para>
It is aimed at being used as a reference for all D-I translators and
developers when i18n/l10n topics are involved.
</para>
</abstract>

<copyright>
 <year>2002-2005
 <trademark class="copyright">
 </trademark>
 </year>
 <holder>Christian Perrier</holder>
</copyright>
<copyright>
 <year>2003-2005
 <trademark class="copyright"></trademark>
 </year> 
 <holder>Dennis Stampfer</holder>
</copyright>
<copyright>
 <year>2001-2005
 <trademark class="copyright"></trademark>
 </year> 
 <holder>Petter Reinholdtsen</holder>
</copyright>

<legalnotice>
<para>

This manual is free software; you may redistribute it and/or modify it
under the terms of the GNU General Public License. 
</para>
</legalnotice>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="abstract">
<title>
Abstract</title>

<para> 
The first section explains how translators need to organize their work
in order to have the whole &debian; installation process localized
(l10n) in their own language. It also explains how to get l10n for
Debian packages involved during the installation process though not
strictly speaking part of Debian Installer.
</para>

<para>The second section explains how Debian Installer (D-I) packages
maintainers should proceed for getting the D-I packages they maintain
properly internationalised (i18n) and thus ready for translation
(localisation==l10n).
</para>

<para>
The third section explains <emphasis>level 1</emphasis> translations are handled in
Debian Installer (D-I) packages.
</para>

<para>
This document is maintained up-to-date according to processes and methods by
the D-I internationalisation (i18n) coordinator.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Debian Installer i18n coordination
</title>

<para>
Some members of the D-I team have taken the responsibility of the
coordination of the translators and translators teams. In all
documents regarding D-I i18n process, they are referred to as <emphasis>the D-I
i18n coordinator</emphasis>.
</para>

<para>Please look at the <filename>i18n/coordination.txt</filename> file to get information about
the current D-I i18n coordinators.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
The work of translators
</title>

<sect2>
<title>
Method for working on D-I translations
</title>

<para>
When starting to translate D-I, please follow the following steps:
</para>

<sect3>
<title>
Initial step (<emphasis>level 0</emphasis>)
</title>

<para>
Several actions are needed for a new language to be supported in
D-I. These will be called the <emphasis>level 0</emphasis> of the translation work.
</para>

<sect4>
<title>
First contact with D-I development team
</title>

<para>
Get in touch with the D-I i18n coordinator. Please provide your real
name (the Debian Project encourages the use of real names) and
possibly your GPG key (this is not mandatory but could help in the
future).
</para>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Prerequisites
</title>

<para>
For a language to be supported completely in the installer and later
in the Debian distribution, at least "locale" must exist for this 
language.
</para>

<para>
This document is not aimed at describing locales and what is the information
they contain. As a rough description, a locale describes specific properties
of a language/country combination. For instance, the "de_DE" locale describes
specifics of the german language in Germany:
</para>

	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  name of the days of the weeks (and abbreviations)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		name of the months (and abbreviations)
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  official symbol of the currency
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  writing numbers
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  writing dates
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  writing telephone numbers
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  collation order for sorting alphabetic lists
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  usual paper size
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  .../...
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>

<para>
Writing a locale need to be used to the locale files format, so don't be
afraid by this : this part may be handled by a i18n specialist
in Debian, most often one of the D-I i18n coordinators. You will only need to
provide him/her the above informations when (s)he will need it.
</para>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Request for early support for your language in Debian Installer
</title>

<para>
First needed is having your language added to languagechooser (the
package responsible for choosing language at the very beginning of the
Debian Installer process) This will often be handled by the D-I i18n
coordinator.
</para>

<para>The D-I i18n coordinator will indicate you the ISO-639 code for your
language if you don't already know it, as well as the official English
name for your language. In the rest of this document, the language
code will be replaced by <emphasis>xx</emphasis>.
</para>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Indications regarding your language
</title>

<para>
Please provide the translation for your language name (with an initial
capital letter if capital letters make sense in your language) and
send it to the i18n coordinator as a single UTF-8 file containing the
language name in your own language. <emphasis>UTF-8 is mandatory here</emphasis>. For
instance, the French translator will send a file containing the single
word: <emphasis>Français</emphasis>.
</para>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Indications about the handling of your language in Linux console
</title>

<para>
During initial discussions with the D-I i18n coordinator you will need
to provide details about the method for displaying your language in a
console environment (display under the X Window System is out of scope
for D-I). If you already know about console font and keyboard
specifics, please provide this information (D-I and more generally
Debian uses the console-tools and console-data packages for handling
console input and output).
</para>

<para>Provide a file containing all characters needed for properly
displaying your language, not including characters which are part of
the ASCII character set (characters in the 32-127 range). This file
will be used by the font reduction mechanism (the UTF-8 font used in
D-I is reduced for size constraints) and is needed for all Latin
languages and all non-Latin languages with reasonably sized
alphabet. If you language uses hundreds or thousands of characters,
the use of this file is not needed and you should rather check that
the bterm-unifont package includes all characters needed by your
language. Content example for French: 
<emphasis>àâéèëêïîôùûüÿÀÂÉÈËÊÔÙÛÜŸÇ°</emphasis>.
</para>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Locales
</title>

<para>
If you're aware of it, please provide the name of the most used
locale(s) for your language. The D-I i18n coordinator will check
whether such locale already exists in Debian. If no locale for your
language already exists, the D-I i18n coordinator will build one and
will probably need your help for this. Of course, if you have some
knowledge about locale files writing, you can provide one by yourself
or help for this.  
</para>

<para>If you don't know what a <emphasis>locale</emphasis> is, don't worry : the D-I i18n
coordinator will handle this part of the work;
</para>

<para>Please mention if your language is usually spoken in more than one
country. Such checks will be made by the i18n coordinator, but your help
will be appreciated here.
</para>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Prepare yourself to translation
</title>

<para>
If you're not used to GNU gettext files (PO files) handling and the
use of dedicated PO files editors and tools, please refer to the
<emphasis><ulink url="#editors_and_tools">Editors and tools</ulink></emphasis> section of this document.
</para>

<para>In any cases, please refer to the <emphasis>Translation methods and advices</emphasis>
for information and guidelines about the way you should work.
</para>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Enter the D-I team
</title>

<para>
Be aware that involving yourself into D-I translation is not a
<emphasis>one-time</emphasis> work. The Debian Installer is always work in progress and
your translations may require some attention or some new work from
time to time even after you completed it.
</para>

<para>When you start working on translations, please announce this in the
<email>&email-debian-boot-list;</email> mailing list and get in touch with the
D-I localisation coordinator. You will then be listed as a translator
in your language and thus will get, by private mail, important general
announcements by the i18n coordinator.
</para>

<para>Welcome on board : you are now a D-I team member! In D-I development
process, translators are NOT a special kind of developers. I18n and
l10n are full part of the development and translators are involved in
all this development. Several D-I developers started by working on
translations and later contributed to other pieces of code.
</para>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Follow the D-I development
</title>

<para>
You are strongly invited to subscribe to <email>&email-debian-boot-list;</email> and debian-i18n
mailing lists.
</para>

<para>The first is the general mailing list about Debian Installer
development. This is a quite high traffic list, though easy to filter
because a lot of mails here are automatic mails when new packages are
uploaded or bugs are reported.
</para>

<para>The latter is a low traffic list for discussions about topics related
to internationalisation (i18n : the actions and tools used
for preparing software to work in different languages and
environments) and localisation (l10n : the actions and tools used for
doing softare translation) in the Debian GNU/Linux distribution.
</para>

<para>Mailing lists subscription information and other informations related
to Debian mailing lists are available at &url-debian-list-archives;.
</para>

<para>If you happen to not be able anymore to work on the translation of
D-I, please notify the i18n coordinator. When doing so, please make
your best for pointing him/her to other l10n resources who may be
able to continue the work on your language. Don't be ashamed
quitting : this is the way free software development works : real life
has its constraints and all of us have to deal with them...
</para>

</sect4>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>
The seven steps to heaven or <emphasis>how to reach World Domination</emphasis>
</title>

<para>
The Debian Installer translator process has been divided into several
<emphasis>levels</emphasis> which represent steps towards a complete translation of the
installer for the Debian GNU/Linux distribution and, more generally,
the translation of the whole distribution itself.
</para>

<para>You are suggested to work in the order detailed below, level by
level. Inside each level, complete the steps in the described
order. This order is related to the degree of <emphasis>importance</emphasis> of each
material which needs translation.
</para>

<para>The sections below will give you details and context about each level
components as well as instructions for getting the material which
needs translations as well as sending back the translated material.
</para>

<para>Please read them carefully, even if you already worked on Debian
translations and even if you are an old timer D-I translator.
</para>

<para>Due to the granularity of Debian work and more specifically the
packages system, you may find differences between the various packages
a bit annoying (some use SVN, some others CVS, some other no
repository at all...). This is a consequence of the work organisation
in Debian. The general i18n team is working on simplifications of
translators work by <emphasis>hiding</emphasis> all the gory details from
translators. This has not been achieved yet...
</para>

<sect4>
<title>
Levels summary
</title>

<para>
The details about what follows are in the next section. This list is here
for being used as a quick reference by translators who are well used to
the levels concepts.
</para>

<para>Beginners are requested to read the next section as well.
</para>

	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 1 : all core D-I packages
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 2 : all non core D-I material involved for user interaction
		screens during a *default priority* installation of
		a Debian base system with default choices:
	      </para>
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    newt (programs)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    base-config (programs and debconf)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    shadow (debconf)                  
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    tasksel (programs, debconf, tasks)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    iso-codes (iso_3166)              
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    console-data (debconf)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    exim4 (debconf)       
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 3 : all non-core D-I material involved for user interaction
		screens during any type of installation of a Debian base
		system. This will include rarely used packages and packages
		which may display their screens under certain circumstances:
	      </para>
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    popularity-contest (debconf)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    discover1 (debconf)  
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    aptitude (programs)  
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    pppconfig (programs) 
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    xdebconfigurator (debconf) 
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    localization-config (debconf)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    console-common (debconf)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    dictionaries-common (debconf)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    pcmcia-cs (debconf)          
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 4 : all packages which may display messages to the screen
		during any type of installation of a Debian base system:
	      </para>
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    debconf (program)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    discover1 (program)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    dpkg (program)     
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    apt (program)      
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    shadow (program)   
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 5 : all Debian base system packages (debconf+programs)
		</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 6 : all Debian packages of priority Standard (debconf+programs)
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 7 : all other Debian packages (debconf+programs)
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>


</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Level 1 of translation
</title>

<para>
All level 1 translations are related to D-I <emphasis>first stage</emphasis>.
</para>

<sect5>
<title>
D-I core files
</title>

<para>
In D-I jargon, the <emphasis>first stage</emphasis> is the part of D-I which occurs from
the initial boot up to the first (and only) reboot of the system. All
user interactions screens shown to users during this stage are part of
the first level for l10n. This means that the translation work must
start by these. 
</para>

<para>
The major part of translatable material here is spread over core D-I
packages. The package development is handled in the main D-I
Subversion (SVN) repository.
</para>

<para>
Some material (country names and keyboard maps names) are handled in
non core D-I packages. This material will be part of the level 2 of
translations.
</para>

<para>
If the translation work for your language did not already started, you
have to copy the <filename>packages/po/template.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> (where xx is the
ISO-639 code for your language) and you can start working on
translations (please have a look at the paragraph giving some advices
about tools and methods).
</para>

<para>
Translators who already used the <emphasis>old</emphasis> method for translating D-I core
packages, please refer to the <ulink url="#transition">Transition from "old" (pre-RC1) work
method to "new" work method</ulink> section in the <ulink url="#appendix">Appendix</ulink> section at the
end of this document.
</para>

<para>
The D-I core file uses hundred of strings which represent the content
of the screens which are or may be shown to D-I users during the
installation process.
</para>

<para>
Please carefully read the comments which may be put with these strings
as they may contain indications or hints for translators.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for level 1
</emphasis>

<para>
You are highly encouraged to work on a local copy of the Subversion
repository for D-I. See <ulink url="#working_with_svn">Working with D-I Subversion repository</ulink>
section of this document.
</para>

<para>If you can't work with SVN:
Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level1/files/xx/packages_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level1/files/xx/packages_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level1/POT/template.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level1/POT/template.pot</ulink>
</para>

<para>Copy <filename>template.pot</filename> file to <filename>xx.po</filename> or use the existing
<filename>xx.po</filename>.
</para>



<emphasis>
Sending/commiting files for level 1
</emphasis>

<para>
You are highly encouraged to work on a local copy of the Subversion
repository for D-I. See <ulink url="#working_with_svn">Working with D-I Subversion repository</ulink>
section of this document.
</para>

<para>If, for some reason, you can't work with SVN, the translation file
should be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>debian-installer</emphasis>
package. Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink>
section of this document.
</para>

</sect5>
</sect4>


<sect4 id="level2">
<title>
Level 2 of translations
</title>

<para>
Most level 2 translations are related to D-I <emphasis>second stage</emphasis>.
</para>

<para>In D-I jargon, the <emphasis>second stage</emphasis> is the part of D-I which occurs from
the system reboot up to the <emphasis>Installation is finished</emphasis> screen followed
by the first <command>login:</command> prompt. This stage is, technically speaking, the
whole run of the base-config program.
</para>

<para>All packages which interact with users during this second stage while
a Debian base system is installed, with the defaults level of
complexity for the asked questions (<emphasis>high priority installs</emphasis> in D-I
jargon)) are considered part of the <emphasis>level 2</emphasis> of l10n for D-I.
</para>

<para>This includes two packages maintained by the D-I team as well as a few
other <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian packages:
</para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		newt
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		base-config (D-I team)
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		shadow
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		tasksel (D-I team)
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		iso-codes
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		console-data
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		exim4
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

<para>Iso-codes and console-data packages material is indeed used in D-I
first stage but including them in the level 1 of translation would
induce too much complication to statistics maintenance and would be
confusing for translators. This is why they are considered part of the
level 2.
</para>

<para>Please follow the order below for translating files. This means that
you should first translate base-config, then shadow and so on...
</para>

<sect5>
<title>
Newt
</title>

<para>
The newt package is a library (whiptail) which includes widgets used by
the most popular interface to the debconf software, the software
involved in packages configuration steps. These widgets include the <emphasis>Yes</emphasis> or  <emphasis>No</emphasis> widgets used by boolean templates, as well as the  <emphasis>OK</emphasis> or  <emphasis>Abort</emphasis> buttons
text.
</para>

<para>The translation of newt is very simple as the above shows.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for newt
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package
maintainer currently does no use any CVS or SVN repository.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material is in one single file:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>po/newt.pot</filename> : whiptail widgets translatable text
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/newt_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/newt_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/newt_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/newt_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for newt
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation file must be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>newt</emphasis>
package. Mention that the file is the <emphasis>debconf</emphasis> translation.
</para>
<para>
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

</sect5>

<sect5>
<title>
Base-config
</title>

<para>
The base-config package is the core of the second stage of the
installation of a Debian system. It consists in a set of tasks which
may be called from a general menu. Each of these tasks is responsible
for a specific operation (such as clock/timezone settings, users
creation...). Some of these tasks are directly part of base-config,
some others are handled by separate packages (which translations are
part of level 2 and level 3)
</para>

<para>This package is, technically speaking, a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian
package. However, the package maintainer is the D-I team and the
package is managed and developed the same way core D-I packages are
managed. In particular, translators automatically get commit access to
the base-config SVN repository when they request for commit access to
D-I repository.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for base-config
</emphasis>

<para>
The base-config package maintainers use a SVN repository hosted on
Alioth.  Direct SVN commit/checkout access is automatically granted to
D-I registered translators.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material is spread over two files. These are, by
order of importance (most important first):
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>debian/po/templates.pot</filename> : screen shown to users while the program runs.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>po/base-config.pot</filename>      : messages displayed by the program;
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>If you can't work with SVN:
</para>

<para>Check whether incomplete translations exist for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/base-config_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/base-config_po_xx.po</ulink>
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/base-config_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/base-config_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If they don't exist, get the POT files at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/base-config_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/base-config_po.pot</ulink>
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/base-config_debian_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/base-config_debian_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending/commiting files for base-config
</emphasis>

<para>
If you commit your translations directly to SVN, don't forget to
update the debian/changelog file accordingly. See <ulink url="#updating_changelog">Updating
"debian/changelog" entries for Debian packages</ulink> section below in this
document.
</para>

<para>If, for some reason, you can't work with SVN, the translation files
should be reported as bugs against the <emphasis>base-config</emphasis> package. Don't
forget to mention whether the file(s) are program translations (po/
directory) or <emphasis>debconf</emphasis> translations (debian/po/ directory).
</para>

<para>
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
Shadow
</title>

<para>
The shadow package includes several core utilities for a Unix system
(login, passwd...) as well as the root user password setting step and
the creation of a non-privileged user.
</para>

<para>It is installed and configured from base-config which triggers some of
these operations and thus implies user input.
</para>

<para>The programs (passwd, login and so on) are themselves i18n'ed but this
translation is not considered in level 2, but in level 4 (see the
details about this level). The only level 2 translation is the
<emphasis>debconf</emphasis> translation (user input screens).
</para>

<para>Please be very careful when translating the shadow user interaction
screens. The most important screen is the one asking for the root
password. Please keep it short so that the screen fits on one
screen. Avoid jargon (D-I is targeted to low skilled users and to Unix
beginners). For instance, try possibly to keep the mention of <emphasis>root</emphasis>
being the system administrator. 
</para>

<para>Another potential source of confusion are the screens asking about the
newly created user real name and login name. The English version tries
to be clear about what is what...so please try to keep your
translation clear also.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for shadow (level 2)
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package
maintainer currently does no use any CVS or SVN repository. However,
he delegated the handling of the package's localisation to the D-I
i18n coordinator.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material for level 2 is in one single file:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>debian/po/templates.pot</filename> : screen shown to users while the program runs.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/shadow_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/shadow_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/shadow_debian_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/shadow_debian_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for shadow
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation file must be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>shadow</emphasis>
package. Mention that the file is the <emphasis>debconf</emphasis> translation.
</para>

<para>Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

<para>For shadow, most translations are included in specific releases of the
package, built by the D-I i18n coordinator (these are called <emphasis>l10n
NMUs</emphasis>).
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
Tasksel
</title>

<para>
The tasksel package, called from base-config for each installation, is
responsible for proposing <emphasis>tasks</emphasis> for trigerring the installation of
Debian packages. A <emphasis>task</emphasis> is a collection of several individual Debian
packages all related to a specific activity.
</para>

<para>The tasksel package is, technically speaking, a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian
package. However, the package maintainer is the D-I team and the
package is managed and developed the same way core D-I packages are
managed. In particular, translators automatically get commit access to
the tasksel SVN repository when they request for commit access to
D-I repository.
</para>

<para>As you will notice, several tasks are related to localised
environments. These tasks install packages that are likely to be
useful when using Debian with the mentioned languages. These tasks are
automatically tagged for install when the given localised environment
has been used with D-I.
</para>

<para>For instance, if D-I is run in French language, the <emphasis>french</emphasis> task will
be automatically installed (not the <emphasis>-desktop</emphasis> variant which is
optional because, through the dependency system, it triggers the
installation of X Window System and huge packages such as OpenOffice).
</para>

<para>If your language does not currently have such task, feel free to
provide one. Look for example tasks in the tasks/ directory of the
source pakcage.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for tasksel
</emphasis>

<para>
The tasksel package maintainers (the D-I team) use a SVN
repository hosted on Alioth.  Direct SVN commit/checkout access is
automatically granted to D-I registered translators.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material is spread over three files. These are, by
order of importance (most important first):
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>debian/po/templates.pot</filename>   : screens displayed to users for prompting
                              them about tasks to be installed;
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>tasks/po/debian-tasks.pot</filename> : <emphasis>tasks</emphasis> names and descriptions. Tasks are 
                              a common way to have several Debian packages
                              installed at a same time. They group together
                              packages with common goals;
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>po/tasksel.pot</filename>:             messages and errors displayed by the program.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>If you can't work with SVN:
</para>

<para>Check whether incomplete translations exist for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/tasksel_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/tasksel_po_xx.po</ulink>
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/tasksel_tasks_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/tasksel_tasks_po_xx.po</ulink>
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/tasksel_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/tasksel_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If they don't exist, get the POT files at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/tasksel_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/tasksel_po.pot</ulink>
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/tasksel_tasks_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/tasksel_tasks_po.pot</ulink>
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/tasksel_debian_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/tasksel_debian_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending/commiting files for tasksel
</emphasis>

<para>
If you commit your translations directly to SVN, don't forget to
update the debian/changelog file accordingly. See other entries in
this file for reference.
</para>

<para>If, for some reason, you can't work with SVN, the translation files
should be reported as bugs against the <emphasis>tasksel</emphasis> package. Don't forget
to mention whether the file(s) are program translations (po/
directory), <emphasis>debconf</emphasis> translations (debian/po/ directory) or tasks
translations (tasks/po directory).
</para>

<para>Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
Iso-codes
</title>

<para>
A core D-I package (countrychooser) uses country names and codes from the
iso-codes package. The country name translations are taken from this
package instead of just sitting in the countrychooser package.
</para>

<para>For this reason, you need to translate the iso_3166.tab file in the
iso-codes package.
</para>

<para>The ISO-3166 list includes all <emphasis>countries, regions ar area of specific
geopolitical interest</emphasis> in the world. Be aware that this translation is
far from being a trivial work and may very quickly turn into some deep
and complicated political difficulties. The original English names are
those used officially by the relevant countries to design
themselves. Please make your best for staying as neutral and close to
these names as possibles. Some countries Foreign Affairs (or
equivalent) ministries keep lists of <emphasis>country</emphasis> names translations in
their own languages. Please use them as a reference if you can.
</para>

<para>If in doubt, please contact the iso-codes package maintainer :
<email>iso-codes@packages.debian.org</email>.
</para>

<para>If you have time (but possibly, AFTER other D-I related translations),
you may also translate other translatable material in this package
such as the ISO-639 files (language names) and ISO-4217 files
(currencies names). Please note that this is a very tedious task which
may turn to be very difficult (are you aware of the correct translation
of more than 450 languages names in your own language?).
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for iso-codes
</emphasis>

<para>
The iso-codes package maintainer uses a CVS repository hosted on Alioth.
</para>

<para>Direct CVS commit/checkout access may be requested to him: 
<email>iso-codes@packages.debian.org</email>. Please provide your Alioth
account name.
</para>

<para>The file to be translated is hosted in the iso_3166 directory in the
package's source tree. If no translation for your language exists,
copy <filename>iso_3166.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> and translate it.
</para>

<para>If you can't work with CVS:
</para>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/iso-codes_iso_3166_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/iso-codes_iso_3166_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/iso-codes_iso_3166.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/iso-codes_iso_3166.pot</ulink>
</para>

<para>copy <filename>iso-codes_iso_3166.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> or use the existing
<filename>iso-codes_iso_3166_xx.po</filename>.
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending/commiting files for iso-codes
</emphasis>

<para>
If you commit your translations directly to CVS, don't forget to
update the debian/changelog file accordingly. See other entries in
this file for reference.
</para>

<para>If, for some reason, you can't work with CVS, the translation files
should be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>iso-codes</emphasis> package.  Please see
the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of this document.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
Console-data
</title>

<para>
A core D-I package (kbd-chooser) uses keyboard names (and mapping
files) from the console-data package.  Thus, in order to get it
completely translated, translators need to translate console-data
debconf templates.
</para>

<para>You must <emphasis>translate</emphasis> the keyboard layout names to <emphasis>real</emphasis> names. For
this, please look at the <filename>en.po</filename> file (which you can get at
<ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/en/console-data_debian_po_en.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/en/console-data_debian_po_en.po</ulink>)
as ths file includes English <emphasis>translations</emphasis> of the original keyboard
map names. For instance <emphasis>de-latin1-nodeadkeys</emphasis> is translated to
"German" there, so you should use the name for <emphasis>German</emphasis> in your own
language as translation of <emphasis>de-latin1-nodeadkeys</emphasis> (in that specific
case, the <emphasis>nodeadkeys</emphasis> part is not translated, as you may see, there
are technical reasons for this : this is why using the English
<emphasis>translation</emphasis> as a reference is highly recommended).
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for console-data
</emphasis>

<para>
The console-data package maintainer uses a SVN repository hosted on Alioth.
</para>
<para>
Direct SVN commit/checkout access may be requested to him: 
<email>console-data@packages.debian.org</email>. Please provide your Alioth
account name.
</para>

<para>The file to be translated is hosted in debian/po in the package's
source tree. If no translation for your language exists, copy
<filename>templates.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> and translate it.
</para>

<para>If you can't work with SVN:
</para>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/console-data_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/console-data_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>
<para>
If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/console-data_debian_po_templates.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/console-data_debian_po_templates.pot</ulink>
</para>

<para>copy <filename>console-data_debian_po_templates.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> or use the
existing <filename>console-data_debian_po_xx.po</filename>.
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending/commiting files for console-data
</emphasis>

<para>
If you commit your translations directly to SVN, don't forget to
update the debian/changelog file accordingly. See other entries in
this file for reference.
</para>

<para>If, for some reason, you can't work with SVN, the translation file
should be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>console-data</emphasis> package.
</para>
<para>
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
Exim4
</title>

<para>
The exim4 package installs the Exim Mail Transport Agent (MTA). It is
installed by default on all newly installed Debian GNU/Linux systems
as Exim has always been the default Debian MTA (even if other MTA may
be used and installed later by the system administrator).
</para>

<para>It is installed and configured from base-config which triggers some of
its configuration steps and thus involves user input.
</para>

<para>The translation of some exim4 user input screens may be tricky. More
particularly, the screen giving the choice between all possible type
of configurations is not easy to handle for translators : each
individual choice contains a description of what this choice means :
THIS MUST BE KEPT SHORTER than 72 characters, otherwise, the display
will be cut on most screens.
</para>

<para>Also try to keep the long description of this specific screen as short
as possible and still be clear and avoid jargon. Remember that this
screen will be shown on every installation, even default ones (which
are very likely to be used by low skilled users).
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for exim4
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package
maintainer currently does no use any CVS or SVN repository.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material is in one single file:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>debian/po/templates.pot</filename> : screen shown to users while the program runs.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/exim4-config_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/exim4-config_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/exim4-config_debian_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/exim4-config_debian_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for exim4
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation file must be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>exim4</emphasis>
package. Mention that the file is the <emphasis>debconf</emphasis> translation.
</para>
<para>
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

</sect5>
</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Level 3 of translations
</title>

<para>
The level 3 of translations groups together the translation of
steps which are not always been used during installation made with
D-I. These steps are optional steps and do no occur on default
installs.
</para>

<para>All packages which interact with users during second stage optional
steps are considered part of the level 3 of l10n for D-I.
</para>

<para>This includes the following <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian packages:

	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    popularity-contest
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  discover1 (debconf)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  aptitude
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  pppconfig
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  xdebconfigurator
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  localization-config
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  console-common
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  dictionaries-common
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  pcmcia-cs
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
</para>
	   
<sect5>
<title>
Popularity-contest
</title>

<para>
The popularity-contest (very often nicknamed as <emphasis>popcon</emphasis>) package is
automatically installed on every Debian system as it is part of what
is called the <emphasis>base</emphasis> system.
</para>

<para>This package installs scripts for periodically sending to Debian
Developers statistics about installed packages on the user's
system. These statistics are used when building releases, for
instances for getting informations about the most used architecture
ports as well as the most used packages.
</para>

<para>Of course, as the Debian Project is highly committed to the respect of
user's privacy, this survey is disabled by default. So, when the
package is installed, it prompts the user whether (s)he wants to
activate this survey system.
</para>

<para>Translators must be very careful with this specific translation :
keep the prompt very clear as it is in English and KEEP IT SHORT.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for popularity-contest
</emphasis>

<para>
The popularity-contest package maintainers team (which works close to
D-I team) uses a CVS repository hosted on Alioth.  CVS commit is
currently managed by the D-I i18n coordinator as a delagated work from
the popcon development team.
</para>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/popularity-contest_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/files/xx/popularity-contest_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/popularity-contest_debian_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level2/POT/popularity-contest_debian_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<para>copy <filename>popularity-contest_debian_po.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> or use the existing
<filename>popularity-contest_debian_po_xx.po</filename>.
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for popularity-contest
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation file must be reported as a bug against the
<emphasis>popularity-contest</emphasis> package (do NOT use the <emphasis>popcon</emphasis>
nickname!). Mention that the file is the <emphasis>debconf</emphasis> translation.
</para>
<para>
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

<para>The translation will most often be quickly committed by the D-I i18n
coordinator with a short message back to you mentioning that the bug
fix is <emphasis>pending</emphasis>.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
discover1 (debconf)
</title>

<para>
The discover1 program is aimed at automatic recognition of hardware on
Debian GNU/Linux systems. Originally developed by Progeny developers
(several of which are very active Debian Developers), it is now
maintained by the D-I team.
</para>

<para>Discover1 will be replaced by the version 2 of the program in the
future. However, this version is not yet used by D-I and is anyway not
internationalised.
</para>

<para>Discover1 is also to be configured during its installation if D-I
<emphasis>expert</emphasis> mode is used. This is why the <emphasis>debconf</emphasis> translation is part
of the level 3 of D-I translations.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for discover1 (debconf)
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package maintainer
team (the D-I team) use a SVN repository. The D-I i18n coordinator
handles commits for l10n material.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material for debconf is in
one file (another file is part of level 4):
</para>

<para>
<filename>debian/po/templates.pot</filename> : configuration screens (debconf)
</para>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/discover1_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/discover1_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/discover1_debian_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/discover1_debian_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for discover1 (debconf)
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation files must be reported as bugs against the <emphasis>discover1</emphasis>
package (BEWARE of the "1"!). 
Please mention that the file is the <emphasis>debconf</emphasis> translation.
</para>
<para>
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

<para>The translation will most often be quickly committed by the D-I i18n
coordinator with a short message back to you mentioning that the bug
fix is <emphasis>pending</emphasis>.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
aptitude
</title>

<para>
The aptitude program is an combination of interactive and
non-interactive tools for installing Debian packages. For long-time
users of Debian, it may be seen as the replacement for both dselect
and apt.
</para>

<para>It is used from base-config when packages are installed. It is also
used interactively when the user chooses the option for installing
individual packages of his/her choice.
</para>

<para>The program uses a text-based menu system when used interactively and
includes a lot of output messages when it is run non-interactively.
</para>

<para>Aptitude's full translation is a huge work because there are hundreds
of strings in the POT file. Moreover, this requires some good
knowledge of several Debian package managements concepts. It is
recommended that this translation is handled by an experienced Debian
system administrator.
</para>

<para>Without any doubt, aptitude's translation is among the most difficult
translations involved in D-I translation. It has an impact far
outside Debian Installer because aptitude is likely to be used all
along the life of a Debian system.
</para>

<para>If you are not confident in your ability to do this translation, just
jump over it until you find some other translator. D-I translators
working with a translation team should ask for help to this
team. Also try asking to your local Debian users groups.
</para>

<para>Aptitude includes a small help file, which may be translated as
well. However, this translation does not use GNU gettext, so the
translation is quite tricky. See the help* files in aptitude's source
tree.
</para>

<para>Aptitude's documentation may also be translated. See the doc/
directory in the package's source tree.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for aptitude
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package maintainer
uses a SVN repository for the program development (the Debian package
is handled in a separate SVN repository). The maintainer delegated the
handling of l10n to the D-I i18n coordinator.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material followed by D-I statistics tools is in
one single file:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>po/aptitude.pot</filename> : all screens translations
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/aptitude_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/aptitude_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/aptitude_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/aptitude_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<para>Be aware that aptitude is still under heavy development, so upstream
strings are very likely to change or be added. So, be prepared to
closely follow these changes. But, in any case, even partial
translation will help the users of a language.
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for aptitude
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation files must be reported as bugs against the <emphasis>aptitude</emphasis>
package. 
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

<para>The translation will most often be quickly committed by the D-I i18n
coordinator with a short message back to you mentioning that the bug
fix is <emphasis>pending</emphasis>.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
pppconfig
</title>

<para>
The pppconfig package is dedicated at configuring PPP systems. It
helps the users in configuring one or several PPP peers as well as PPP
interface details.
</para>

<para>It is installed and configured from base-config when run at <emphasis>medium</emphasis>
priority (thus, for <emphasis>expert</emphasis> installs).
</para>

<para>The program uses a dialog-like interface for building a set of menus
which the users navigate in.
</para>

<para>The paragraph formatting is hard-coded with "\n" which represents
carriage returns. You must be careful about keeping the lines below 72
characters even if this ends in more or less "\n" then the original
English file. THIS DOES NOT HARM even if your PO editing tools warns
you about this.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for pppconfig
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package
maintainer currently does no use any CVS or SVN repository.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material is in one single file:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>po/pppconfig.pot</filename> : all screens translations
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/pppconfig_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/pppconfig_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/pppconfig_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/pppconfig_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for pppconfig
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation file must be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>pppconfig</emphasis>
package. 
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
Xdebconfigurator
</title>

<para>
The xdebconfigurator package is a tool aimed at automatic configuration of the
X-Window server component.
</para>

<para>It is called from base-config when the installed system includes
a X Window System server software.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for xdebconfigurator
</emphasis>

<para>
The xdebconfigurator package is maintained by the Debian-Edu project
maintainers.  Direct SVN commit/checkout access to Debian-Edu may be requested to the project administrators. Please provide your Alioth account
name.
</para>

<para>The file to be translated is hosted in debian/po in the package's
source tree. If no translation for your language exists, copy
<filename>templates.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> and translate it.
</para>

<para>The translatable part only includes the base-config menu
entry. Remember that, being a menu entry, its translation must be kept
short: below 70 columns</para>


<para>If you can't work with SVN:
</para>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/xdebconfigurator_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/xdebconfigurator_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>
<para>
If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/xdebconfigurator_debian_po_templates.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/xdebconfigurator_debian_po_templates.pot</ulink>
</para>

<para>copy <filename>xdebconfigurator_debian_po_templates.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> or use the
existing <filename>xdebconfigurator_debian_po_xx.po</filename>.
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending/commiting files for xdebconfigurator
</emphasis>

<para>
If you commit your translations directly to SVN, don't forget to
update the debian/changelog file accordingly. See other entries in
this file for reference.
</para>

<para>If, for some reason, you can't work with SVN, the translation file
should be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>xdebconfigurator</emphasis> package.
</para>
<para>
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
Localization-config
</title>

<para>
The localization-config package is a tool aimed at automatic
configuration of locales-related settings in several key packages.
</para>

<para>It is called from base-config except in the case the installed
system has no localization at all.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for localization-config
</emphasis>

<para>
The localization-config package is maintained by the Debian-Edu project
maintainers.  Direct SVN commit/checkout access to Debian-Edu may be requested to the project administrators. Please provide your Alioth account
name.
</para>

<para>The file to be translated is hosted in debian/po in the package's
source tree. If no translation for your language exists, copy
<filename>templates.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> and translate it.
</para>

<para>The translatable part only includes the base-config menu
entry. Remember that, being a menu entry, its translation must be kept
short: below 70 columns</para>

<para>If you can't work with SVN:
</para>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/localization-config_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/localization-config_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>
<para>
If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/localization-config_debian_po_templates.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/localization-config_debian_po_templates.pot</ulink>
</para>

<para>copy <filename>localization-config_debian_po_templates.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> or use the
existing <filename>localization-config_debian_po_xx.po</filename>.
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending/commiting files for localization-config
</emphasis>

<para>
If you commit your translations directly to SVN, don't forget to
update the debian/changelog file accordingly. See other entries in
this file for reference.
</para>

<para>If, for some reason, you can't work with SVN, the translation file
should be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>localization-config</emphasis> package.
</para>
<para>
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

<emphasis>
Contribute to your language/locale support in localization-config
</emphasis>

<para>As localization-config indeed pre-configures several packages
for locales-related settings, you may help its maintainer to adjust
settings for your own language. This often starts by providing the
most common xfree86 settings for keyboard for your locale and all
locales supported by your language. For this, you should contact the
package maintainer(s) at
localization-config@packages.debian.org</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
Console-common
</title>

<para>
The console-common package includes all tools for handling the console
(input and output).
</para>

<para>It is installed and configured as part of the Debian base system. Its
configuration process involves some user input and may be shown to
users during a base system install, in some occasions (but not
always).
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for console-common
</emphasis>

<para>
The console-common package maintainer uses a SVN repository hosted on
Alioth.  Direct SVN commit/checkout access may be requested to him:
<email>console-common@packages.debian.org</email>. Please provide your Alioth account
name.
</para>

<para>The file to be translated is hosted in debian/po in the package's
source tree. If no translation for your language exists, copy
<filename>templates.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> and translate it.
</para>

<para>If you can't work with SVN:
</para>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/console-common_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/console-common_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>
<para>
If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/console-common_debian_po_templates.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/console-common_debian_po_templates.pot</ulink>
</para>

<para>copy <filename>console-common_debian_po_templates.pot</filename> to <filename>xx.po</filename> or use the
existing <filename>console-common_debian_po_xx.po</filename>.
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending/commiting files for console-common
</emphasis>

<para>
If you commit your translations directly to SVN, don't forget to
update the debian/changelog file accordingly. See other entries in
this file for reference.
</para>

<para>If, for some reason, you can't work with SVN, the translation file
should be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>console-common</emphasis> package.
</para>
<para>
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
dictionaries-common
</title>

<para>
The dictionaries-common package includes all common tools for using
word dictionaries in Debian.
</para>

<para>It is installed and configured as part of the Debian base system. Its
configuration process inputs the user for choosing a word dictionary
when the installation is run at <emphasis>medium</emphasis> priority (using the <emphasis>expert</emphasis>
mode of install...or when some problem occurred earlier in the
installation process).
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for dictionaries-common
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package
maintainer currently does no use any CVS or SVN repository.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material is in one single file:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>debian/po/templates.pot</filename> : configuration screens (debconf)
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/dictionaries-common_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/dictionaries-common_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/dictionaries-common_debian_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/dictionaries-common_debian_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for dictionaries-common
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation files must be reported as a bug against the
<emphasis>dictionaries-common</emphasis> package. Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of this document.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
pcmcia-cs
</title>

<para>
The pcmcia-cs package includes all common tools for using PCMCIA
devices on a Debian system.
</para>

<para>It is installed and configured as part of the Debian base system when
the system used a PCMCIA device while being installed. Its
configuration process inputs the user about stopping the PCMCIA Card
Servivces when upgrading. This configuration screen is then shown on
some Debian installs.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for pcmcia-cs
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package
maintainer currently does no use any CVS or SVN repository.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material is in one single file:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>debian/po/templates.pot</filename> : configuration screens (debconf)
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/pcmcia-cs_debian_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/files/xx/pcmcia-cs_debian_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/pcmcia-cs_debian_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level3/POT/pcmcia-cs_debian_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for pcmcia-cs
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation files must be reported as a bug against the
<emphasis>pcmcia-cs</emphasis> package. Please see the 
<ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of this document.
</para>

</sect5>
</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Level 4 of translations
</title>

<para>
The level 4 of translations groups together the translations of
programs which may output messages to the screen but DO NOT input users.
</para>

<para>All internationalised packages which output messages to the screen
during first and second stage are considered part of the level 4 of
l10n for D-I.
</para>

<para>This includes the following <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian packages:

	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  debconf (program)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  discover1 (program)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  dpkg
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  apt
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  shadow (program)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
</para>
		  
<para>Dpkg, apt and shadow programs are very often used during the whole
life of a Debian system, so having them translated, though very
tedious, is a must-have for a good localised system.
</para>

<para>Discover1 outputs messages to the console during D-I processes just like
debconf does.
</para>

<sect5>
<title>
debconf (program)
</title>

<para>The debconf program is the softare which is used for user interaction
during Debian packages configuration step. All Debian packages should
use debconf when they need user input for installation-time configuration.
</para>

<para>Debconf may output information to the screen : this is why the
program translation is included in D-I fourth level of
translation.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for debconf (program)
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package maintainer
(the D-I team) use a SVN repository. The D-I i18n coordinator
handles commits for l10n material.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material  for program translation is in one file:
</para>

<para><filename>po/debconf.pot</filename> : program output
</para>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/files/xx/debconf_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/files/xx/debconf_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/POT/debconf_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/POT/debconf_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for debconf (program)
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation files must be reported as bugs against the <emphasis>debconf</emphasis>
package. Please mention that the file is the
<emphasis>program</emphasis> translation.  Please see the 
<ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of this document.
</para>

<para>The translation will most often be quickly committed by the D-I i18n
coordinator with a short message back to you mentioning that the bug
fix is <emphasis>pending</emphasis>.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
discover1 (program)
</title>

<para>The discover1 program is aimed at automatic recognition of hardware on
Debian GNU/Linux systems. Originally developed by Progeny developers
(several of which are very active Debian Developers), it is now
maintained by the D-I team.
</para>

<para>Discover1 will be replaced by the version 2 of the program in the
future. However, this version is not yet used by D-I and is anyway not
internationalised.
</para>

<para>Discover1 may output information to the screen : this is why the
program translation is included in D-I fourth level of
translation. The program configuration screens (<emphasis>debconf</emphasis>) are part of
the third level you should already have completed.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for discover1 (program)
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package maintainer
team (the D-I team) use a SVN repository. The D-I i18n coordinator
handles commits for l10n material.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material  for program translation is in one file:
</para>

<para><filename>po/discover.pot</filename> : program output
</para>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/files/xx/discover1_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/files/xx/discover1_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/POT/discover1_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/POT/discover1_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for discover1 (program)
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation files must be reported as bugs against the <emphasis>discover1</emphasis>
package (BEWARE of the "1"!). Please mention that the file is the
<emphasis>program</emphasis> translation.  Please see the 
<ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of this document.
</para>

<para>The translation will most often be quickly committed by the D-I i18n
coordinator with a short message back to you mentioning that the bug
fix is <emphasis>pending</emphasis>.
</para>

</sect5>

<sect5>
<title>
dpkg
</title>

<para>
The dpkg program is a low level program aimed at installing and
removing Debian packages.
</para>

<para>Including it in D-I level 4 of translation is an extension of the
scope of D-I l10n process. Dpkg does not ouput very often during a
base system install, but is very likely to be used further, either
directly invoked by the system administrator or from another program
such as aptitude, apt, or the good old dselect.
</para>

<para>Dpkg full translation is a huge work because there are hundreds of
strings in the POT file. Most of these strings are very short strings
and most of them are hard-formatted as all of them are outputted
during the use of a command-line program.
</para>

<para>Without any doubt, dpkg translation requires a good knowledge of the
Debian package management system as well as some good experience of
command-line programs translation.
</para>

<para>The developers have put comments targeted at translators for some
strings. Please read them carefully.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for dpkg
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package maintainer
team use a CVS repository, with a quite complicated branching
system. Using your own CVS checkout copy is discouraged unless you are
very aware of dpkg development process.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material followed by D-I statistics tools is in
one single file:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>po/dpkg.pot</filename> : all translations
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/files/xx/dpkg_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/files/xx/dpkg_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/POT/dpkg_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/POT/dpkg_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for dpkg
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation file must be reported as a bugs against the <emphasis>dpkg</emphasis>
package. 
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

<para>The translation will most often be committed quite quickly by one of
the dpkgpackage maintainers. However, having it included in a release
may take some time because dpkg follows a very strict development process, being a critical tool in a Debian system.
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
apt
</title>

<para>
The apt program is aimed at installing and removing Debian packages
from packages <emphasis>sources</emphasis> such as Debian HTTP/FTP mirrors, Debian CD's,
third party CD's or repositories, or local files.
</para>

<para>Including it in D-I level 4 of translation is an extension of the
scope of D-I l10n process. Apt does not ouput very often during a
base system install, but is very likely to be used further.
</para>

<para>Apt full translation is a huge work because there are hundreds of
strings in the POT file. Most of these strings are short strings
and most of them are hard-formatted as all of them are outputted
during the use of a command-line program.
</para>

<para>Similarly to dpkg, apt translation requires a good knowledge of the
Debian package management system as well as some good experience of
command-line programs translation.
</para>

<para>The developers have put comments targeted at translators for some
strings. Please read them carefully. Some of them are VERY important.
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for apt
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package maintainer
team use a CVS repository but commits are handled by the development
team. You are thus encouraged to use the files grabbed by the D-I i18n
coordinator.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material followed by D-I statistics tools is in
one single file:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>po/apt.pot</filename> : all translations
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/files/xx/apt_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/files/xx/apt_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/POT/apt_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/POT/apt_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for apt
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation file must be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>apt</emphasis>
package. 
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

<para>The translation will most often be committed quite quickly by one of
the apt package maintainers. Similarly to dpkg, the development
process of APT is very strict, so the inclusion of l10n material may
not occur very often. Be patient..:-)
</para>

</sect5>
<sect5>
<title>
Shadow
</title>

<para>
The shadow package has already been mentioned previously in this document as
part of the level 2 of translation.
</para>

<para>The utilities installed by this package have been internationalised
and, as they are core utilities for a Debian system, translating them
is likely to be made for having a good localised system.
</para>

<para>This translation is, like apt and dpkg translations, a <emphasis>program</emphasis>
translation : programs (like passwd, chpw, chsh, etc.) output, error
and help messages. Such translation is quite tedious and long term
work and need some carefulness (respect line breaks, variable
substitutions...).
</para>

<emphasis>
Getting files for shadow (level 4)
</emphasis>

<para>
This package is a <emphasis>regular</emphasis> Debian package. The package
maintainer currently does no use any CVS or SVN repository. However,
he delegated the handling of the package's localisation to the D-I
i18n coordinator.
</para>

<para>This package's l10n material for the fourth level is in one single file:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>po/shadow.pot</filename> : output/help/error messages from the programs
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>You may also look at the man/ directory as manual pages may also be
translated though this is out of the scope of this document.
</para>

<para>Check whether an incomplete translation exists for your language:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/files/xx/shadow_po_xx.po">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/files/xx/shadow_po_xx.po</ulink>
</para>

<para>If it doesn't exist, get the POT file at:
   <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/POT/shadow_po.pot">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/level4/POT/shadow_po.pot</ulink>
</para>

<emphasis>
Sending files for shadow
</emphasis>

<para>
The translation file must be reported as a bug against the <emphasis>shadow</emphasis>
package. Mention that the file is the <emphasis>programs</emphasis> translation.
</para>
<para>
Please see the <ulink url="#reporting_bugs">Reporting bugs against Debian packages</ulink> section of
this document.
</para>

<para>Most translations are included in specific releases of the package,
built by the D-I i18n coordinator (these are called <emphasis>l10n NMUs</emphasis>).
</para>

</sect5>
</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Level 5 of translations
</title>

<para>
A full translation of all packages which are part of the Debian <emphasis>base</emphasis>
system may be called the level 5 of translation.
</para>

<para>This document will not maintain a full list of these packages and the
relevant material (which may be <emphasis>programs</emphasis> translations as well as
<emphasis>debconf</emphasis> -Debian configuration system- translations).
</para>

<para>The Debian i18n team in in the process of building a centralised
system for gathering and handling l10n material for Debian
packages. The files will be grouped there according to the <emphasis>levels</emphasis>
defined here.
</para>

<para>Below is a list of packages with debconf templates that should be
translated first (as of this writing):
</para>

<para> debconf man-db console-common netbase ifupdown console-data adduser
 setserial bsdmainutils lilo
</para>


</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Level 6 of translations
</title>

<para>
A full translation of all packages which are part of the Debian <emphasis>standard</emphasis>
system may be called the level 6 of translation.
</para>

<para>similarly to level 5, there is currently no list of the concerned
packages (these are all Debian package of <emphasis>Standard</emphasis> priority). These
package are numerous and most of them already have complete or partial
upstream translation when it comes at programs translations. 
</para>

<para>First translating the debconf screens (which are Debian specific) is
recommended. Please get in touch with the Debian i18n team for details
about this process.
</para>

<para>Below is a list of packages with debconf templates that should be
translated first (as of this writing):
</para>

<para> ssh wamerican openssl locales ibritish flex
 dictionaries-common iamerican
</para>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>
Level 7 of translations
</title>

<para>
Reaching and completing this step would mean that you have reached the l10n
Holy Grail : fully translate the Debian GNU/Linux distribution in your
language and dominate the world...:-)
</para>

<para>This includes translations for ALL Debian packages, programs and
debconf. Of course, no translation team currently has achieved this
and no will in a near future, except in this document writer's dreams.
</para>

<para>Below is a list of packages with debconf templates that should be
translated first (as of this writing):
</para>

<para> apache xfree86 cupsys ntp fontconfig samba mozilla libpaper pango1.0
 cvs xscreensaver tetex-bin screen powermgmt-base mysql-dfsg
 gdm apt-listchanges discover libnet-perl openslp
</para>

</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="working_with_svn">
<title>
Working with Subversion (SVN) repositories
</title>

<sect3>
<title>
Debian Installer SVN repository (and base-config/tasksel)
</title>

<para>
Working with the Debian Installer SVN repository first requires
you to get an account on the Alioth project server. Alioth is a
project for helping at the development of free software, related to
Debian or not. Several D-I-related projects are hosted on this server.
</para>

<para>Getting an account on Alioth is easy : just go to
<ulink url="http://alioth.debian.org">http://alioth.debian.org</ulink> and follow the relevant links.
</para>

<para>Non-official Debian Developers are welcomed. They will get
<emphasis>xxxx-guest</emphasis> account names but have no other restriction of use.
</para>

<para>As soon as your account has been confirmed by the Alioth project
administrators, please contact the D-I i18n coordinator (you should
have already do so before this) and give him/her your account name.
</para>

<para>The D-I i18n coordinator will then validate your account for commit
access to the core D-I repository as well as the base-config and
tasksel Subversion repositories (they are also managed on Alioth, but
as separate projects because they aren't special <emphasis>Installer</emphasis>
packages). For details about base-config and tasksel, see <ulink url="level2">level 2</ulink> sections of this document.
</para>

<para>There is no commit restriction : translators may contribute to other
parts of D-I if they feel they can bring their experience and skills
to the project. Of course, never forget that this is team work and
follow the general work methods of the team.
</para>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>
Installing SVN
</title>

<para>  You need to install SVN (Subversion) on your system. For Debian sid or
  sarge users, just do <command>apt-get install subversion</command>. Users of Debian <emphasis>woody</emphasis>
  release may use backports from www.backports.org.  Please add this
  entry to your /etc/apt/sources.list file:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>    
    deb http://www.backports.org/debian stable subversion
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>  Or use Adam Conrad's backports:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
    deb http://people.debian.org/~adconrad woody subversion
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>  Please be aware that these backports are not officially supported by
  the Debian Project. Though their maintainers are well-known and
  respected Debian Developers, they're the only people who can
  guarantee these packages are well maintained and secured.
</para>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>
Using SVN to get and put back files
</title>

<para>  Once your account is allowed to write to the project, you can retrieve the
  full project using the checkout commands you will find on the D-I translation
  reference pages:
</para>

<para><ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/checkouts.html">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/checkouts.html</ulink>
</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="updating_changelog">
<title>
Updating <filename>debian/changelog</filename> entries for Debian packages
</title>

<para>
This section applies to translators who directly commit their
translations into packages SVN or CVS repositories.
</para>

<para>It DOES NOT apply to level 1 translations, that is the Debian
Installer <emphasis>core</emphasis> packages translations. For these translations, no
changelog updates are needed.
</para>

<para>Each change in Debian packages must be documented in the
debian/changelog file.
</para>

<para>Below is an excerpt of the changelog file for base-config:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
base-config (2.39) UNRELEASED; urgency=low

  * Updated translations: 
    - Croatian by Krunoslav Gernhard

 -- Christian Perrier &lt;bubulle@debian.org&gt;  Sat, 24 Jul 2004 08:14:13 +0200

base-config (2.38) unstable; urgency=high
.../...
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>The above means several things:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
the last released version of the package is 2.38. The SVN repository
  currently contains the future unpublished 2.39 release
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
the only change which occured since 2.38 is the update of the Croatian
  translation (made by Krunoslav Gernhard)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
the commiter of this change was Christian Perrier
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Different Debian packages may use slightly different methods and
styles for changelog maintenance. When working with SVN/CVS
repositories, always remember using the <emphasis>UNRELEASED</emphasis> entries for new
unpublished changes (add one entry if none exists).
</para>

<para>You are encourage to use the <command>debchange</command> utility from the <emphasis>devscripts</emphasis>
Debian package.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="reporting_bugs">
<title>
Reporting bugs against Debian packages regarding localisation
</title>

<para>This section applies to translators who need to send their completed
translations back to the package maintainers, especially for second or
third level packages for which no direct Subversion or CVS commit is
possible (either because the translator cannot use SVN or CVS or
because the package maintainer(s) do not encourage wide commit access).
</para>

<para>Reporting a bug to a Debian package is just sending a specially
written mail to <email>submit@bugs.debian.org</email>.
</para>

<para>The mail should include, at the top, a few special fields:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
Package: &lt;package name&gt;
Version: &lt;version of the package&gt;
Severity: &lt;bug severity&gt;
Tags: &lt;bug tags&gt;
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>Details about bug severities, tags and other information regarding bug
reports may be found at <ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org">http://bugs.debian.org</ulink>.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>
Sending bug reports from a Debian system
</title>

<para>
Translators are encouraged to use the Debian <command>reportbug</command> utility which
will handle all these formatting details for them.
</para>

<para>An example command line follows. It will report a bug against the
<emphasis>shadow</emphasis> package with the Klingon (code: tlh) translation:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
reportbug --attach=tlh.po --offline -s "shadow: [INTL:tlh] Klingon debconf templates translation" --severity=wishlist --tag=patch --tag=l10n --no-config-files shadow
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>The bug severity must be <emphasis>wishlist</emphasis>. 
</para>

<para>The bug tags must always include <emphasis>l10n</emphasis> and <emphasis>patch</emphasis>. The <emphasis>d-i</emphasis> tag
  must be used for core D-I translations as well as base-config and
  tasksel.
</para>

<para>The subject of the bug report should begin by "[INTL:xx]". When the
  package has several translatable material, the subject should
  mention which translation is sent. Please file a bug for each
  translation when you want to send several file. Do not open a bug
  for sending several files at the same time, as they may require
  different handling by maintainers.
</para>

<para>The reportbug utility must be configured for using correct originating
addresse and real name. See <command>man reportbug</command> for details. An example
~/.reportbugrc is given below. Do not use it directly but adapt it to
your own needs!
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
# reportbug preferences file
# Version of reportbug this preferences file was written by
reportbug_version "1.99.51"
# default operating mode: one of: novice, standard, advanced, expert
mode advanced
# default user interface
ui text
# offline setting - comment out to be online
#offline
# name and email setting (if non-default)
realname "Christian Perrier"
email "bubulle@debian.org"
# You can add other settings after this line.  See
# /etc/reportbug.conf for a full listing of options.
</screen>
</informalexample>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>
Sending bug reports from a non Debian system
</title>

<para>
Translators who do not use a Debian system can still report bugs. You just need to send a mail to <email>submit@bugs.debian.org</email> and include the following text at the beginning of your mail:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
Package: &lt;package name&gt;
Version: &lt;version of the package&gt;
Severity: &lt;bug severity&gt;
Tags: &lt;bug tags&gt;
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>Don't forget to attach the translation file to the mail! If you're not
sure about the correct handling of encodings by your mail tool, you'd
better compress the file first (using gzip or any other compress
utility).
</para>


</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>
Methods and advices for translation work
</title>

<para>
This section is not intended to be a tutorial for gettext-related
stuff. Please look for documentation of PO editing software such as
KBabel, gtranslator, PoEdit, EMacs PO-mode, etc.
</para>

<para>Translators should use a dedicated PO-editing tool until they become
very familiar with translation work.
</para>

<para>Using normal editors such as all vi flavours is also possible, but
these will not prevent common errors, neither will they offer useful
features in a translation work.
</para>

<para>Don't forget to properly fill up the PO files header, especially the
<userinput>Last-Translator</userinput> field. 
</para>

<para>Fill the <userinput>Project-Id-Version</userinput> field with the package name : this will
help you in translation maintenance.
</para>

<para>If a translation team exists for your language, WORK WITH THEM. First
check the debian-l10n-xxxxx mailing list where xxxxx is your language
name in english (e.g. debian-l10n-polish, debian-l10n-portuguese...).
</para>

<para>
The list of all available translation teams is available at
<ulink url="http://lists.debian.org/i18n.html">http://lists.debian.org/i18n.html</ulink>
If in doubt, contact <email>debian-i18n@lists.debian.org</email> for assistance.
</para>

<para>For general translation issues or for finding other translators for
your language, you may also use the debian-i18n mailing list (don't
post translations there, however).
</para>

<sect3>
<title>
Remain consistent
</title>

<para>
Some strings are identical in two or more packages. Please try to
translate them consistently.
</para>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>
Update existing translations
</title>

<para>
If you want to update a translation, please always contact the previous
translator in order to prevent duplication of work.  His mail address can
be found in the PO file.
</para>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>
Test your translations
</title>

<para>
When you have finished your translation, always re-read your file at
least once to correct all meaning-, spelling-, grammar-, typo-, etc-
mistakes (maybe your po-editor does include a spellchecker or a
translation helper like acheck).  Run the following command
before commiting or sending your translation:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
  msgfmt --check --statistics &lt;YOUR LANGUAGE CODE&gt;.po
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>(msgfmt is included in the <emphasis>gettext</emphasis> Debian package) 
</para>

<para>You may also use the Debian aspell package for testing the spelling in
your translation. This package is designed for testing the spelling in
PO files as it will only test the spelling in their translated
part. It relies on the ispell program : this will then only work with
languages for which an ispell dictionary exists.
</para>

<para>You can also run podebconf-display-po (from po-debconf >= 0.8.3)
on your file when this is a <emphasis>debconf</emphasis> translation:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
  podebconf-display-po -fdialog &lt;YOUR LANGUAGE CODE&gt;.po
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>This will give you a rough idea on how your translation will look
like, particularly the screens length (use this utility on a usual
80x25 terminal).  But as cdebconf and debconf displays slightly
differ, and as some scripts do heavy use of text substitution, do not
fully rely on this program.  Running debian-installer is the only
solution to test translations.
</para>

<para>Using podebconf-displaypo is mandatory for testing debconf
translations when they are mentioned to be tricky (such as shadow,
popularity-contest and exim4 translations).
</para>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>
Be careful about variables substitutions
</title>

<para>
In several D-I packages, you will find embedded variable names such
as: "You are currently modifying ${PARTITION} properties".  Please DO
NOT translate the variable names and be very careful abou tkeeping
braces and "dollar" signs. For instance, the French translation of the
above is: "Vous modifiez actuellement les propriétés de ${PARTITION}".
</para>

<para>When translating programs such as dpkg, apt or shadow, be careful
about "%s" variables : your translation needs to have the same number
of such variables than the original English string.
</para>

<para>Modern PO editing tools will warn you about such mistakes and msgfmt
(see <emphasis>Testing your translations</emphasis>) will also report <emphasis>errors</emphasis>.
</para>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>
Get help
</title>

<para>
If you need further assistance, feel free to ask for help on
<email>&email-debian-boot-list;</email> (for debian-installer related stuff) or debian-i18n (for
l10n related questions) Debian mailing lists.
</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="status_pages">
<title>
Translation status pages and statistics
</title>

<para>The D-I team maintains web pages giving the statistics of translations
for each language, level by level.
</para>

<para>These pages are maintained or co-maintained by the i18n coordination team.
</para>

<para>Translators should check these pages regularly in order to follow the
possible changes to upstream packages and then update their work if
needed.
</para>

<para>The address for the top page of translation statistics is <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/translation-status.html">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/translation-status.html</ulink>
</para>

<para>The statistics page will give statistics about <emphasis>committed</emphasis> translations,
<emphasis>unstable</emphasis> and <emphasis>testing</emphasis> translations:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>committed</emphasis> translation are the bleeding edge statistics : they
 represent the status of translations in all repositories
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>unstable</emphasis> are translation statistics for Debian
 packages which have been released by their maintainers and are
 currently in the <emphasis>unstable</emphasis> branch of the distribution
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>testing</emphasis> are translation statistics for Debian
 packages which have been released by their maintainers and are
 currently in the <emphasis>testing</emphasis> branch of the distribution
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Explaining the differences between testing and unstable is out of
scope of this document. Please refer to more general documents about
Debian development for these details.
</para>

<para>As <emphasis>testing</emphasis> is the upcoming next stable Debian release, the goal is
of course having the best statistics for this branch of the
distribution.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>
String freezes and the D-I release process
</title>

<para>
The Debian Installer is managed by a team of developers. The release
of the installer involves the releases of all packages which are part
of it.
</para>

<para>Debian Installer releases are managed by the D-I release
manager. Periodically, a <emphasis>release plan</emphasis> is built in order to publish a
stable release of the installer from the source of packages which are
in the archive.
</para>

<para>Outside release processes, the D-I packages are work in progress which
means that the string they contain are likely to change.
</para>

<para>As a consequence, translators ay choose to halt their work during high
develpment activity periods, and thus get their translation statistics
slowly decreasing as long as packages are changed. Another method for
working is by very regularly surveying translation statistics pages
and update files as soon as they get outdated material.
</para>

<para>Both methods are OK for the D-I development team as long as languages
reach back 100% translation for releases. I18n coordinators tend to
favour the constant update method of working because the first method
never give them the guarantee that translators for a given language
are still active.
</para>

<para>All releases plans include a <emphasis>string freeze</emphasis> period. This time period
is quite short and usually lasts a few days (4-6) possibly with a
week-end. A string freeze means that D-I package maintainers should
not change the strings in their upstream files. Thus, a string freeze
guarantee translators that they can work afely without fearing to see
their work dropped away because of a last minute change.
</para>

<para>Be aware that string freezes always have exceptions. In rare
occasions, when important bugs are discovered which require updates to
English strings, they are changed even during the string
freeze. However, such changes are always made with the agreement of
the release manager and the i18n coordinator. In that case,
translators are privately warned about the change. So, during string
freezes, please carefully check your mailboxes, or watch the status
pages regularly.
</para>

<para>String freeze are only relevant for level 1 translations. Level 2 and
above packages may get updates while D-I packages are frozen. In most
cases, however, their maintainers are aware of the D-I release process
and they make their best for not doing last minute changes.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
The work of maintainers
</title>

<sect2>
<title>
Generalities about D-I i18n and l10n
</title>
<para>The Debian Installer packages use a debconf-managed interface for handling
user interaction screens and all display.
</para>

<para>
The debconfized packages use po-debconf for handling localisation which means
that templates translations are hosted in directories named "debian/po" in
each package source code tree.
</para>

<para>
These directories contain <filename>xx.po</filename> files where xx is the ISO-639 code of
handled languages (xx may sometimes be xx_YY when some languages such
as Portuguese or Chinese have different variants). A section about
<ulink url="#iso639">ISO-639 codes</ulink> may be found in this document.
</para>

<para>
They also contain a file named <filename>templates.pot</filename> which contains up-to-date
strings. This file is generated by the <command>debconf-updatepo</command> utility when
debconf templates are modified or written.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>
English templates handling
</title>

<para>
D-I developers are strongly encouraged to read the <emphasis>po-debconf(7)</emphasis> man
page and must have a good knowledge of po-debconf mechanisms. Please ask
for advice in the <email>&email-debian-boot-list;</email> mailing list when in doubt.
</para>

<para>
Strings which need translation must be prepended by a leading
underscore (_) character in the templates files.
</para>

<para>
Templates files MUST be named <filename>&lt;package&gt;.templates</filename>. Developer SHOULD
NOT use files named <filename>debian/templates</filename> though <command>debhelper</command> scripts
properly handle such files. This requirement has been added because
the translators work on a general file which groups together all
templates from all D-I packages. This general file mentions, for each
string, the originating file name. If this file name contains the
package name, the translator will then know which package the string
(s)he translates belongs to.
</para>

<para>
Please respect the <ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~bubulle/dtsg/dtsg.txt">Debconf Templates Style Guide (DTSG)</ulink> and the general style
for writing templates for D-I (a special section of the DTSG mentions
D-I templates). And, and any case, BEFORE commiting new templates or
templates changes, please have these templates reviewed by other D-I
developers.
</para>

<para>
If you commit templates with incorrect English or templates with a
different writing style than the general D-I writing style, several
translators will start working on these templates and will be angry
when they will be changed again after being reviewed.
</para>

<para>
ANY templates files in the <filename>packages/</filename> directory of the D-I source tree
will enter the translators work files a few hours after it has been
committed. So, if you work on a new prospective package which does not
need translations yet, please do not put it immediately in the
<filename>packages/</filename> directory in the SVN tree.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>
"New" work method for translators
</title>

<para>
Up to D-I RC1, translators worked by updating all individual packages
PO files one by one. 
</para>

<para>
However, this method showed some limitations and made the translators
work quite tedious in maintenance tasks.
</para>

<para>
For this reason, a few weeks after RC1, the translators team changed
their work method : all PO files are now merged into one single file
and translators update this file. These single PO files are placed
into packages/po into the D-I main directory.
</para>

<para>
A script is run regularly by the D-I i18n coordinator. This script
does the following tasks:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
merge all <filename>templates.pot</filename> file into packages/po/template.pot
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
update <filename>packages/po/*.po</filename> files according to this template.pot file
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
update all individual packages <filename>debian/po/*.po</filename> files with the
 translations from these single <filename>packages/po/*.po</filename> files
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
As one may see, changes made directly to <filename>debian/po/*.po</filename> files are <emphasis>lost</emphasis>
in this process. So, if for some reason, maintainers need to update
these files (there is normally NO reason for this), they should
consider modifying the source files in <filename>packages/po</filename>. But, in any case,
they should coordinate their action with the i18n coordinator.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>
Handling modifications to templates
</title>

<para>
When maintainers modify the strings in the templates files, the
translations will often need updates.
</para>

<para>
Maintainers do not need to run the <command>debconf-updatepo</command> utility which
updates the debian/po/templates.pot file as well as all <filename>debian/po/*.po</filename>
files. Such updates will be handled by the i18n coordinator
synchronisation script.
</para>

<para>
Modifications to templates will change the status of the translations
for the modified string : in all PO files, this string will be marked
as <emphasis>fuzzy</emphasis>. This means that though the former translation is kept, it
is known to be outdated. <emphasis>Fuzzy</emphasis> translations are of course not used :
a template which contains at least one fuzzy string will be
<emphasis>completely</emphasis> displayed in English. As a consequence, don't worry about
outdated translations, this is the translators job.
</para>

<para>
This <emphasis>fuzzy</emphasis> string will be marked fuzzy in the general PO files when
the i18n coordinator merging script will be run.
</para>

<para>
When modifications make the new string too different from the original
string, the string translations are not kept and thus the string
becomes <emphasis>untranslated</emphasis>.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>Handling <emphasis>trivial</emphasis> modifications to templates</title>

<para>
<emphasis>Trivial</emphasis> modifications are all modifications which have no impact on
the translations: these will be most often spelling errors or typos
in original templates files.
</para>

<para>
If the update is made without care, correcting a typo in one template
will result in one more <emphasis>fuzzy</emphasis> string in all translations. 
</para>

<para>
In such case, a special <emphasis>unfuzzy</emphasis> process may be run on PO files.
</para>

<para>
As an example, let's assume that an original template contained the
following wrong English sentence:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
These changes will be applied to all partitons.
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
If the package maintainer simply changes <emphasis>partitons</emphasis> to the correct
<emphasis>partitions</emphasis> word, all translations of the paragraph containing this
sentence will be fuzzied.
</para>

<para>
In this case, preventive <emphasis>unfuzzyfication</emphasis> may be done:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
cd &lt;di_dir&gt;/packages/po/
svn update
mkdir NEW
for i in *po ; do
 cat $i | sed 's/partitons/partitions/g' >NEW/$i
 mv NEW/$i $i
done
svn commit -m"Typo correction in &lt;mypackage&gt;" *.po
rmdir NEW
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
<emphasis>This is a dangerous action</emphasis>. The replacement string
in the <command>sed</command> command above must be carefully chosen so that it matches
only the occurrence you have changed.
</para>

<para>
If in doubt, please contact the i18n coordinator <emphasis>
before commiting the error correction</emphasis> to the original templates file.
</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
String freezes
</title>

<para>
During the release process of the Debian Installer, the D-I project
manager will call for <emphasis>string freezes</emphasis>. A string freeze theoretically
forbids any change to templates files in D-I packages. It is meant for
translators to complete their work without having it outdated by
maintainers changes.
</para>

<para>
Of course, some urgent or critical changes may be needed even during a
string freeze. If, as a maintainer, you need to commit such changes,
please first warn the D-I i18n coordinator and possibly get approval
from the D-I release manager.
</para>

<para>
The i18n coordinator will warn translators about the unplanned change
and will request them for a special update.
</para>

<para>
Always remember that D-I translation is the work of more than 40 teams
and thus each change adds more time for all of them to get
synchronised again.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>
Releasing packages
</title>
<para>
When releasing their packages, maintainers should use the
<command>scripts/l10n-utilities/l10n-release</command> script. This script will do a last
synchronisation of the translations for the package with the
translators work from the general PO files directory.
</para>

<para>
The script will also output the changelog entries which should be
added to the package's changelog file, for translations which got
modifications since the last release of the package. This will work
properly ONLY if the last changelog entry includes "UNRELEASED".
</para>

<para>
After running the script, please add these lines to the package's
changelog file and process with other release tasks (which are out
of scope for this document).
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Technical details about processes involved in Debian Installer i18n handling
</title>

<sect2>
<title>
Synchronisation between packages source trees and translations
</title>

<para>
The files which are really used for building D-I packages are hosted
in the SVN (Subversion) repository used for the development of D-I
packages.
</para>

<para>
These files need to be synchronised with the translations from the
packages/po directory.
</para>

<para>
Starting from the RC1 release of the Debian Installer, translators do
not work anymore on the package's debian/po/*.po files. All
translations are merged into files which are committed in packages/po.
</para>

<para>
When D-I packages templates are changed, the individual
debian/po/templates.pot file will change. These changes have to be
moved to files in packages/po.
</para>

<para>
When translations are updated in the packages/po directory, these
changes have to be moved back into individual debian/po/*.po files for
each package. This does not need to be done at each translation update but
must be done BEFORE building packages.
</para>

<para>
The task of keeping track of the correct synchronisation is one of the
most important tasks of the D-I i18n coordinator. It is handled by the
scripts/l10n-utilities/l10n-sync script.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Synchronisation method
</title>

<sect3>
<title>
Initial synchronisation
</title>

<para>
Generate template.pot from the D-I repository by merging together all
  debian/po/templates.pot files. The scripts/l10n-utilities/l10n-sync
  may be used for this. First check that no PO files stay in packages/po
  when running it for the first time.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Switch a language to the new method
</title>

<para>
This action should only happen once for each language.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
bring this language to 100% translation according to the <emphasis>old</emphasis> method
  (this step is not mandatory but will help in tracking down fuzzies)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
stop commiting <filename>xx.po</filename> files for this language
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
build the general <filename>xx.po</filename> file in <filename>packages/po</filename> by using the
  <command>scripts/l10n-utilities/gettex-helper</command> script
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
fill in the PO file header properly. Do not forget the <userinput>Plural-Forms</userinput>
  header. Ask i18n coordinator for help
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
track <emphasis>fuzzy</emphasis> strings which are often caused by identical strings 
  with different translations in different D-I packages. For these strings, keep only one translation
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
commit back the new <filename>xx.po</filename> file to <filename>packages/po</filename>. This will automatically trigger
  individual PO files update when packages will be built (see <ulink url="#changes_to_build">changes to
  packages build process</ulink>)
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
 Later synchronisations
</title>

<para>
On a regular basis, the <command>l10n-sync</command> script will run under the account of
the i18n coordinator on people.debian.org and will update the general
<filename>template.pot</filename> and all PO files from individual <filename>templates.pot</filename> files from
all D-I packages.
</para>

<para>
The time period during which this process occurs is called <emphasis>l10n
synchronisation window</emphasis>. Such window occurs four times a day (at H+27
at 1, 7, 13 and 19 UTC) during normal D-I development process and
hourly (at H+27) during string freezes.
</para>

<para>
While running, this script will also run <command>debconf-updatepo</command> for each
D-I package and will commit back the regenerated templates.pot files
(package maintainers often forget running debconf-udpatepo when
commiting changes to English templates).
</para>

<para>  
The general process is:
</para>

	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		for each D-I package:
	      </para>
	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    synchronize the local copy with the D-I SVN
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    run <command>debconf-updatepo</command>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    commit back the files in debian/po
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Update the general template.pot file:
	      </para>
	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		      merge all templates.pot files to packages/po/template.pot
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		      commit this file
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		For each PO file:
	      </para>
	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		      synchronize with D-I SVN
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		      update with packages/po/template.pot
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		      commit back the changed file to D-I SVN
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		for each D-I package:
	      </para>
	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		      synchronize the local copy with the D-I SVN 
		      (in case some update occurred in the meantime)
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		      update debian/po/*.po files with files in packages/po/
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		      commit back the changes to D-I SVN
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>

<para>
A few "conflicts windows" exist :
</para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  during 1) if changes are made by an upstream maintainer to templates file
		  and (s)he runs debconf-updatepo then commits the changes between 1a and 1c
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  between 3a and 3c if a translator commits an update to his/her translation
		  before the l10n synchronisation script commits the update
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  between 4a and 4c if an upstream maintainer updates his templates file
		  and runs debconf-updatepo before the l10n synchronisation script commits back
		  the updated files
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>

<para>
For these reasons, maintainers <emphasis>should not use</emphasis> <command>debconf-updatepo</command> and
commit back the updated files during the D-I l10n synchronisation
windows. For the same reasons, translators should avoid commiting
updates during the D-I l10n synchronisation windows.
</para>

<para>
The conflict windows have been minimised as much as possible in the
<command>l10n-sync</command> script. This explains the high number of commit actions made
by this script (as soon as a file is modified, it is committed to SVN).
</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="l10n_synchronisation_script">
<title>
l10n synchronisation script
</title>

<para>
The l10n synchronisation script is kept in D-I repository in the
<filename>scripts/l10n-utilities</filename> directory and is named <filename>l10n-sync</filename>.
</para>

<para>
This is a shell script (which may contain some bashisms until a
skilled shell programmer cleans it out).
</para>

<para>
The script uses some command-line switches which may affetc its behaviour:
</para>


	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		"--debug" will trigger more output by the
		script. Otherwise, the script reports about its
		actions but commands output (such as
		<command>svn</command>,
		<command>debconf-updatepo</command>,
		<command>msgmerge</command>) will be redirected to
		<filename>/dev/null</filename>.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		the "--online" switch is very important:
	      </para>
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    it triggers "svn update" commands before
		    working on files
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    it allows the script
		    to COMMIT files back to the D-I repository
		    Of course, this is quite risky and must be done only on
		    controlled environments because this will update a lot of files
		    in D-I repository
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		the <command>svn</command> switch defines the command for calling the <command>svn</command> utility
		It is used in the script just in case some special behaviour is needed
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		the <command>debconfupdatepo</command> switch serves the same purpose the the
		<command>debconf-updatepo</command> command. It allows using a specially crafted
		<command>debconf-updatepo</command> command, for just updating <filename>templates.pot</filename> files
		and save a lot of time
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

<para>
The script needs the location of the local copy of the D-I repository
to be passed as an argument. It makes some simple checks about the copy.
</para>

<para>
When using this script with commits, the D-I copy must be as clean
as possible. It should not be used for development tasks. The scripts checks for possible SVN conflict files and aborts if it finds some.
</para>

<para>
<ulink url="#prospective_languages">Prospective languages</ulink> are not touched: 
Is a language listed in 
<filename>packages/po/PROSPECTIVE</filename>, the translations
are not spreaded into the packages. These languages are not 
available in the installer.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="prospective_languages">
<title>
About prospective languages
</title>

<para>
Since September 2004, the number of languages supported by debian-installer for sarge is frozen.
All languages which started translating after September 2004 are called "prospective languages".
These languages won't go into sarge but rather in the next release of the distribution.
</para>

<para>
Another reason for keeping a language out of the installer is when the basis is done, but it's
lacking a translator.
</para>

<para>
Prospective languages are kept in the file <filename>packages/po/PROSPECTIVE</filename> along
with the master po files. Translators can continue translating, but the translations will be 
kept back and not spreaded into packages by 
<ulink url="#l10n_synchronisation_script">l10n synchronisation script</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
Status of prospective languages can be fetched at 
<ulink url="http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/translation-status.html">http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/translation-status.html</ulink>
like for every other language. The only difference is rank.txt. A prospective language is not listed 
in rank.txt and not calculated into the graph. See 
<ulink url="#status_pages">Translation status pages and statistics</ulink> for information
about the status and statistics pages.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="appendix">
<title>
Appendixes
</title>
<sect2 id="#transition">
<title>
Transition from <emphasis>old</emphasis> (pre-RC1) work method to <emphasis>new</emphasis> work method
</title>

<para>Since D-I (Debian Installer) RC1 release, the translation of individual
core packages is discouraged (though still possible in theory).
</para>


<para>Translators should now use the merged files which are hosted in the
packages/po directory of the D-I SVN source tree.
</para>

<para>During the transition period from the old working method and the new
working method, the packages/po directory will only host files for
translation teams which have switched their work method.
</para>

<para>If your language is not listed, this means that no translation work
already took place or that the translation team for your language
still uses the old work method. Please get in touch with the
D-I i18n coordinator for getting instructions.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="iso639">
<title>
ISO-639 codes, languages and languages variants
</title>

<para>
The ISO-639 standard defines all languages and standardize codes for
designing them as well as the English and French names of these
languages.
</para>

<para>Each language in the ISO-639 list has a three letter code. The most
widely spread languages also have a two-letter code defined.
</para>

<para>In Unix systems, the two-letter codes are used in locales files and
thus these codes should be used when they exist for a given language.
</para>

<para>On Debian systems, the iso-codes packages includes a list of all
ISO-639 material. If you are in doubt about the appropriate code for
your language, please refer to this list or talk with the D-I i18n
coordinator.
</para>

<para>Some languages may have <emphasis>variants</emphasis> depending on the region they're
spoken in, for instance. First be aware that the topic here are
<emphasis>written</emphasis> languages : so if the variants are only in the way to
pronounce the language, using such variants is out of topic for Debian
translations.
</para>

<para>When the variants differ on the way to <emphasis>write</emphasis> the same language (that
is when no different ISO codes exist), the country/region part of the
locale shoul dbe used. If you are considering doing so, PLEASE GET IN
TOUCH with the i18n coordinator. Such cases should be kept to a very
low number of occurrences and should only be used when the two
languages differ too much.
</para>

<para>The currently registered variants are:
</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      zh_CN/zh_TW : <emphasis>Simplified</emphasis> Chinese and <emphasis>Traditional</emphasis> Chinese. These
	      two ways of <emphasis>writing</emphasis> the Chinese language have their own
	      translation teams (but only one mailing list)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      pt/pt_BR    : <emphasis>classical</emphasis> Portuguese is spoken in Portugal as well as 
	      nearly all former Portugal colonies
	      Brazilian Portuguese largely differs from Portuguese
	      and is of course used in Brazil
	      Two different translation sets exist for Debian packages
	      though both teams work closely together (there is for
	      instance only one mailing list)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      pa_IN/pa_PK    : the Punjabi language has only one spoken for, but two written forms : one using Indic-style glyphs, mostly used in India (Punjab state), and another one, using an Arabic script, mostly used in Pakistan.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

<para>FAQ about variants:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
there are no en_GB/en_US variants in Debian. The use of either
 <emphasis>British</emphasis> or <emphasis>American</emphasis> spelling is not highly standardised in Debian. The installer team has however decided to refer to US-style spelling.
</para>

</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
the spanish team has chosen to keep only one variant even though some
 differences exist in the way Spanish is spoken in Spain and Latin
 America, for instance.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="editors_and_tools">
<title>
Editors and tools
</title>

<sect3>
<title>
PO files editors
</title>

<para>
Translators are highly encouraged to use dedicated GNU gettext files
(PO files) editing tools. Even though PO files are plain text files
which may be modified with any text editor, the use of dedicated tools
will save translators a lot of time.
</para>

<para>This document does not intend to be a reference document about these
tools. Most tools have been packaged for the Debian GNU/Linux
distribution and thus installing them on a Debian system is as easy as
running <command>apt-get install &lt;package&gt;</command>.
</para>

<para>Short list of PO editing tools:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
KBabel (Debian package <emphasis>kbabel</emphasis>): very complete and powerful. Needs
  installing the KDE libraries (but, of course, it may work without the
  full KDE environment).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Poedit (Debian package <emphasis>poedit</emphasis>): quite complete tool but no
  correct handling of non Latin languages on Debian. Uses the WxWindows
  toolkit.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Gtranslator (Debian package <emphasis>gtranslator</emphasis>): PO-file editor for the 
  GNOME Desktop. No feedback yet.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Emacs <emphasis>po-mode</emphasis> (Debian package <emphasis>gettext-el</emphasis>): editing mode for
  the emacs/xemacs editor. For Emacs addicts...
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>
PO files tools
</title>

<para>
The Debian package <emphasis>gettext</emphasis> includes a whole set of command-line
utilities for handling i18n material.
</para>

<para>Several utilities may help translators in manipulating the PO files
contents. For all these utilities, see their respective man pages for
details about their use:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<command>msgcat</command> combines together one or several files. When used on a single file, it
 will wrap the file contents and make it easy to read.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<command>msgmerge</command> may merge together translations from one or two files as well
 as update a PO files according to the contents of a <filename>templates</filename> file.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<command>msgfmt</command> is aimed at compiling message catalog files but is also very useful
 for checking files and get statistics about their contents. The use of <command>msgfmt --check --statistics --output-file=/dev/null
 file.po</command> is highly recommended before commiting a translation file or
 sending it to the package maintainer.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1>
<title>
Changelog for this document
</title>

<informalexample>
<screen>
2004/11/21 Dennis Stampfer
  - Writing something about "prospective languages"

2004/09/04 Guillem Jover
  - Refer to Adam Conrad's subversion backport instead.

2004/08/09 Christian Perrier
  - Complete rewrite : 
    - "stages" are replaced by "levels"
    - core D-I translation is made in a general file
    - more details about each translation specifics
    - more details about getting/sending translations for each
      package
    - lots of other changes
    - XMLised

2004/07/18 Dennis Stampfer
  - In statistics is no STATUS.utf8.txt anymore. It is called &lt;lang&gt;.txt
  
2004/06/12 Christian Perrier
  - Change all references to D. Barbier pages to Dennis Stampfer or Pierre
    Machard pages
  - Change reference from CVS to SVN for base-config
  - Adapt instructions for ISO-3166 translations

2004/04/17 Jean Christophe Andre
  - Completed the SVN section (alioth account, SVN)

2004/03/28 Christian Perrier
  - Added reference to a SVN browse URL
  - Review of the packages to be translated list by
    Konstantinos Margaritis

2004/03/26 Christian Perrier
  - Reordered arch-dependent packages accordign to release status

2004/03/24 Javier Fernandez-Sanguino
  - Minor changes: typo fixes and some more verbosity in some places.

  - Point people to the debian-i18n mailing list.

  - Added pointer to iso-codes CVS access (took me a bit to find it)

2004/03/24 Christian Perrier
 - Major update:
   - debian-installer switched to subversion
   - reference page is now Dennis Stampfer's page which references
     other specialised status pages
   - general modifications for fitting the current context of d-i
     development

2004/03/10 Christian Perrier
 - Added mention of Seppy's status page for level2

2004/02/16 Christian Perrier
 - Added instructions for keeping translations consistent among packages

2004/02/14 Christian Perrier
 - Corrected instructions for iso-codes

2004/01/30 Christian Perrier
 - give details about kbd-chooser/console-data
 - mention *core* udebs in translation order

2004/01/22 Christian Perrier
 - updated packages information (countrychooser and partman-* added)
 - mentioned aspell in tools
 - appendix added with iso-codes note
 - reformatted changelog
 - new title

2004/01/20 Javier Fernandez-Sanguino
 - added more packages and mentioned the 'by priority' and 'popular' criteria

2003/12/20 Christian Perrier
 - updated packages list and more information
 - rewamped the file

2003/11/08 Petter Reinholdtsen
 - file creation
</screen>
</informalexample>
</sect1>

</article>
