<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id: using-d-i.xml 19074 2004-08-15 12:59:43Z fjpop-guest $ -->


 <chapter id="d-i-intro"
><title
>Использование программы установки Debian</title>

 <sect1
><title
>Как работает программа установки</title>
<para
>The Debian Installer consists of a number of special-purpose components to perform each installation task. Each component performs its task, asking the user questions as necessary to do its job. The questions themselves are given priorities, and the priority of questions to be asked is set when the installer is started. </para
><para
>When a default installation is performed, only essential (high priority) questions will be asked. This results in a highly automated installation process with little user interaction. Components are automatically run in sequence; which components are run depends mainly on the installation method you use and on your hardware. The installer will use default values for questions that are not asked. </para
><para
>If there is a problem, the user will see an error screen, and the installer menu may be shown in order to select some alternative action. If there are no problems, the user will never see the installer menu, but will simply answer questions for each component in turn. Serious error notifications are set to priority 'critical' so the user will always be notified. </para
><para
>Some of the defaults that the installer uses can be influenced by passing boot arguments when &d-i; is started. If, for example, you wish to force static network configuration (DHCP is used by default if available), you could add the boot parameter <userinput
>netcfg/disable_dhcp=true</userinput
>. See <xref linkend="installer-args"/> for available options. </para
><para
>Power users may be more comfortable with a menu-driven interface, where each step is controlled by the user rather than the installer performing each step automatically in sequence. To use the installer in a manual, menu-driven way, add the boot argument <userinput
>debconf/priority=medium</userinput
>. </para
><para
>If your hardware requires you to pass options to kernel modules as they are installed, you will need to start the installer in <quote
>expert</quote
> mode. This can be done by either using the <command
>expert</command
> command to start the installer or by adding the boot argument <userinput
>debconf/priority=low</userinput
>. Expert mode gives you full control over &d-i;. </para
><para
>The normal installer display is character-based (as opposed to the now more familiar graphical interface). The mouse is not operational in this environment. Here are the keys you can use to navigate within the various dialogs. The <keycap
>Tab</keycap
> or <keycap
>right</keycap
> arrow keys move `forward', and the <keycombo
> <keycap
>Shift</keycap
> <keycap
>Tab</keycap
> </keycombo
> or <keycap
>left</keycap
> arrow keys move `backward' between displayed buttons and selections. The <keycap
>up</keycap
> and <keycap
>down</keycap
> arrow select different items within a scrollable list, and also scroll the list itself. In addition, in long lists, you can type a letter to cause the list to scroll directly to the section with items starting with the letter you typed and use <keycap
>Pg-Up</keycap
> and <keycap
>Pg-Down</keycap
> to scroll the list in sections. The <keycap
>space bar</keycap
> selects an item such as a checkbox. Use &enterkey; to activate choices. </para
><para arch="s390"
>S/390 does not support virtual consoles. You may open a second and third ssh session to view the logs described below. </para
><para
>Error messages are redirected to the third console. You can access this console by pressing <keycombo
><keycap
>Left Alt</keycap
><keycap
>F3</keycap
></keycombo
> (hold the left <keycap
>Alt</keycap
> key while pressing the <keycap
>F3</keycap
> function key); get back to the main installer process with <keycombo
><keycap
>Left Alt</keycap
><keycap
>F1</keycap
></keycombo
>. </para
><para
>These messages can also be found in <filename
>/var/log/messages</filename
>. After installation, this log is copied to <filename
>/var/log/debian-installer/messages</filename
> on your new system. Other installation messages may be found in <filename
>/var/log/</filename
> during the installation, and <filename
>/var/log/debian-installer/</filename
> after the computer has been booted into the installed system. </para>
 </sect1>


  <sect1 id="modules-list"
><title
>Введение в компоненты</title>
<para
>Вот список компонентов программы установки с кратким описанием назначения каждого компонента. Детали об использовании каждого компонента, которые вы возможно должны знать, находятся в  <xref linkend="module-details"/>. </para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>

<term
>main-menu</term
><listitem
><para
>Shows the list of components to the user during installer operation, and starts a component when it is selected. Main-menu's questions are set to priority medium, so if your priority is set to high or critical (high is the default), you will not see the menu. On the other hand, if there is an error which requires your intervention, the question priority may be downgraded temporarily to allow you to resolve the problem, and in that case the menu may appear. </para
><para
>You can get to the main menu by selecting the "Back" button repeatedly to back all the way out of the currently running component. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>languagechooser</term
><listitem
><para
>Показывает список языков и варианты языка. Программа установки будет отображать сообщения на выбранном языке, если перевод на этот язык закончен. Когда перевод не закончен, будут показываться английские сообщения. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>countrychooser</term
><listitem
><para
>Shows a list of countries. The user may choose the country he lives in. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>kbd-chooser</term
><listitem
><para
>Показывает список клавиатур, из которого пользователь выбирает модель, которая ему подходит. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>hw-detect</term
><listitem
><para
>Automatically detects most of the system's hardware, including network cards, disk drives, and PCMCIA. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>cdrom-detect</term
><listitem
><para
>Looks for and mounts a Debian installation CD. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>netcfg</term
><listitem
><para
>Настраивает сетевые подключения компьютера, чтобы он мог общаться через интернет. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>iso-scan</term
><listitem
><para
>Ищет файловые системы ISO, которые могут располагаться на компакт-дисках или на жестком диске. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>choose-mirror</term
><listitem
><para
>Presents a list of Debian archive mirrors. The user may choose the source of his installation packages. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>cdrom-checker</term
><listitem
><para
>Checks integrity of a CD-ROM. This way the user may assure him/herself that the installation CD-ROM was not corrupted. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>lowmem</term
><listitem
><para
>Lowmem tries to detect systems with low memory and then does various tricks to remove unnecessary parts of &d-i; from the memory (at the cost of some features). </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>anna</term
><listitem
><para
>Anna's Not Nearly APT. Installs packages which have been retrieved from the chosen mirror or CD. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>partman</term
><listitem
><para
>Allows the user to partition disks attached to the system, create file systems on the selected partitions, and attach them to the mountpoints. Included are also interesting features like a fully automatic mode or LVM support. This is the preferred partitioning tool in Debian. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>autopartkit</term
><listitem
><para
>Автоматически размечает весь диск на разделы, согласно заданным пользователем установкам </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>partitioner</term
><listitem
><para
>Позволяет пользователю разметить на разделы диски, подключенные к системе. Выбирается программа разметки, соответствующая архитектуре вашего компьютера. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>partconf</term
><listitem
><para
>Отображает список разделов и создает файловые системы на выбранных разделах, согласно пользовательским инструкциям. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>lvmcfg</term
><listitem
><para
>Helps the user with the configuration of the <firstterm
>LVM</firstterm
> (Logical Volume Manager). </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>mdcfg</term
><listitem
><para
>Allows the user to setup Software <firstterm
>RAID</firstterm
> (Redundant Array of Inexpensive Disks). This Software RAID is usually superior to the cheap IDE (pseudo hardware) RAID controllers found on newer motherboards. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>base-installer</term
><listitem
><para
>Устанавливает самый минимальный набор пакетов, который позволит компьютеру работать под Linux после перезагрузки. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>os-prober</term
><listitem
><para
>Detects currently installed operating systems on the computer and passes this information to the bootloader-installer, which may offer you an ability to add discovered operating systems to the bootloader's start menu. This way the user could easily choose at the boot time which operating system to start. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>bootloader-installer</term
><listitem
><para
>Устанавливает на жесткий диск программу системного загрузчика, которая необходима для того, чтобы компьютер заработал под Linux без использования дискеты или компакт-диска. Многие системные загрузчики позволяют пользователю выбрать альтернативную операционную систему каждый раз при загрузке компьютера. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>base-config</term
><listitem
><para
>Обеспечивает диалоги для настройки базовых системных пакетов, согласно установкам пользователя. В норме это происходит после перезагрузки компьютера; это 'первый запуск' новой системы Debian. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>shell</term
><listitem
><para
>Позволяет пользователю вызвать командную оболочку из меню или на второй консоли </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>

<term
>bugreporter</term
><listitem
><para
>Обеспечивает пользователю возможность записать информацию на дискету в случае возникновения затруднений, для того, чтобы позже отправить разработчикам Debian точный отчет о проблеме в программе установки. </para
></listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

 </sect1>
&using-d-i-components.xml; </chapter>

