<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

 <sect2 arch="not-s390" id="PPP">
 <title>Setting Up PPP</title>

<para>

If your computer is not connected to a network, you will next be asked
whether you wish to install the rest of the system using PPP.

</para><para>

If you do choose to configure PPP at this point, a program named
<command>pppconfig</command> will be run.  This program helps you
configure your PPP connection.  <emphasis>Make sure, when it asks you
for the name of your dialup connection, that you name it
<userinput>provider</userinput>.</emphasis>

</para><para>

Hopefully, the <command>pppconfig</command> program will walk you
through a pain-free PPP connection setup.  However, if it does not
work for you, see below for detailed instructions.

</para><para>

In order to setup PPP, you'll need to know the basics of file viewing
and editing in GNU/Linux.  To view files, you should use
<command>more</command>, and <command>zmore</command> for compressed
files with a <userinput>.gz</userinput> extension.  For example, to
view <filename>README.debian.gz</filename>, type <userinput>zmore
README.debian.gz</userinput>.  The base system comes with an editor
named <command>nano</command>, which is very simple to use, but does
not have a lot of features. You will probably want to install more
full-featured editors and viewers later, such as
<command>jed</command>, <command>nvi</command>,
<command>less</command>, and <command>emacs</command>.

</para><para>

Edit <filename>/etc/ppp/peers/provider</filename> and replace
<userinput>/dev/modem</userinput> with
<userinput>/dev/ttyS<replaceable>&num;</replaceable></userinput> where
<replaceable>&num;</replaceable> stands for the number of your serial
port. In Linux, serial ports are counted from 0; your first serial
port <phrase arch="i386">(i.e., <userinput>COM1</userinput>)</phrase>
is <filename>/dev/ttyS0</filename> under Linux.

<phrase arch="powerpc;m68k">On Macintoshes with serial ports, the
modem port is <filename>/dev/ttyS0</filename> and the printer port is
<filename>/dev/ttyS1</filename>.</phrase>

The next step is to edit
<filename>/etc/chatscripts/provider</filename> and insert your
provider's phone number, your user-name and password. Please do not
delete the <quote>\q</quote> that precedes the password. It hides the
password from appearing in your log files.

</para><para>

Many providers use PAP or CHAP for login sequence instead of text mode
authentication.  Others use both.  If your provider requires PAP or
CHAP, you'll need to follow a different procedure.  Comment out
everything below the dialing string (the one that starts with
<quote>ATDT</quote>) in
<filename>/etc/chatscripts/provider</filename>, modify
<filename>/etc/ppp/peers/provider</filename> as described above, and
add <userinput>user <replaceable>name</replaceable></userinput> where
<replaceable>name</replaceable> stands for your user-name for the
provider you are trying to connect to.  Next, edit
<filename>/etc/ppp/pap-secrets</filename> or
<filename>/etc/ppp/chap-secrets</filename> and enter your password
there.

</para><para>

You will also need to edit <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> and
add your provider's name server (DNS) IP addresses.  The lines in
<filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> are in the following format:
<userinput>nameserver
<replaceable>xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx</replaceable></userinput> where the
<replaceable>x</replaceable>s stand for numbers in your IP
address. Optionally, you could add the
<userinput>usepeerdns</userinput> option to the
<filename>/etc/ppp/peers/provider</filename> file, which will enable
automatic choosing of appropriate DNS servers, using settings the
remote host usually provides.

</para><para>

Unless your provider has a login sequence different from the majority
of ISPs, you are done! Start the PPP connection by typing
<command>pon</command> as root, and monitor the process using
<command>plog</command> command. To disconnect, use
<command>poff</command>, again, as root.

</para><para>

Read <filename>/usr/share/doc/ppp/README.Debian.gz</filename> file for
more information on using PPP on Debian.

</para><para>

For static SLIP connections, you will need to add the
<userinput>slattach</userinput> command (from the
<classname>net-tools</classname> package) into
<filename>/etc/init.d/network</filename>. Dynamic SLIP will require
the <classname>gnudip</classname> package.

</para>
 </sect2>
