<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 27345 untranslated -->

   <sect3 arch="powerpc">
   <title>USB stick partitioning on &arch-title;</title>
<para>

Most USB sticks do not come pre-configured in such a way that Open
Firmware can boot from them, so you will need to repartition the stick.
On Mac systems, run <userinput>mac-fdisk /dev/sda</userinput>,
initialise a new partition map using the <userinput>i</userinput>
command, and create a new partition of type Apple_Bootstrap using the
<userinput>C</userinput> command. (Note that the first "partition" will
always be the partition map itself.) Then type

<informalexample><screen>
$ hformat /dev/<replaceable>sda2</replaceable>
</screen></informalexample>

Take care that you use the correct device name for your USB stick. The
<command>hformat</command> command is contained in the
<classname>hfsutils</classname> Debian package.

</para><para>

In order to start the kernel after booting from the USB stick, we will
put a boot loader on the stick. The <command>yaboot</command> boot
loader can be installed on an HFS filesystem and can be reconfigured by
just editing a text file. Any operating system which supports the HFS
file system can be used to make changes to the configuration of the boot
loader.

</para><para>

The normal <command>ybin</command> tool that comes with
<command>yaboot</command> does not yet understand USB storage devices,
so you will have to install <command>yaboot</command> by hand using the
<classname>hfsutils</classname> tools. Type

<informalexample><screen>
$ hmount /dev/sda2
$ hcopy -r /usr/lib/yaboot/yaboot :
$ hattrib -c UNIX -t tbxi :yaboot
$ hattrib -b :
$ humount
</screen></informalexample>

Again, take care that you use the correct device name. The partition
must not be otherwise mounted during this procedure. This procedure
writes the boot loader to the partition, and uses the HFS utilities to
mark it in such a way that Open Firmware will boot it. Having done this,
the rest of the USB stick may be prepared using the normal Unix
utilities.

</para><para>

Mount the partition (<userinput>mount /dev/sda2 /mnt</userinput>) and
copy the following files from the Debian archives to the stick:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>

<filename>vmlinux</filename> (kernel binary)

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>initrd.gz</filename> (initial ramdisk image)

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>yaboot.conf</filename> (yaboot configuration file)

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

<filename>boot.msg</filename> (optional boot message)

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Optional kernel modules

</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para><para>

The <filename>yaboot.conf</filename> configuration file should
contain the following lines:

<informalexample><screen>
default=install
root=/dev/ram

message=/boot.msg

image=/vmlinux
        label=install
        initrd=/initrd.gz
        initrd-size=10000<phrase condition="sarge">
        append="devfs=mount,dall --"</phrase>
        read-only
</screen></informalexample>

Please note that the <userinput>initrd-size</userinput> parameter
may need to be increased, depending on the image you are booting.

</para>
   </sect3>
