<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id$ -->


  <sect2 arch="sparc" id="sparc-cpus"><title>CPU, Main Boards, and Video Support</title>
<para>

Currently the <emphasis>&architecture;</emphasis> port supports
several types of Sparc systems. The most common identifiers for Sparc
systems are sun4, sun4c, sun4m, sun4d and sun4u. Currently we do not
support very old sun4 hardware. However, the other systems are
supported. Sun4d has been tested the least of these, so expect
possible problems with regard to the kernel stability. Sun4c and
Sun4m, the most common of the older Sparc hardware, includes such
systems as SparcStation 1, 1+, IPC, IPX and the SparcStation LX, 5,
10, and 20, respectively. The UltraSPARC class systems fall under the
sun4u identifier, and are supported using the sun4u set of install
images. Some systems that fall under these supported identifiers are
known to not be supported. Known unsupported systems are the AP1000
multicomputer and the Tadpole Sparcbook 1. See the 
<ulink url="&url-sparc-linux-faq;">Linux for SPARCProcessors FAQ</ulink> 
for complete information.

</para>

   <sect3><title>Memory Configuration</title>
<para>

Some older Sun workstations, notably the Sun IPX and Sun IPC have
memory banks located at fixed locations in physical memory.  Thus if
the banks are not filled gaps will exist in the physical memory space.
The Linux installation requires a contiguous memory block into which
to load the kernel and the initial RAMdisk.  If this is not available a
`Data Access Exception' will result.

</para><para>

Thus you must configure the memory so that the lowest memory block is
contiguous for at least 8Mb.  In the IPX and IPC cited above, memory banks
are mapped in at 16Mb boundaries.  In effect this means that you must have
a sufficiently large SIMM in bank zero to hold the kernel and RAMdisk.
In this case 4Mb is <emphasis>not</emphasis> sufficient.

</para><para>

Example:
In a Sun IPX you have a 16Mb SIMM and a 4Mb SIMM.  There are four
SIMM banks (0,1,2,3). [Bank zero is that furthest away from the SBUS
connectors]. You must therefore install the 16Mb SIMM in bank 0; it is
then recommended to install the 4Mb SIMM in bank 2. 

</para>
   </sect3>

   <sect3><title>Graphics Configuration</title>
<para>

Especially in the case of older Sun workstations, it is very common
for there to be an onboard framebuffer which has been superseded (for
example the bwtwo on a sun IPC), and an SBUS card containing a later
probably accelerated buffer is then plugged in to an SBUS slot.
Under Solaris/SunOS this causes no problems because both cards are
initialised.  

</para><para>

However with Linux this can cause a problem, in that the boot PROM
monitor may display its output on this additional card; however the
linux kernel boot messages may then be directed to the original on
board framebuffer, leaving <emphasis>no</emphasis> error messages on
the screen, with the machine apparently stuck loading the RAMdisk.

</para><para>

To avoid this problem, connect the monitor (if required) to the video
card in the lowest numbered SBUS slot (on motherboard card counts 
as below external slots).  Alternatively it is possible to use a serial
console.

</para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
