<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 11573  -->

 <sect1 id="install-overview">
 <!--<title>Overview of the Installation Process</title>  -->
 <title>Visione di insieme del processo di installazione</title> 
<para>

Prima di tutto, una nota sulla reinstallazione. Con Debian, una circostanza in
cui sia necessaria una reistallazione completa del sistema &egrave; rara; 
forse la rottura fisica del disco rigido pu&ograve; il caso pi&ugrave; comune.
<!--
First, just a note about re-installations. With Debian, a
circumstance that will require a complete re-installation of your
system is very rare; perhaps mechanical failure of the hard disk would
be the most common case. 
-->
</para><para>

Molti sistemi opertivi comuni hanno bisogno di un'installazione completa per
funzionare quando si verifica un guasto importante o per aggiornare a una 
nuova versione. Anche se un'installazione completa non richiesta spesso i
programmi che si usano di pi&ugrave; devono essere reinstallati per
funzionare correttamente con il nuovo OS.
<!--
Many common operating systems may require a complete installation to
be performed when critical failures take place or for upgrades to new
OS versions. Even if a completely new installation isn't required,
often the programs you use must be re-installed to operate properly in
the new OS.
-->
</para><para>

Sotto &debian;, &egrave; molto probabile che il vostro OS si possa riparare
piuttosto che rimpiazzarlo se qualcosa va storto. Gli aggiornamenti non
implicano mai una reinstallazione completa; si pu&ograve; sempre aggiornare.
E i programmi sono quasi sempre compatibili con le versioni successive
del sistema operativo. Se una nuova versione di un programma richiede
nuovo software di support, il sistema di gestione dei pacchetti di Debian
assicura che tutti i software necessari siano automaticamente indentificati
e instalalti. Il punto &egrave;, molto sforzo &egrave; stato posto
nell'evitare la necessit&agrave; di reinstallare, quindi ci si pensi
come l'ultima risorsa. Il programma di installazione
 <emphasis>non</emphasis> &egrave; progettato per reinstallare su un
 sistema operativo esistente.

<!-- Under &debian;, it is much more likely that your OS can be repaired
rather than replaced if things go wrong. Upgrades never require a
wholesale installation; you can always upgrade in-place. And the
programs are almost always compatible with successive OS releases.  If
a new program version requires newer supporting software, the Debian
packaging system ensures that all the necessary software is
automatically identified and installed. The point is, much effort has
been put into avoiding the need for re-installation, so think of it as
your very last option. The installer is <emphasis>not</emphasis>
designed to re-install over an existing system. -->

</para><para>

Di seguito la road map per i passi da seguire durante il processo di
installazione.

<!-- Here's a road map for the steps you will take during the installation
process. 
 -->
</para>

<orderedlist> 
<listitem><para>

Raccogliete informazioni sul vostro computer e tutta la documentazione

Gather information about your computer and any needed documentation,
before starting the installation.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Back up any existing data or documents on the hard disk where you
plan to install. 

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Create partition-able space for Debian on your hard disk.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Locate and/or download the installer software and any specialized
driver files your machine requires (except Debian CD users).

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Set up boot tapes/floppies/USB sticks, or place boot files (most Debian
CD users can boot from one of the CDs).

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Boot the installation system.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Select installation language.

</para></listitem>
<listitem arch="not-s390"><para>

Activate the ethernet network connection, if available.

</para></listitem>

<listitem arch="s390"><para>

Configure one network interface.

</para></listitem>
<listitem arch="s390"><para>

Open a telnet connection to the new system.

</para></listitem>
<listitem arch="s390"><para>

Attach one or more DASDs (Direct Access Storage Device).

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>

Create and mount the partitions on which Debian will be installed.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Watch the automatic download/install/setup of the 
<firstterm>base system</firstterm>.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Install a <firstterm>boot loader</firstterm>
which can start up &debian; and/or your existing system.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Load the newly installed system for the first time, and make some
initial system settings.

</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>

Install additional software (<firstterm>tasks</firstterm>
and/or <firstterm>packages</firstterm>), at your discretion.

</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>

If you have problems during the installation, it helps to know which
packages are involved in which steps. Introducing the leading software
actors in this installation drama:

</para><para>

The installer software, <classname>debian-installer</classname>, is
the primary concern of this manual. She directs the
architecture-specific partitioning program, installs the linux kernel,
and then supervises <classname>modconf</classname> to load specific
hardware drivers, <classname>dhclient</classname> to set up the
network connection, <classname>debootstrap</classname> to install the
base system packages, and &boot-loader-installer;, the boot loader
installer. Many more actors play smaller parts in this process, but
<classname>debian-installer</classname> has completed her task when
you load the new system for the first time.

</para><para>

Upon loading the new base system, <classname>base-config</classname>
supervises adding users, setting a time zone, and setting up the
package installation system. It then offers to launch
<classname>tasksel</classname> which will install large groups
of related programs, and in turn <classname>aptitude</classname> which
allows you to choose individual software packages.

</para><para>

When <classname>debian-installer</classname> finishes, before the
first system load, you have only a very basic command line driven
system. The graphical interface which displays windows on your monitor
will not be installed unless you select it during the final steps,
with either <classname>tasksel</classname> or
<classname>aptitude</classname>.  It's optional because many &debian;
systems are servers which don't really have any need for a graphical
user interface to do their job.

</para><para>

Just be aware that the X system is completely separate from
<classname>debian-installer</classname>, and in fact is much more
complicated. Installation and trouble shooting of the X window
installation is not within the scope of this manual.

</para>
 </sect1>

