<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

   <sect3 id="kbd-chooser">
   <title>Choosing a Keyboard</title>

<para>

Keyboards are often tailored to the characters used in a language.
Select a layout that conforms to the keyboard you are using, or
select something close if the keyboard layout you want
isn't represented. Once the system installation is complete, you'll be
able to select a keyboard layout from a wider range of choices (run
<command>kbdconfig</command> as root after you have completed the
installation).

</para><para>

Move the highlight to the keyboard selection you desire and press
&enterkey;.  Use the arrow keys to move the highlight &mdash; they are
in the same place in all national language keyboard layouts, so they
are independent of the keyboard configuration. An 'extended' keyboard
is one with <keycap>F1</keycap> through <keycap>F10</keycap> keys
along the top row.

</para><para arch="mipsel">

On DECstations there is currently no loadable keymap available,
so you have to skip the keyboard selection and keep the default
kernel keymap (LK201 US). This may change in the future as it
depends on further Linux/MIPS kernel development.

</para><para arch="powerpc">

There are two keyboard layouts for US keyboards; the qwerty/mac-usb-us
(Apple USB) layout will place the Alt function on the
<keycap>Command/Apple</keycap> key (in the keyboard position next to
the <keycap>space</keycap> key similar to <keycap>Alt</keycap> on
PC keyboards), while the qwerty/us (Standard) layout will place the
Alt function on the <keycap>Option</keycap> key (engraved with 'alt'
on most Mac keyboards). In other respects the two layouts are similar.

</para>

<note arch="sparc"><para>

If you are installing on a system that has a Sun USB keyboard and have
booted the installer with the default 2.4 kernel, the keyboard will not
be identified correctly by the installation system. The installer will show
you a list of Sun type keymaps to choose from, but selecting one of these
will result in a non-working keyboard. If you are installing with the 2.6
kernel, there is no problem.

</para><para>

To get a working keyboard, you should boot the installer with parameter
<userinput>debconf/priority=medium</userinput>. When you get to keyboard
selection<footnote>

<para>
If you are installing at default priority you should use the <userinput>Go
Back</userinput> button to return to the installer menu when you are shown
the list of Sun type keymaps.
</para>

</footnote>, choose <quote>No keyboard to configure</quote> if you have a
keyboard with an American (US) layout, or choose <quote>USB keyboard</quote>
if you have a keyboard with a localized layout. Selecting <quote>No keyboard
to configure</quote> will leave the kernel keymap in place, which is correct
for US keyboards.

</para></note>
   </sect3>
