<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

   <sect3 id="netcfg"><title>Configuring Network</title>
<para>

As you enter this step, if the system detects that you have more than
one network device, you'll be asked to choose which device will be
your <emphasis>primary</emphasis> network interface, i.e. the one
which you want to use for installation. The other interfaces won't be
configured at this time. You may configure additional interfaces after
installation is complete; see the <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>interfaces</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> man page.

</para><para>

By default, &d-i; tries to configure your computer's network
automatically via DHCP. If DHCP probe succeeds, you are done. If the
probe fails, it may be caused by many factors ranging from unplugged
network cable, to a misconfigured DHCP setup. Or maybe you don't have
DHCP server in your local network at all.  For further explanation
check the error messages on the third console.  In any case, you will
be asked, if you want to retry, or if you want to perform manual
setup. DHCP servers are sometimes really slow in their responses, so
if you are sure everything is in place, try again.

</para><para>

The manual network setup in turn asks you number of questions about
your network, notably
<computeroutput>IP address</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>Netmask</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>Gateway</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>Name server addresses</computeroutput>, and a
<computeroutput>Hostname</computeroutput>.
Moreover, if you have a wireless network interface, you will be asked
to provide your <computeroutput>Wireless ESSID</computeroutput> and
a <computeroutput>WEP key</computeroutput>.  Fill in the answers from
<xref linkend="needed-info"/>.

</para><note><para>

Some technical details you might, or might not, find handy: the
program assumes the network IP address is the bitwise-AND of your
system's IP address and your netmask. It will guess the broadcast
address is the bitwise OR of your system's IP address with the bitwise
negation of the netmask. It will also guess your gateway.  If you
can't find any of these answers, use the system's guesses &mdash; you
can change them once the system has been installed, if necessary, by
editing <filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename>.  Alternatively,
you can install <classname>etherconf</classname>, which will step you
through your network setup.

</para></note>

   </sect3>
