<!-- <chapter id="translators-level4"><title>Translating &d-i; - Level 4</title> -->

<sect1 id="translators-level4">
<title>
Level 4
</title>

<sect2>
<title>
Contents
</title>

<para>
The level 4 of translations groups together the translations of
programs which may output messages to the screen but do not input users.
</para>

<para>All internationalized packages which output messages to the screen
during first and second stage are considered part of the level 4 of
&d-i; localization.
</para>

<para>This includes the following Debian packages:

	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  debconf (program)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  dpkg
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  apt
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
</para>
		  
<para>
<classname>dpkg</classname> and <classname>apt</classname> are very often used during the
whole life of a Debian system, so having them translated, though very
tedious, is a must-have for a good localized system.
</para>

<para>
<classname>discover1</classname> and <classname>debconf</classname>
outputs messages to the console during &d-i; processes.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
debconf (program)
</title>

<sect3>
<title>
Package description
</title>

<para>
The <command>debconf</command> program is the software which is used
for user interaction during Debian packages configuration step. All
Debian packages should use <command>debconf</command> when they need
user input for installation-time configuration.
</para>

<para>
<command>debconf</command> may output information to the screen: this
is why the program translation is included in &d-i; fourth level of
translation.
</para>

<para>
<classname>Debconf</classname> also prompts users with questions when
installed. However, during a complete &d-i; run, these questions are
pre-answered with the similar questions from the
<classname>cdebconf</classname> package (which is part of level 1). As
a consequence, the translation of these questions is only part of level
5.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Files location and access methods
</title>

<para>
The package uses a <acronym>SVN</acronym> repository. Commit access may be requested to
the &i18n-coords;. However, as the translatable parts do not change
very often, getting commit access is not highly useful.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<acronym>SVN</acronym> access: &svn-debconf;, <filename>src/debconf/po</filename> directory (anonymous)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<acronym>HTTP</acronym> access: 
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
          <ulink url="&url-level4-pot;/debconf_po.pot">&url-level4-pot;/debconf_po.pot</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
&url-level4-po;/debconf_po_&language;.po
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Updating/Adding translations
</title>

<para>
Translations should be reported as bugs against the <classname>debconf</classname> package or committed directly to the <acronym>SVN</acronym> repository.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Specific recommendations
</title>

<para>
N/A
</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
dpkg
</title>

<sect3>
<title>
Package description
</title>

<para>
The <classname>dpkg</classname> program is a low level program which
installs and removes Debian packages.
</para>

<para>Including it in &d-i; level 4 of translation is an extension of
the scope of &d-i; localization process. <classname>dpkg</classname>
does not output very often during a base system install, but is very
likely to be used further, either directly invoked by the system
administrator or from another program such as
<classname>aptitude</classname>, <classname>apt</classname>, or <classname>dselect</classname>
(<classname>dselect</classname> translations are part of
<classname>dpkg</classname> translations).
</para>

<para><classname>dpkg</classname> full translation is a huge work
because there are hundreds of strings in the POT file. Most of these
strings are very short strings and most of them are hard-formatted
because they are used from a command-line program.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Files location and access methods
</title>

<para>
This package is a <quote>regular</quote> Debian package. The
package maintenance team uses a SVN repository to maintain
it. 
</para>

<para>
As arch-style repositories are somewhat complicated to setup, all localization of <classname>dpkg</classname> is handled by one of the &i18n-coords;.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<acronym>SVN</acronym> access: &svn-dpkg;, <filename>po</filename> directory (anonymous)
</para>
</listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <acronym>HTTP</acronym> access: 
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <ulink url="&url-level4-pot;/dpkg_po.pot">&url-level4-pot;/dpkg_po.pot</ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          &url-level4-po;/dpkg_po_&language;.po
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Updating/Adding translations
</title>

<para>
Translations should be reported as bugs against the
<classname>dpkg</classname> package or commited directly to the SVN repository. Don't forget updating the <classname>po/Changelog</classname> and <classname>debian/changelog</classname> files if you update the translations yourself by getting SVN commit access.

</para>

<para>
If reported as a bug, the translation will be committed quickly by the dpkg localization
maintainer.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Specific recommendations
</title>

<para>
Undoubtfully, <classname>dpkg</classname> translation
requires a good knowledge of the Debian package management system as
well as some good experience of command-line programs translation.
</para>

<para>
The developers have put comments targeted at translators for some
strings. Translators should read and follow them carefully.
</para>

<para>
The <classname>po/</classname> directory contains a file named <classname>Changelog</classname>. Translators must update this file when updating translations, as well as the <classname>debian/changelog</classname> file.
</para>

<para>
Adding a new language also requires translators to add it to the
<classname>po/LINGUAS</classname> file. Otherwise, the new translation
will not be used.
</para>

<para>
<classname>dpkg</classname> man pages can also be translated, using
gettext files. Please look into the <classname>man/</classname>
directory in SVN for examples.
</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
apt
</title>

<sect3>
<title>
Package description
</title>

<para>
The <classname>apt</classname> program handles installation and
removal of Debian packages from packages <emphasis>sources</emphasis>
such as Debian <acronym>HTTP</acronym>/FTP mirrors, Debian CD's, third party CD's or
repositories, or local files.
</para>

<para>
Including it in &d-i; level 4 of translation is an extension of the
scope of &d-i; localization process. <classname>apt</classname> does not output
very often during a base system install, but is very likely to be used
further.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Files location and access methods
</title>

<para>
This package is a <quote>regular</quote> Debian package. The
package maintenance team uses arch repositories to maintain
it. 
</para>

<para>
As arch-style repositories are somewhat complicated to setup, all
localization of <classname>apt</classname> is handled by one of the
&i18n-coords;.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <acronym>HTTP</acronym> access: 
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <ulink url="&url-level4-pot;/apt_po.pot">&url-level4-pot;/apt_po.pot</ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          &url-level4-po;/apt_po_&language;.po
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Updating/Adding translations
</title>

<para>
Translations should be reported as bugs against the
<classname>apt</classname> package.
</para>

<para>
The translation will be committed quickly by the dpkg localization
maintainer. This will not appear immediately on status pages because
<classname>apt</classname> development is handled in
<quote>arch</quote> repositories which are not easily handled by the
scripts which generate the status pages.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Specific recommendations
</title>

<para><classname>apt</classname> full translation is a huge work because there are hundreds of
strings in the POT file. Most of these strings are short strings
and most of them are hard-formatted because they are outputted
during the use of a command-line program.
</para>

<para>
Similarly to <classname>dpkg</classname>, <classname>apt</classname>
translation requires a good knowledge of the Debian package management
system as well as some good experience of command-line programs
translation.
</para>

<para>
The developers have put comments targeted at translators for some
strings. Translators should read them carefully. Some of them are
<emphasis>very</emphasis> important.
</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>



</sect1>

<!-- </chapter> -->
