<!-- <chapter id="translators-level1"><title>Translating &d-i; - Level 1</title> -->

<sect1 id="translators-level1">
<title>
Level 1
</title>

<sect2>
<title>
Contents
</title>

<para>
Level 1 consists of all "core" &d-i; packages, i.e. all packages with
translatable material in the &d-i; development tree. These packages
are used during the installation "first stage".
</para>

<para>
In &d-i; jargon, the <emphasis>first stage</emphasis> is the part of
&d-i; which occurs from the initial boot up to the first (and only)
reboot of the system. All user interactions screens shown to users
during this stage are part of the first level for l10n.
</para>

<para>
Most parts of the translatable material is spread over core &d-i;
packages. The package development is handled in the main &d-i;
Subversion (<acronym>SVN</acronym>) repository.
</para>

<para>
Some material (country names and keyboard maps names) are handled in
non core &d-i; packages. This material will be part of the level 2 of
translations.
</para>

<para>
In order to make the translators work easy and simple, all
translatable strings are assembled in a single file. Translators must
work on this file and not on the various files dispersed in the &d-i;
development tree (these files are automatically generated).
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Files location and access methods
</title>

<para>
Translators should remember that using <acronym>SVN</acronym> is strongly encouraged as
this is the only way for them to commit their own translations.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <acronym>SVN</acronym> access: &svn-level1;
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <acronym>HTTP</acronym> access: &url-level1;
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          &url-level1-pot-link;
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          &url-level1-po-link;
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>


<para>
To begin the translation work for level 1, translators should copy the
<filename>packages/po/template.pot</filename> to
<filename>&language;.po</filename> (where &language; is
the ISO-639 code of the language, see <xref
linkend="language-codes"/>) and complete this file.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Updating/Adding translations
</title>

<para>
Translation updates should be done by direct commits to the &d-i; <acronym>SVN</acronym>
repository (see <xref linkend="svn-basics"/> for details about <acronym>SVN</acronym>
use). In case this is absolutely impossible, these updates can be sent
as bug reports against the <classname>debian-installer</classname>
package (see <xref linkend="bug-reports"/> for details).
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>
Specific recommendations
</title>

<para>
The &d-i; core file uses hundreds of strings which represent the content
of the screens which are or may be shown to &d-i; users during the
installation process.
</para>

<para>
Several of these strings are commented with indications or hints for
translators.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>
Limited length strings
</title>
<para>
Several strings are limited in length to 65 columns. This means they
should not exceed 65 characters for single-width character languages
and 32 characters for double-width character languages such as CJK
(Chinese/Japanese/Korean) and similar languages.
</para>

<para>
This constraint may be checked by the <filename>scripts/l10n/choices-check.pl</filename> script from the &d-i; development tree:
</para>

<para>
<command>scripts/l10n/choices-check.pl &lt; packages/po/&language;.po</command>
</para>

<para>
This script will output the offending line(s) number(s) as well as the number of characters in this/these line(s).
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
"Choose language" menu entry
</title>

<para>
This entry is the language selection screen entry for each
language. Translators can translate it but they should keep "Choose
language" in English as an alternative so that users mistakenly
choosing a language can still find the appropriate entry to change it
back to their own language.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Variable names
</title>

<para>
Many places in &d-i; use variables (e.g. "${LOCALE} is currently not
supported in Debian"). The variable names should <emphasis>not be
translated</emphasis> and be kept inside braces prepended by the
dollar sign in the translation.
</para>

<para>
This constraint is checked by the spell checking scripts which report
these errors separately (see <xref linkend="spellchecking"/> for
details about the spell checking scripts).
</para>

<para>
Advanced translation software such as <command>kbabel</command> are
able to visually display such errors and warn about them before saving
files.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Default mirror country
</title>

<para>
A special string from the <classname>choose-mirror</classname> package
is intended to setup the default Debian archive mirror country,
depending on the language. Translators should put there the ISO-3166
code of the country to be used as default, most often their own
country name, or the country their language is spoken in. For
instance, the Brazilian Portuguese translator will use "BR" as
translation there, as this is the ISO-3166 code for Brazil.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>
Partman entries
</title>

<para>
A few entries in the <classname>partman</classname> are limited to 8
symbols only. Translators must be VERY careful about not exceeding
this value, otherwise, the display in the
<classname>partman</classname> screens will be badly broken.
</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- </chapter> -->
