<chapter id="translators"><title>For translators: translating &d-i;</title>

<sect1>
<title>
The &d-i; five levels of translation
</title>

<para>
The Debian Installer translator process has been divided into several
<emphasis>levels</emphasis> which represent steps towards a complete translation of the
installer for the Debian GNU/Linux distribution.
</para>

<para>Translators should work in the order detailed below, level by
level. Inside each level, complete the steps in the described
order. This order is related to the degree of <emphasis>importance</emphasis> of each
material needing translation.
</para>

<para>The following parts of this chapter will give details and
context about each level components, instructions for
getting the material which needs translations as well as sending back
the translated material.
</para>

<para>
Translators should read them carefully, even if they already worked on
Debian translations.
</para>

<para>
Due to the granularity of Debian work and more specifically the
packages system, translators may find differences between the various packages
a bit annoying (some use <acronym>SVN</acronym>, some others <acronym>CVS</acronym>, some other no
repository at all...). This is a consequence of the current work organization
in Debian. 
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>
Levels summary
</title>

<para>
This section is intended to give translators a general idea of each
level contents.
</para>

	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 1: all core &d-i; packages;
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 2: all non core &d-i; material involved for
		user interaction screens during a <emphasis>default
		priority</emphasis> installation of a Debian base
		system with default choices;
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 3: all non-core &d-i; material involved for
		user interaction screens during any type of
		installation of a Debian base system. This will
		include rarely used packages and packages which may
		display their screens under certain circumstances;
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 4: all packages which may display messages to the screen
		during any type of installation of a Debian base system;
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		level 5: all packages including translatable material used for user interaction during a default priority desktop system installation.
		</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>


</sect1>

&translators-level1.xml;
&translators-level2.xml;
&translators-level3.xml;
&translators-level4.xml;
&translators-level5.xml;
&string-freezes.xml;

</chapter>
