<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 16340 untranslated -->

<chapter id="boot-new">
 <title>Booting Into Your New Debian System</title>

 <sect1 id="base-boot"><title>The Moment of Truth</title>
<para>

Your system's first boot on its own power is what electrical engineers
call the <quote>smoke test</quote>.

</para><para arch="s390">

Select the <guimenuitem>Reboot the System</guimenuitem> menu item
which will halt the system
because rebooting is not supported on &arch-title; in this case. You
then need to IPL GNU/Linux from the DASD which you selected for the
root filesystem during the first steps of the installation.

</para><para>

If you are booting directly into Debian, and the system doesn't start
up, either use your original installation boot media, or insert the
custom boot floppy if you have one, and reset your system.  This way,
you will probably need to add some boot arguments like
<userinput>root=<replaceable>root</replaceable></userinput>, where
<replaceable>root</replaceable> is your root partition, such as
<filename>/dev/sda1</filename>.

</para>

  <sect2 arch="m68k"><title>VME6000 Booting</title>
<para>

If you have just performed a diskless install on a BVM or Motorola
VMEbus machine: once the system has loaded the
<command>tftplilo</command> program from the TFTP server, from the
<prompt>LILO Boot:</prompt> prompt enter one of:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>

<userinput>b6000</userinput> followed by &enterkey;
to boot a BVME4000/6000

</para></listitem><listitem><para>

<userinput>b162</userinput> followed by &enterkey;
to boot an MVME162

</para></listitem><listitem><para>

<userinput>b167</userinput> followed by &enterkey;
to boot an MVME166/167

</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>

   </sect2>

  <sect2 arch="m68k"><title>Macintosh Booting</title>

<para>

Go to the directory containing the installation files and start up the
<command>Penguin</command> booter, holding down the
<keycap>command</keycap> key.  Go to the
<userinput>Settings</userinput> dialogue (<keycombo>
<keycap>command</keycap> <keycap>T</keycap> </keycombo>), and locate
the kernel options line which should look like
<userinput>root=/dev/ram video=font:VGA8x16</userinput> or similar.

</para><para>

You need to change the entry to
<userinput>root=/dev/<replaceable>yyyy</replaceable></userinput>.
Replace the <replaceable>yyyy</replaceable> with the Linux name of the
partition onto which you installed the system
(e.g. <filename>/dev/sda1</filename>); you wrote this down earlier.
The <userinput>video=font:VGA8x8</userinput> is recommended especially
for users with tiny screens. The kernel would pick a prettier (6x11)
font but the console driver for this font can hang the machine, so
using 8x16 or 8x8 is safer at this stage.  You can change this at any
time.

</para><para>

If you don't want to start GNU/Linux immediately each time you start,
uncheck the <userinput>Auto Boot</userinput> option. Save your
settings in the <filename>Prefs</filename> file using the
<userinput>Save Settings As Default</userinput> option.

</para><para>

Now select <userinput>Boot Now</userinput> (<keycombo>
<keycap>command</keycap> <keycap>B</keycap> </keycombo>) to start your
freshly installed GNU/Linux instead of the RAMdisk installer system.

</para><para>

Debian should boot, and you should see the same messages as
when you first booted the installation system, followed by some new
messages. 

</para>
   </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="powerpc"><title>OldWorld PowerMacs</title>
<para>

If the machine fails to boot after completing the installation, and
stops with a <prompt>boot:</prompt> prompt, try typing
<userinput>Linux</userinput> followed by &enterkey;. (The default boot
configuration in <filename>quik.conf</filename> is labeled Linux). The
labels defined in <filename>quik.conf</filename> will be displayed if
you press the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key at the <prompt>boot:</prompt>
prompt. You can also try booting back into the installer, and editing
the <filename>/target/etc/quik.conf</filename> placed there by the
<guimenuitem>Install <command>Quik</command> on a Hard
Disk</guimenuitem> step. Clues for dealing with
<command>quik</command> are available at <ulink
url="&url-powerpc-quik-faq;"></ulink>.

</para><para>

To boot back into MacOS without resetting the nvram, type
<userinput>bye</userinput> at the Open Firmware prompt (assuming MacOS
has not been removed from the machine). To obtain an OpenFirmware
prompt, hold down the <keycombo> <keycap>command</keycap>
<keycap>option</keycap> <keycap>o</keycap> <keycap>f</keycap>
</keycombo> keys while cold booting the machine. If you need to reset
the OpenFirmware nvram changes to the MacOS default in order to boot
back to MacOS, hold down the <keycombo> <keycap>command</keycap>
<keycap>option</keycap> <keycap>p</keycap> <keycap>r</keycap>
</keycombo> keys while cold booting the machine.

</para><para>

If you use <command>BootX</command> to boot into the installed system,
just select your desired kernel in the <filename>Linux
Kernels</filename> folder, un-choose the ramdisk option, and add
a root device corresponding to your installation;
e.g. <userinput>/dev/hda8</userinput>.

</para>
   </sect2>


  <sect2 arch="powerpc"><title>NewWorld PowerMacs</title>
<para>

On G4 machines and iBooks, you can hold down the
<keycap>option</keycap> key and get a graphical screen with a button
for each bootable OS, &debian; will be a button with a small penguin
icon.

</para><para>

If you kept MacOS and at some point it changes the OpenFirmware
<envar>boot-device</envar> variable you should reset OpenFirmware to
its default configuration.  To do this hold down the <keycombo>
<keycap>command</keycap> <keycap>option</keycap> <keycap>p</keycap>
<keycap>r</keycap> </keycombo> keys while cold booting the machine.

</para><para>

The labels defined in <filename>yaboot.conf</filename> will be
displayed if you press the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key at the
<prompt>boot:</prompt> prompt.

</para><para>

Resetting OpenFirmware on G3 or G4 hardware will cause it to boot
&debian; by default (if you correctly partitioned and placed the
Apple_Bootstrap partition first).  If you have &debian; on a SCSI disk
and MacOS on an IDE disk this may not work and you will have to enter
OpenFirmware and set the <envar>boot-device</envar> variable,
<command>ybin</command> normally does this automatically.

</para><para>

After you boot &debian; for the first time you can add any additional
options you desire (such as dual boot options) to
<filename>/etc/yaboot.conf</filename> and run <command>ybin</command>
to update your boot partition with the changed configuration.  Please
read the <ulink url="&url-powerpc-yaboot-faq;">yaboot HOWTO</ulink>
for more information.

</para>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="base-config">
 <title>Debian Post-Boot (Base) Configuration</title>

<para>

After booting, you will be prompted to complete the configuration of
your basic system, and then to select what additional packages you
wish to install.  The application which guides you through this
process is called <classname>base-config</classname>. Its concept is
very similar to the &d-i; from the first stage.  Indeed,
<classname>base-config</classname> consists of a number of specialized
components, where each component handles one configuration task,
contains <quote>hidden menu in the background</quote> and also uses
the same navigation system.

</para><para>

If you wish to re-run the <classname>base-config</classname> at any
point after installation is complete, as root run
<userinput>base-config</userinput>.

</para>

&module-bc-timezone.xml;
&module-bc-shadow.xml;
&module-bc-ppp.xml;
&module-bc-apt.xml;
&module-bc-packages.xml;
&module-bc-install.xml;
&module-bc-mta.xml;

 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="login">
 <title>Log In</title>

<para>

After you've installed packages, you'll be presented with the login
prompt.  Log in using the personal login and password you
selected. Your system is now ready to use.

</para><para>

If you are a new user, you may want to explore the documentation which
is already installed on your system as you start to use it. There are
currently several documentation systems, work is proceeding on
integrating the different types of documentation. Here are a few
starting points.

</para><para>

Documentation accompanying programs you have installed is in
<filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename>, under a subdirectory named after
the program.  For example, the APT User's Guide for using
<command>apt</command> to install other programs on your system, is
located in
<filename>/usr/share/doc/apt/guide.html/index.html</filename>.

</para><para>

 
In addition, there are some special folders within the
<filename>/usr/share/doc/</filename> hierarchy. Linux HOWTOs are
installed in <emphasis>.gz</emphasis> format, in
<filename>/usr/share/doc/HOWTO/en-txt/</filename> and
<filename>/usr/share/doc/HOWTO/en-txt/mini/</filename>. The
<filename>/usr/share/doc/HTML/index.html</filename> contains
browse-able indexes of documentation installed by
<command>dhelp</command>.

</para><para>

One easy way to view these documents is to <userinput>cd
/usr/share/doc/</userinput>, and type <userinput>lynx</userinput>
followed by a space and a dot (the dot stands for the current
directory).

</para><para>

You can also type <userinput>info
<replaceable>command</replaceable></userinput> or <userinput>man
<replaceable>command</replaceable></userinput> to see documentation on
most commands available at the command prompt. Typing
<userinput>help</userinput> will display help on shell commands. And
typing a command followed by <userinput>--help</userinput> will
usually display a short summary of the command's usage. If a command's
results scroll past the top of the screen, type <userinput>|
more</userinput> after the command to cause the results to pause
before scrolling past the top of the screen. To see a list of all
commands available which begin with a certain letter, type the letter
and then two tabs.

</para><para>

For a more complete introduction to Debian and GNU/Linux, see
<filename>/usr/share/doc/debian-guide/html/noframes/index.html</filename>.

</para>

 </sect1>
</chapter>
