<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 11648 untranslated -->


  <sect2 arch="powerpc"><title>Partitioning Newer PowerMacs</title>
<para>

If you are installing onto a NewWorld PowerMac you must create a
special bootstrap partition to hold the boot loader. The size of this
partition must be 800KB and its partition type must be
<emphasis>Apple_Bootstrap</emphasis>.  If the bootstrap partition is
not created with the <emphasis>Apple_Bootstrap</emphasis> type your
machine cannot be made bootable from the hard disk.  This partition
can easily be created in <command>mac-fdisk</command> using the
<userinput>b</userinput> command.

</para><para>

The special partition type Apple_Bootstrap is required to prevent
MacOS from mounting and damaging the bootstrap partition, as there are
special modifications made to it in order for OpenFirmware to boot it
automatically.

</para><para>

Note that the bootstrap partition is only meant to hold 3 very small
files: the <command>yaboot</command> binary, its configuration
<filename>yaboot.conf</filename>, and a first stage OpenFirmware
loader <command>ofboot.b</command>.  It need not and must not be
mounted on your file system nor have kernels or anything else copied
to it. The <command>ybin</command> and <command>mkofboot</command>
utilities are used to manipulate this partition.

</para><para>

In order for OpenFirmware to automatically boot &debian; the bootstrap
partition should appear before other boot partitions on the disk,
especially MacOS boot partitions.  The bootstrap partition should be
the first one you create. However, if you add a bootstrap partition
later, you can use <command>mac-fdisk</command>'s
<userinput>r</userinput> command to reorder the partition map so the
bootstrap partition comes right after the map (which is always
partition 1). It's the logical map order, not the physical address
order, that counts.

</para><para>

Apple disks normally have several small driver partitions. If you
intend to dual boot your machine with MacOSX, you should retain these
partitions and a small HFS partition (800k is the minimum size). That
is because MacOSX, on every boot, offers to initialize any disks which do
not have active MacOS partitions and driver partitions.

</para>
  </sect2>