<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- original version: 23579 untranslated -->


  <sect2 arch="alpha"><title>Partitioning in Tru64 UNIX</title>
<para>

Tru64 UNIX, formerly known as Digital UNIX, which is in turn formerly
known as OSF/1, uses the partitioning scheme similar to the BSD `disk
label', which allows for up to eight partitions per disk drive.  The
partitions are numbered `1' through to `8' in
Linux and ``lettered'' `a' through to `h' in UNIX.
Linux kernels 2.2 and higher always correspond `1' to
`a', `2' to `b' and so on.  For
example, <filename>rz0e</filename> in Tru64 UNIX would most likely be called
<filename>sda5</filename> in Linux.

</para><para>

Partitions in a Tru64 disk label may overlap.  Moreover, if this disk
will be used from Tru64, the `c' partition is required to span the
entire disk (thus overlapping all other non-empty partitions).  Under
Linux this makes <filename>sda3</filename> identical to
<filename>sda</filename> (<filename>sdb3</filename> to
<filename>sdb</filename>, if present, and so on).  However, the partman
partitioning tool used by &d-i; cannot handle overlapping partitions at
present.  As a result, it is currently not recommended to share disks
between Tru64 and Debian.  Partitions on Tru64 disks can be mounted
under Debian after installation has been completed.

</para><para>

Another conventional requirement is for the `a' partition to start from
the beginning of the disk, so that it always includes the boot block
with the disk label. If you intend to boot Debian from that disk, you
need to size it at least 2MB to fit aboot and perhaps a kernel.
Note that this partition is only required for compatibility; you must
not put a file system onto it, or you'll destroy data.

</para><para>

It is possible, and indeed quite reasonable, to share a swap partition
between UNIX and Linux.  In this case it will be needed to do a
<command>mkswap</command> on that partition every time the system is rebooted
from UNIX into Linux, as UNIX will damage the swap signature.  You may
want to run <command>mkswap</command> from the Linux start-up scripts before
adding swap space with <command>swapon -a</command>.

</para><para>

If you want to mount UNIX partitions under Linux, note that Digital UNIX
can use two different file system types, UFS and AdvFS, of which Linux
only understands the former.

</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 arch="alpha"><title>Partitioning in Windows NT</title>

<para>

Windows NT uses the PC-style partition table.  If you are manipulating
existing FAT or NTFS partitions, it is recommended that you use the
native Windows NT tools (or, more conveniently, you can also
repartition your disk from the AlphaBIOS setup menu).  Otherwise, it
is not really necessary to partition from Windows; the Linux
partitioning tools will generally do a better job.  Note that when you
run NT, the Disk Administrator may offer you to write a ``harmless
signature'' on non-Windows disks if you have any.  <emphasis>Never</emphasis>
let it do that, as this signature will destroy the partition
information.

</para><para>

If you plan to boot Linux from an ARC/AlphaBIOS/ARCSBIOS console, you
will need a (small) FAT partition for MILO.  5 Mb is quite
sufficient.  If Windows NT is installed, its 6 Mb bootstrap partition
can be employed for this purpose.  Debian &releasename; does not support
installing MILO.  If you already have MILO installed on your system, or
install MILO from other media, Debian can still be booted from ARC.

</para>
  </sect2>
