<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id: preface.xml 18951 2004-08-10 08:10:02Z rudy-guest $ -->

<bookinfo id="debian_installation_guide">
<title>Руководство по установке &debian; </title>

<abstract>
<para>В этом документе содержатся инструкции по установке системы &debian; &release; для архитектуры &arch-title; (<quote>&architecture;</quote>). В нем также есть ссылки на более подробные источники и информация о том, как получить максимум возможного из вашей новой системы Debian. </para>
</abstract>

<copyright>
 <year>2004
 <trademark class="copyright">
 </trademark>
 </year>
 <holder>Команда Debian Installer</holder>
</copyright>

<legalnotice>
<para>Это руководство может распространяться и/или модифицироваться согласно Стандартной Общественной лицензии GNU. Текст лицензии можно найти здесь: <xref linkend="appendix-gpl"/>. </para>
</legalnotice>
</bookinfo>

<preface>
 <title>Installing &debian; &release; For &architecture;</title>
<para>

We are delighted that you have decided to try Debian, and are
sure that you will find that Debian's GNU/Linux distribution is
unique. &debian; brings together high-quality free software
from around the world, integrating it into a coherent whole. We
believe that you will find that the result is truly more than the sum
of the parts.

</para><para>

We understand that many of you want to install Debian without reading this
manual, and the Debian installer is designed to make this possible. If you
don't have time to read the whole Installation Guide right now, we recommend
that you read the Installation Howto, which will walk you through the basic
installation process, and links to the manual for more advanced topics or
for when things go wrong. The Howto is in <xref linkend="installation-howto"/>.

</para><para>

With that said, we hope that you have the time to read most of this manual,
and doing so will lead to a more informed and likely more successful
installation experience.

</para>
</preface>
